<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise, written by an author of the communion of the Church of Rome, touching transubstantiation wherein is made appear, that according to the principles of that church, this doctrine cannot be an article of faith.</title>
            <title>Traitté d'un autheur de la communion romaine touchant la transsubstantiation. English</title>
            <author>Dufour de Longuerue, Louis, 1652-1733.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 236 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A36764</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2456</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R229806</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16350066</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16350066</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105312</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A36764)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105312)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1091:3, 2353:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise, written by an author of the communion of the Church of Rome, touching transubstantiation wherein is made appear, that according to the principles of that church, this doctrine cannot be an article of faith.</title>
                  <title>Traitté d'un autheur de la communion romaine touchant la transsubstantiation. English</title>
                  <author>Dufour de Longuerue, Louis, 1652-1733.</author>
                  <author>Wake, William, 1657-1737.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[9], 73, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Chiswell ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLXXXVII [1687]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of the author's Traitté d'un autheur de la communion romaine touchant la transsubstantiation.</note>
                  <note>Running title: A treatise of transubstantiation.</note>
                  <note>Translated by William Wake.</note>
                  <note>Second edition of same year has title: An historical treatise ...</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of originals in: Henry E. Huntington Library and William Andrews Clark Memorial Library.</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Transubstantiation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:105312:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105312:2"/>
            <p>Imprimatur.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Henricus Maurice R<hi rend="sup">mo</hi> P. D. Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>helmo Archiep. Cant. à Sacris.</signed>
               <date>Januarii 11. 1686.</date>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:105312:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TREATISE WRITTEN By an AUTHOR of the Communion of the CHURCH of <hi>ROME.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>TOUCHING <hi>Tranſubſtantiation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WHEREIN Is made appear, That according to the PRINCIPLES of That CHURCH, This DOCTRINE cannot be an ARTICLE of FAITH.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Chiſwell,</hi> at the <hi>Roſe</hi> and <hi>Crown</hi> in S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard. <abbr>MDCLXXXVII.</abbr>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:105312:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105312:3"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>IT is well known that there are in the Communion of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> a great many Learned Perſons, that do not approve of all which it teacheth, and that do earneſtly long for a Reformation, although they remain within its boſome. But it is no leſs true, that there's but very few, that have the courage to make their thoughts known, and 'tis no hard matter to gueſs at the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of it.</p>
            <p>In the laſt Age, one <hi>Picherel,</hi> and ſome others of great note, wrote ſolid Treatiſes on certain matters of Controverſie, and explain'd themſelves juſt as Proteſtants do now. And in the preſent, <hi>Monſieur de Marca</hi> did the ſame, on the Doctrine of the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> and <hi>Barnes,</hi> an Eminent <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedictine,</hi> on moſt of the principal Queſtions wherein Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants differ from the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> But as if every one feared ſuch uſage as Father <hi>Paolo,</hi> and poor <hi>Barnes</hi> found, for the Liberty they had taken, the works of theſe ſincere and learned Men, have almoſt always been ſuppreſt during their Life-time, and not ſuffer'd to come abroad till after their Deceaſe.</p>
            <p>It is therefore ſomething more than ordinary, to behold the Work of a Perſon now living, and of the Communion of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> that dares ſhew the like affection for the Reformation of his Church in the Doctrine of the
<pb facs="tcp:105312:4"/>
               <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> and that heartily wiſhes, the Biſhops and Clergy of <hi>France,</hi> would take it into their ſerious conſideration. This Perſon is conſiderable for his Quality, but much more for his great Learning. He was an intimate friend of the late <hi>Monſieur de Launoy's,</hi> a noted Divine of the Faculty of <hi>Paris,</hi> who mightily deſired to ſee a free Council, wherein Men might ſpeak their thoughts touching the Reforming of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church; and it plainly appears he was of the ſame judgment with this Eminent Perſon, touching the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Reader may reſt aſſured that the Author's Manuſcript Copy has been exactly follow'd in the Edition of this Work; which not only his Letters, now in our Hands, will juſtifie, but alſo the Original of theſe Papers, which he ſent to a Friend to be Printed.</p>
            <p>It is to be hoped the World will not take it ill, if the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of this Work be not more particularly deſcribed, which could not be done without expoſing him to the malice of thoſe who uſe all mann r of ways to deſtroy ſuch of their party, as do own the Truth. It nearly behoves the Biſhops and Clergy of <hi>France,</hi> to make ſome ſerious Reflections up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what the Author thought fit to repreſent to them concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Tranſubſtantiation.</hi> The ſame might have been ſaid to the other Articles of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> belief, which are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected by Proteſtants, as ſo many additions to the ancient Faith of the Primitive Chriſtians; which are impos'd upon Mens conſciences by the Clergy, by ſuch unheard-of ways, and that are ſo contrary to the nature of Religion. If ſuch Remonſtrances as theſe, are not of ſufficient force to make them change their proceedings againſt Proteſtants; they will at leaſt ſerve to ſhew their Injuſtice before Men, and will one day aggravate their condemnation before the Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal of God.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:105312:4"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <head>INTRODUCTION.</head>
               <item>THE Method propoſed by the Aſſembly of the Clergy of <hi>France</hi> to judge of Articles of Faith. <hi>Pag.</hi> 1</item>
               <item>This Method admitted by Proteſtants. 2</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> to be Examined by it. ib.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>PART I.</head>
               <item>THAT ſeveral of the Doctors of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> have confeſs'd that <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> is no ancient Doctrine. 3</item>
               <item>So <hi>Suarez.</hi> 3</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Scotus.</hi> ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>D'Alliaco.</hi> ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Card. Cuſa.</hi> ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Eraſmus.</hi> ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Alphonſus à Caſtro.</hi> 4</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tonſtal.</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Durham.</hi> ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Caſſander.</hi> ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ch. du Moulin.</hi> ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>J. Yribarne.</hi> ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Monſ. de Marca.</hi> ib.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>PART II. THAT the Ancients did not believe <hi>Tranſubſtantiation.</hi>
               </head>
               <pb facs="tcp:105312:5"/>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <head>Proved: In GENERAL.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Firſt,</hi> The <hi>Papiſts</hi> themſelves confeſs, that <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> is not expreſly mentioned nor taught in Scripture. 5</item>
                     <item>So, <hi>Scotus.</hi> ib.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ockham.</hi> ib.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Alphonſus de Caſtra.</hi> ib.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Gabriel Biel.</hi> ib.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Card. Cajetane.</hi> ib.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Secondly,</hi> That <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> comprehending infinite diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, we do not yet find that either the <hi>Jews</hi> or <hi>Gentiles</hi> have objected any thing to the Chriſtians in their diſputes againſt it. <hi>ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Not
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Trypho.</hi> ib.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Celſus.</hi> ib.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Julian.</hi> ib.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Who yet have traduced moſt of the Myſteries of our Religion. 7</item>
                     <item>Which plainly ſhews that <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> was not then known. <hi>ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <head>In PARTICULAR. <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> was not believed by any of the Fathers of the Church. This ſhewn in thoſe of the ſeveral Ages.</head>
                     <item>CENT. II.
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Juſtine Martyr.</hi> 8</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Irenaeus.</hi> 9</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Clemens Alexandr.</hi> 10</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Theodotus.</hi> ib.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>CENT. III.
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Tertullian.</hi> 11</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Origen.</hi> 13</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Cyprian.</hi> 15</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>CENT. IV.
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Euſtathius.</hi> 16</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Euſebius Caeſarienſis.</hi> ib.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Cyrillus Hieroſel.</hi> 17</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Macharius.</hi> ib.</item>
                           <item>S. <hi>Baſil.</hi> 18</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Ephraem.</hi> ib.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Epiphanius.</hi> 19</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Gregorius Naz.</hi> ib.</item>
                           <pb facs="tcp:105312:5"/>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Gregorius Nyſſen.</hi> 20</item>
                           <item>S. <hi>Ambroſe.</hi> 21</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Gaudentius.</hi> 22</item>
                           <item>S. <hi>Chryſoſtome.</hi> ib.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>CENT. V.
<list>
                           <item>S. <hi>Jerome.</hi> 26</item>
                           <item>S. <hi>Auguſtine.</hi> 27</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Theodoret.</hi> 37</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Arnobius</hi> Jun. 38</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Proſper.</hi> ib.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Heſychius.</hi> 39</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Procopius Gazens.</hi> ib.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>P. Gelaſius.</hi> 40</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>CENT. VI.
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Fulgentius.</hi> 41</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Ephrem de Conte.</hi> ib.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Facundus.</hi> ib.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Primaſius.</hi> 42</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>CENT. VII, VIII.
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Iſidorus Hiſpalenſis.</hi> 43</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Beda.</hi> 44</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Sedulius.</hi> ib.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Jo. Damaſcenus.</hi> ib.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Concil. Conſtantinop.</hi> 45</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Alcuinus.</hi> 46</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Carolus M.</hi> 47</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Officium Ambroſianum.</hi> ib.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Ordo Romanus</hi> ib.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>CENT. IX.
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Theodorus Studita.</hi> 48</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Ahyto.</hi> ib.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Theodulphus.</hi> 49</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Rabanus.</hi> 51</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Amalarius.</hi> 52</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Walafridus Strabo.</hi> 54</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Herribald.</hi> ib.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Trudegard.</hi> 55</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Ratramne.</hi> ib.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Jo. Erigena.</hi> 56</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Prudentius.</hi> 58</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Chriſtian Drutmar.</hi> ib.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Florus Diacon.</hi> 60</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>CENT. X.
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Alferic,</hi> A. B. <hi>Cant.</hi> 61</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Wolphinus.</hi> ib.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Saxon Homil.</hi> ib.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Fulcuinus.</hi> 62</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Herriger.</hi> ib.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Monaſt. Cluny.</hi> ib.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Ratherius.</hi> 63</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>CENT. XI.
<list>
                           <item>Auth. Life of S. <hi>Genulphe.</hi> 64</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Leuthericus.</hi> ib.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Fulbertus.</hi> ib.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Berno.</hi> 65</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Bruno.</hi> 66</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Gregory</hi> VII. P. ib.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Theophylact.</hi> 67</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Nicetas Pectoratus.</hi> ib.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Chronicon Malleac.</hi> ib.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>CENT. XII.
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Honorius</hi> 67</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Rupertus.</hi> 68</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Zonaras.</hi> ib.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Amalaricus.</hi> ib.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:105312:6"/>
                     <item>CENT. XIII, &amp;c.
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Of the Council of</hi> Lateran. 69</item>
                           <item>That ſeveral after it did not believe <hi>Tranſubſtantiation.</hi>
                              <list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Guido le Gros.</hi> 69</item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Reginald Peacock.</hi> 70</item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Guido Cluv.</hi> 71</item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Jo.</hi> of <hi>Paris.</hi> ib.</item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Albert. M.</hi> 72</item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Durand.</hi> ib.</item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Cornelius</hi> Bp. of <hi>Bitonte.</hi> ib.</item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Dominicus Bannes.</hi> ib.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>CONCLUS. <hi>To the Clergy of</hi> France, <hi>that they ought not to preſs upon the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants the belief of</hi> Tranſubſtantiation. 72</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:105312:6"/>
            <head>A TREATISE OF <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> Written by one of the <hi>CH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RCH</hi> of <hi>ROME</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Biſhops of <hi>France</hi> in their laſt <hi>Aſſembly</hi> held at <hi>Paris</hi> in the year 1682.
<note place="margin">The Clergy of <hi>France</hi>'s Method to judge of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of Faith.</note> compos'd a <hi>Paſtorial Letter</hi> addreſſed to the Proteſtants, to invite them to return to the Communion of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in order to put an end to their differences in Matters of Religion, ſome <hi>Rule</hi> muſt be agreed on to be received by the different Parties; they laid down ſeveral Principles which they called <hi>Methods,</hi> as fit to be made uſe of, whereby to judge what ſhould be received as an <hi>Article of Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Fourth <hi>Method</hi> they laid down as a <hi>Maxim,</hi> that the true means to diſcern what relates to matter of Faith, or not, is to ſee if the Article which is to be admitted, was always be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved as Matter of Faith; that is to ſay, <hi>that</hi> the French Biſhops admitted in their paſtoral Letter, the Maxim which <hi>Vincentius Lyrinenſis</hi> left us above 1100. years ago; <hi>That great Care muſt be taken to retain in the Catholick Church, what hath been believed every where, by all, and at all times,</hi> as being the true Means whereby to diſcern what is Matter of Faith, and what is not. This ſame is the Rule given by Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the Fourth, who obliges them to ſwear in the profeſſion of Faith, added to the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:105312:7"/>That the Holy Scriptures ſhould not be Interpreted,
<note n="†" place="margin">Secundum unanimem con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſum Patrum.</note> 
               <hi>But by the unanimous conſent of the Ancient Fathers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Proteſtants have thought this Maxim ſo reaſonable, that Monſieur <hi>Larroque</hi> a French Miniſter,
<note place="margin">Admitted by the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants.</note> ſaith in his Preface to the <hi>Hiſtory of the Euchariſt,</hi> that he believes there is no Man of Senſe, but ought to admit of it. And it was received as a <hi>Rule of Faith</hi> by the Reform'd <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> by <hi>Philip Melancthon,</hi> by <hi>Peter Martyr, Gallaſius, Scultetus, Caſaubon, Grotius, Voſſius, Beza,</hi> and by <hi>Geſſelius,</hi> (who recites their Authorities,) in the Preface of his <hi>Hiſtory of Memorable things from the Creation of the World, to the year of Chriſt</hi> 1125.</p>
            <p>Seeing therefore that the Biſhops of <hi>France</hi> have propos'd to us ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a <hi>Method,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation to be examined by it.</note> let us examine if the Doctrin of <hi>Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation</hi> be a <hi>Doctrin</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> and prove i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, not becauſe the <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Trent</hi> has defin'd it ſo; Or that the <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Lateran</hi> in the year 1215. ſuppos'd it to be ſo, <hi>non quia ipſam quam tenemus fidem commendaverit Milevitanus Optatus, vel Mediolanenſis Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſtus, aut quia Collegarum Noſtrorum Conciliis ipſa praedicta eſt,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> againſt the Donatiſts, <hi>De unit. Eccleſ.</hi> cap. 16. But becauſe 'tis contain'd in the <hi>Holy Scriptures,</hi> and underſtood in that Senſe by the unanimous conſent of the <hi>Doctors</hi> and <hi>Councils</hi> that have gone before us.</p>
            <p>This is what we now undertake to perform by the aſſiſtance of God's holy Spirit, and with a diſpoſition of Mind free from all Malice and Prejudice, according to what <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſaith in <hi>Saluſt,</hi> in the beginning of the Book of <hi>Cataline, Omnes homines qui de Rebus dubiis conſultant, ab ira &amp; odio vacuos eſſe debere, &amp; haud facile animum pervidere verum, ubi illa officiunt.</hi> And St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> upon the Book againſt the Letter of the <hi>Manichean,</hi> by them called the Letter of Foundation; <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t autem facilius miteſcatis, &amp;c. nemo noſtrum ſo jam quaeramus quaſi ab utriſque neſciatur, ita enim diligenter &amp; concorditer quari poterit, ſi nulla temeraria praeſumtione inventa &amp; cognita eſſe credatur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But not to over-burthen this ſmall Treatiſe with too great a number of Arguments or Citations, we will chiefly examine two things; Firſt, <hi>Who thoſe Catholick Doctors are, that believed the Doctrine of</hi> Tranſubſtantiation <hi>not to be ancient.</hi> Secondly, <hi>If what thoſe Doctors have writ be true: And whether we can indeed produce ſufficient Authorities to believe that the ancient Church did not hold nor believe it.</hi>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:105312:7"/>
               <head>PART I.</head>
               <p>IN the firſt place,
<note place="margin">Several Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin of <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantion</hi> not to be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ancient.</note> That there have been Catholick Doctors which have taught, that <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> is no ancient Doctrine,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>SUAREZ in</hi> 3. <hi>Tom. in Euch. Diſp.</hi> 70. <hi>Sect.</hi> 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Suarez</hi> formally aſſerteth it, although indeed he ſaith, their Opinion ought to be corrected. The truth is,
<note n="⸪" place="margin">
                     <hi>Lombard l.</hi> 4. <hi>d.</hi> 11.</note> 
                  <hi>Peter Lombard</hi> Maſter of the Sentences, ſaith expreſly, <hi>Si quaeras qualis ſit illa converſio, an formalis, an ſubſtantialis, an alterius generis, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finire non audeo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly,
<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Scotus in</hi> 4. <hi>d.</hi> 11. <hi>q.</hi> 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Scotus</hi> ſaith, That there were formerly three Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions touching the changing the <hi>Bread</hi> into the <hi>Body of Chriſt,</hi> the firſt of which held that the <hi>Bread</hi> remain'd in the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> In the Paragraph, <hi>quantum ergo ad iſtum articulum, &amp;c.</hi> he ſaith, that at preſent the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> holds <hi>Tranſubſtantiation. Nunc autem ipſa tenet (Sancta Rom. Eccleſia) panem tranſubſtantiari.</hi> And a little under, he ſaith, <hi>ad tertium ubi ſtat vis, dicendum quod Eccleſia declaravit iſtum intellectum eſſe de veritate fidei,
<note n="§" place="margin">Haec duo videnda.</note> in illo Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolo edito ſub Innocentio tertio in Concilio Lateranenſi.</hi> And ſince this Declaration made by this Council held in the year 1215. it is an Article of Faith. <hi>Tenendum eſt eſſe de ſubſtantia fidei, &amp; hoc poſt iſtam declarationem ſolemnem.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de Euch. cap.</hi> 23.</note> Bellarmine</hi> doth own that <hi>Scotus</hi> did believe <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> was no Article of Faith before the <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Lateran</hi> under <hi>Innocent</hi> the Third; but he adds, that 'twas becauſe <hi>Scotus</hi> did not know of the Council held under <hi>Gregory the Seventh,</hi> and that he had not read the Authorities of the Fathers which ſaith <hi>Bellarmin,</hi> I have now recited.</p>
               <p>Thirdly,
<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>P. Dayly</hi> on 4th Sent. q. 6. Art. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Peter Dayly,</hi> Cardinal and Biſhop of <hi>Cambray</hi> ſaith, It doth not clearly follow from the Determination of the Church, that the ſubſtance of Bread ceaſeth, therefore he doth not believe this to be the ancient Doctrine.</p>
               <p>Fourthly,
<note n="*" place="margin">Card. Cuſa.</note> Cardinal <hi>Cuſa,</hi> Excit. l. 6. Serm. 40. <hi>Super una Oblatione, conſummavit, &amp;c.</hi> ſaith, That there were ſome ancient Divines which did not believe <hi>Tranſubſtantiation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fifthly,
<note n="†" place="margin">Eraſmus.</note> 
                  <hi>Eraſmus</hi> in his Notes on the Firſt to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> ſaith, That it was late ere the Church eſtabliſhed <hi>Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:105312:8"/>
               <p>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Alphonſus à Caſtro Lib.</hi> 8. <hi>contr. Haereſ.</hi>
                  </note> Sixthly, <hi>Alphonſus à Caſtro,</hi> ſaith, That the ancient Writers very feldom ſpake of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Seventhly,
<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Tonſtal Lib.</hi> 1. of the Sacrament.</note> 
                  <hi>Tonſtall</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Lurham</hi> about the middle of the laſt Century, ſpeaking of the <hi>Breads</hi> being chang'd into the <hi>Body of Chriſt,</hi> ſaith, It were much better to leave it to the Liberty of Chriſtians to believe as they pleas'd, of the manner in which this change is made, as it was practis'd in the Church, before the Council of <hi>Lateran.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Eighthly,
<note place="margin">Coſſander.</note> in his Conſultation with the Emperour <hi>Maximilian</hi> the Second, touching the differences of Religion, confeſſeth that <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> is a Novelty, and that 'twere much better to keep to the terms of the Ancients, that the Abuſes therein, <hi>approach near to Idolatry.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ninthly,
<note place="margin">Du Mouten.</note> 
                  <hi>Charles du Moulin,</hi> the Oracle of the <hi>French</hi> Civilians, upon the <hi>Edicts and Ordinances of</hi> France, <hi>againſt the Injuries of Popes,</hi> Num. 406. ſpeaks in theſe Terms; <hi>Innocent</hi> the Third forged, or at leaſt eſtabliſhed it as a general Article of Faith, and as neceſſary to be believed by all, as that of the holy Trinity, the <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> of the <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> into the <hi>true Body</hi> and <hi>true Blood</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Tenthly,
<note place="margin">Jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Yriba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ne</note> 
                  <hi>John Yribarne</hi> a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Divine, in the 4th. Sent. Diſt. 11. q. 3. Diſp. 42. S. 1. ſaith, That in the Primitive Church it was matter of Faith, that the <hi>Body</hi> of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> was contain'd under the Species of <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine,</hi> but that 'twas not any matter of Faith to hold that the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of <hi>Bread</hi> was changed into the <hi>Fleſh</hi> of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and that it ſubſiſted no longer after Conſecration.</p>
               <p>Eleventhly,
<note place="margin">De Marca.</note> Monſieur <hi>de Marca,</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Paris</hi> in his Poſthumous Diſſertations, ſaith, in his <hi>French</hi> Treatiſe of the <hi>Sacrament of the Euchariſt,</hi> That until S. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi>'s time, it was believed the <hi>Bread</hi> was the <hi>Body</hi> of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> by a marvelous change that comes on the <hi>Bread;</hi> but that it becomes united to the incarnate Word and to his Natural Body, the Bread not changing its Nature, and yet not going into the Draught; which is a kind of pious conſideration which he added againſt <hi>Origen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:105312:8"/>
               <head>PART II.</head>
               <p>AS for the <hi>Second Point,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">That the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients indeed did not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
                  </note> which is to ſee if there is effectively to be found in the Writings of the Ancients, ſufficient Authorities to believe that the <hi>Ancients</hi> did not believe <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Before I alledge their Authorities, two Reflections may be made.</p>
               <p>Firſt, that our own Authors do obſerve, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſ </seg>1</label> that <hi>Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation</hi> is not expreſly mention'd nor taught in the Scriptures.
<note place="margin">The Papiſts confeſs that it is not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture. So</note>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Scotus.</note> 
                  <hi>Scotus</hi> cited by <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> of the Euchariſt, <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 23. ſaith, It doth not plainly follow from the words of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> that the Bread is <hi>tranſubſtantiated.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ockham. Lib.</hi> 4. <hi>q.</hi> 34.</note> 
                  <hi>Ockham</hi> ſaith of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> that it cannot be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by natural Reaſon, nor by Authority of the Bible, but only by the Authority of the Ancients.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Alfonſus de Caſtro Vocubulo In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgentiae.</note> 
                  <hi>Alfonſus de Caſtro</hi> diſapproves what <hi>Ockham</hi> ſays, that it can be proved by the Authority of the Ancients, for he ſaith, that it was not to be found, no more than <hi>Indulgences</hi> were, in the Writings of the Ancients.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gabriel
<note n="†" place="margin">
                        <hi>Biel. Lect.</hi> 40. <hi>in Can. Miſ.</hi>
                     </note> Biel</hi> ſpeaking of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> ſaith, That it is not expreſly taught in the Holy Scriptures.</p>
               <p>Cardinal
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>CAJETAN in</hi> 3 <hi>p.</hi> 8. <hi>Th</hi> 9.75. <hi>Art.</hi> 7.</note> 
                  <hi>Cajetan</hi> does not find the words of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> clear, neither for the <hi>Real Preſence,</hi> nor for <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> without the determination of the <hi>Church</hi> be joyned to them.</p>
               <p>The ſecond Reflection, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſ. </seg>2</label> is that <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> comprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a great many Difficulties quite contrary to natural Reaſon,
<note place="margin">None of the Pagans ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected to the ancient Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties of it. Not <hi>Trypho.</hi>
                  </note> none of the Jews nor Pagan Philoſophers, diſputing againſt the ancient Chriſtians, ever dream'd of making any Objections againſt it in their Diſputations. <hi>Trypho</hi> the Jew charges us with things monſtrous, incredible, and ſtrangely invented; as what we teach of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt's being before Aaron,</hi> and <hi>Abraham,</hi> that <hi>he took on him our Nature,</hi> that <hi>he was born of a Virgin,</hi> that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:105312:9"/>
                  <hi>God ſhould be born, be made Man;</hi> that <hi>we ſhould adore a Man,</hi> that <hi>we ſhould put our truſt in him,</hi> and <hi>that we ſhould invoke another God beſides the Creator,</hi> all this appears in S. <hi>Juſtin Martyr,</hi> in his <hi>Dialogue</hi> againſt <hi>Trypho.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Pagans</hi> reproach us for ſaying <hi>God</hi> has a <hi>Son,</hi> that this <hi>Son ſhould appear in humane ſhape,</hi> and they ſtile it <hi>the Follies of the Chriſtian Diſcipline;</hi> that <hi>God ſhould be born,</hi> and that he ſhould <hi>be born of a Virgin,</hi> and be <hi>a God of Fleſh, crucified and buried;</hi> The laſt <hi>Judgment,</hi> the <hi>pains of eternal Fire,</hi> the <hi>Joys of Heaven,</hi> the <hi>Reſurrection of the Dead.</hi> All this appears by <hi>Clement</hi> of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandria Stromat.</hi> l. 6. by <hi>Tertullian</hi> his <hi>Apologet.</hi> ch. 21.47. in his <hi>Treatiſe</hi> of the <hi>Fleſh of Chriſt,</hi> chap. 4. and 5. And in his <hi>Treatiſe</hi> of the <hi>Teſtimony of the Soul,</hi> chap. 4. By S. <hi>Juſtine</hi> in his ſecond <hi>Apology,</hi> and <hi>Arnobius</hi> in his ſecond <hi>Book.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Celſus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Nor <hi>Celſus.</hi>
                  </note> in
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>L.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2. <hi>contr. Celſ.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Origen,</hi> ſcoffs at the <hi>Incarnation,</hi> as of a thing unworthy of <hi>God.</hi> In the Sixth Book, he laughs that we ſhould believe <hi>God</hi> ſhould be <hi>born of a Virgin.</hi> In the Third and Eighth Book, he ſaith of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> That they honour with a <hi>Religious Worſhip</hi> even above all Religion, a Man that was a <hi>Priſoner</hi> and that <hi>ſuffered Death.</hi> He even thereby pleads for the plurality of his Gods: as if Chriſtians were not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfi'd in <hi>worſhipping one God,</hi> under colour that they <hi>adored Jeſus Chriſt; If Chriſtians,</hi> ſaith he in the Eighth Book, <hi>worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped but one God, they might have ſome colour to deſpiſe others. But they pay infinite Honours to him that has but very lately appear'd, and yet they don't think they diſpleaſe God when they ſerve and honour his Miniſter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Julian</hi> the <hi>Apoſtate</hi> oppos'd the <hi>Myſtery of the Incarnation,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Nor <hi>Julian.</hi>
                  </note> the <hi>Divinity of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>Salvation he purchas'd for us by the price of his Blood;</hi> he reproaches us with the glorious Title of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of God,</hi> which we give to the <hi>Bleſſed Virgin;</hi> he conteſts the <hi>Myſtery</hi> of the <hi>Trinity of Perſons</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of Eſſence,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing us of contradicting <hi>Moſes,</hi> who ſaid, There is but <hi>one God.</hi> He reproaches us for <hi>Baptiſm;</hi> See, ſaith he, <hi>what</hi> Paul <hi>ſaith to them, that they are ſanctified and cleanſed by Water, as if Water could penetrate to the Soul, to waſh and purifie it; Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſm can't ſo much as cleanſe a Leper, nor a Scurf, it cannot heal a Cancer nor the Gout.</hi> He aggravates what we read, that God <hi>viſits the Iniquity of the Fathers upon the Children,</hi> thereby to endeavour to attack the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of <hi>Original Sin.</hi> He bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly queſtions what <hi>God</hi> ſaith in the Book of <hi>Numbers</hi> touching
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:105312:9"/>
                  <hi>Phineas,</hi> that thruſt his Javelin through the Body of an <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelite</hi> that committed <hi>Folly</hi> with a <hi>Midianitiſh Woman,</hi> which turn'd away <hi>God</hi>'s Anger from the <hi>Children</hi> of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd him from conſuming them. <hi>Let us ſuppoſe,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that there had been to the Number of one Thouſand that had attempted to have tranſgreſſed the Law of God, ought ſix hundred Thouſand to have been deſtroy'd for the ſake of one Thouſand; it ſeems to me to have been much juſter to have ſaved one ill Man with ſo many good ones, than to involve ſo many good Men in the ruine of one bad one.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There's ſcarce any of our <hi>Myſteries</hi> that have not been cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd by the <hi>Jews</hi> or <hi>Pagans;</hi> yet 'tis very ſtrange that not one ſhould accuſe us of admitting in the <hi>Euchariſt, accidents</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>ſubſtance, whiteneſs</hi> without any thing that's <hi>white, roundneſs</hi> without any thing <hi>round; weight</hi> without any thing that's <hi>weighty;</hi> a <hi>corruption</hi> whereunto the <hi>ſpecies</hi> are ſubject, without any thing that's capable of being <hi>corrupted;</hi> a <hi>Nouriſhment</hi> in the <hi>Symbols,</hi> without any thing that can <hi>nouriſh;</hi> a power in the <hi>Wine</hi> to be ſmelt without any thing that may be ſmelled. No body ever reproach'd us with ſo ſtrange a thing, that a Man with one word ſhould deſtroy a ſubſtance which he holdeth in his hands, and that never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs againſt the teſtimony of all the Senſes, I <hi>ſee</hi> that which is <hi>no more;</hi> I <hi>feel</hi> that which I do <hi>not feel,</hi> I <hi>taſte</hi> that which I do <hi>not taſte,</hi> I <hi>underſtand</hi> that which I do <hi>not underſtand;</hi> I <hi>touch</hi> that which I do <hi>not touch,</hi> that I ſhould be <hi>nouriſhed</hi> with <hi>nothing;</hi> that my <hi>taſte</hi> ſhould be delighted with <hi>nothing;</hi> that my <hi>Eyes</hi> and <hi>Ears</hi> ſhould be ſtruck with <hi>Nothing</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The three Reflections we have hitherto made,
<note place="margin">Hence it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, that <hi>Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation</hi> was not ancient.</note> That many of the antient Catholick Doctors have not believed <hi>Tranſubſtantiation to</hi> be antient; That they have judged it could not evidently be dedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced from the <hi>Holy Scriptures;</hi> and, That the antient Pagan <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers</hi> have not reproached us with it, are three very ſtrong Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions to make us mightily doubt the <hi>Antiquity</hi> of this <hi>Doctrine.</hi> But to ſhew evidently that 'twas but in the <hi>laſt Ages</hi> that this opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion was made an <hi>Article of Faith,</hi> we need only conſult the Doctors of the <hi>Primitive Church,</hi> and ſee if they have effectively explain'd the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> by the <hi>Syſteme of Tranſubſtantiation.</hi>
               </p>
               <div n="2" type="century">
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:105312:10"/>
                  <head>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">AGE </seg>ii.</label>
                     <note place="margin">Juſt. Martyr</note> 
                     <hi>That the Fathers of the</hi> SECOND CENTURY <hi>did not believe</hi> Tranſubſtantiation.</head>
                  <p>S <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Apol.</hi> 2.</note>
                     <q>
                        <hi>That after the common Prayers were ended, there was preſented to the chief of the Brethren, which was God's Miniſter, the</hi> Bread <hi>and the</hi> Wine, <hi>mixt with</hi> Water, <hi>which he receiv'd into his hands, and giving thanks and glory to the Father of Heaven and Earth, through Jeſus Chriſt his Son, and the Holy Ghoſt, &amp;c. and the ſaid</hi> Preſident <hi>or</hi> Miniſter <hi>having ended his thanksgiving, the People ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving all ſaid</hi> Amen, <hi>thoſe whom we call</hi> Deacons <hi>and</hi> Miniſters, <hi>at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending on this Holy Service, give to every one preſent at the Holy Communion, part of this Holy Bread, ſo bleſſed and glorify'd; and alſo of the Holy liquor mixt of Wine and Water, upon which Prayers had been made.</hi>
                     </q> And a little lower,
<q>
                        <hi>Behold, Lord, we do not receive this</hi> Bread <hi>nor this</hi> Wine <hi>as common</hi> Bread <hi>and</hi> Wine, <hi>but as Jeſus Chriſt is become</hi> Fleſh <hi>and</hi> Blood <hi>by the Word, ſo alſo the nouriſhment which by the Word is become a</hi> Sacrament, <hi>and of which by</hi> converſion and change, our fleſh and Blood are nouriſh'd, <hi>is as we have learned, the</hi> Fleſh and Blood <hi>of Jeſus Chriſt incarnate.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>If St. <hi>Juſtin</hi> had believed that the ſubſtance of the <hi>Bread, Wine,</hi> and <hi>Water</hi> had been <hi>changed</hi> after Conſecration, ſo that they had been deſtroy'd, how could he have ſaid, that after Conſecration the Deacons did diſtribute to the People the <hi>Bread,</hi> the <hi>Wine,</hi> and the <hi>Water?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, When he ſaith, we do not take this <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> as <hi>common Bread and Wine:</hi> this language amongſt the antient Doctors intimates, that both the one and the other do ſtill ſubſiſt, but that by Conſecration, they have acquir'd a new uſe and quality. As when <hi>Cyril</hi> of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> Catech. 3. <hi>Ad Illum.</hi> ſaith, <hi>Approach not to Baptiſm as to common Water.</hi> Or as <hi>Gregory Nyſſen</hi> ſaith of Baptiſm, <hi>Do not deſpiſe the Holy Font, and look not upon it as common Water.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To conclude, this bleſſed Martyr ſaith, Our <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood are nouriſh'd by the change of the Euchariſtical food, which converts
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:105312:10"/>and turns it ſelf into our Fleſh and Blood.</hi> Theſe words plainly ſhew, that 'tis the Bread and Wine which are turn'd into our <hi>Subſtance,</hi> into our <hi>Fleſh,</hi> and into our <hi>Blood,</hi> ſeeing that tis 'certain,
<note place="margin">Juſtin Martyr.</note> that the <hi>real Fleſh and Blood</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, is not converted into our <hi>Fleſh</hi> and <hi>Blood.</hi> So when <hi>Juſtin</hi> ſaith, That the Sacramental Food is the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, that imports, that 'tis not common <hi>Bread and Wine,</hi> but a <hi>Bread</hi> and Wine which is to be conſider'd as the <hi>Fleſh</hi> and <hi>Blood of</hi> the <hi>Word incarnate.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>S. <hi>Irenaeus</hi> proves againſt <hi>Valentine</hi> and his followers,
<note place="margin">Irenaeus</note> that our Bodies ſhall not be deſtroy'd, and by conſequence that they ſhall be raiſed incorruptible by receiving the Sacrament, as the <hi>Bread</hi> of the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> becomes ſupernatural by the invocation of the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We eſtabliſh in the Euchariſt,</hi> ſaith S. Irenaeus,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Adverſus Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſ. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 24.</note> 
                     <hi>the Communion and unity of the Fleſh and of the Spirit; for as the Bread which is of the Earth, receiving the invocation of God, is no longer common Bread, but is the Sacrament compos'd of two things, one Terreſtrial, and the other Celeſtial: So alſo our Bodies which receive the Euchariſt, are no longer corruptible, but have the Hope of a future Reſurrection.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This paſſage doth ſuppoſe, that the <hi>Bread</hi> remains in the <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt;</hi> in the firſt place, becauſe if Conſecration did deſtroy the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of the <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wire,</hi> it muſt be confeſs'd the Holy Doctor had taken wrong meaſures, to ſhew that the Fleſh is not deſtroy'd by the grace of the Holy Spirit, by the Bread of the Euchariſt, which it ſelf ſhould be deſtroy'd by the grace of the Spirit which comes upon it.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, Becauſe a little before, <hi>Irenaeus</hi> ſaith, <hi>How is it they ſay, the Fleſh ſhall be deſtroy'd and turn to corruption, ſeeing it is nouriſh'd with the body and blood of Chriſt?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now the <hi>Fleſh</hi> is ſed by the converſion of nouriſhment into the body, which not being to be ſaid of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> is only to be apply'd to the <hi>Bread.</hi> Moreover theſe words, That <hi>the Euchariſt is compos'd of two things,</hi> ſufficiently ſhew, that the <hi>Bread</hi> remains; for to ſay <hi>Ireneus</hi> means by a <hi>Terreſtrial thing,</hi> the <hi>accidents</hi> of <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine,</hi> beſides that <hi>S. Auſtin</hi> ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th in the ſecond Book of <hi>Soliloquies,</hi> Chap. 12. that 'tis a thing monſtrous to ſay that accidents ſubſiſt without a ſubject; <hi>Irereus</hi> alſo himſelf ſaith, Book 2. cap. 14. that Water cannot be without moiſture, Fire without heat, a Stone without hardneſs. For theſe things are ſo united, that the one cannot be ſeparated from the other, but the one muſt ſubſiſt in the other. So in like manner, by this <hi>Terreſtrial thing</hi> muſt be
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:105312:11"/>underſtood the <hi>Bread,</hi> as S. <hi>Gregory Naz.</hi> ſaith in his fourth Orati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on according to <hi>Bilius</hi> his verſion, <hi>Baptiſm alſo is compos'd of two things, Water and the Spirit; the one is viſible and is meant in a corporal manner,
<note place="margin">Irenaeus</note> but the other is inviſible and operates after a ſpiritual manner; the one is Typical, the other cleanſeth that which is inward, and moſt hidden.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Clement</hi> of <hi>Alexandria</hi> ſaith the ſame in different terms.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Clem. Alexand. Paedag. l.</hi> 2.</note> 
                     <hi>The</hi>
                     <q>Blood <hi>of Chriſt is twofold, the one is</hi> carnal, <hi>whereby we are deliver'd from corruption, the other is</hi> ſpiritual, <hi>whereby we are anointed, and that is to</hi> drink <hi>the</hi> Blood <hi>of Jeſus Chriſt, to be partakers of the incorruption of the Lord. Now the virtue of the Word is the Holy Spirit, as the Blood is the virtue of the Fleſh. By Analogy then, the Wine, mixt with Water, as the Spirit with Man; and this mixture makes the Wine the pleaſanter to drink, but the Spirit leadeth to incorruption. Now this mixture of the one with the other, to wit, of the Wine and the Word, is called</hi> Euchariſt, <hi>which is highly eſteem'd, whereby thoſe who worthily partake of it by Faith, are ſanctify'd both in their Body and Soul.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>When <hi>Clement</hi> of <hi>Alexandria</hi> ſaid that the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> is a mixture of <hi>Wine</hi> and the <hi>Word,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Graecè <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> ſignifies mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</note> it is a compoſition, a mixture, which could not be, if there was but the Word only in the Euchariſt. For a mixture is at leaſt of two things. So the Fathers have called <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> a mixture of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man. The Body of Man,</hi> ſaith <hi>S.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">S. Auſtin Ep. 3. ad <hi>Voluſen.</hi>
                     </note> Auſtin, <hi>is a mixture of Body and Soul; the Perſon of Chriſt is a mixture of God and Man.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Epitome of <hi>Theodotus</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">Theodotus.</note> 
                     <hi>The Bread and Oyl are ſanctified by the virtue of the name, and they remain not what they were before, though to look on them they ſeem to be the ſame, but by virtue, they are changed into a Spiritual force. So water ſanctified is become Baptiſm, it not only retains what's leſs, but alſo acquires a ſanctification.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The author ſaith, The <hi>Bread</hi> is <hi>changed,</hi> but when he adds that 'tis into a <hi>Spiritual virtue,</hi> he quite excludes the change of its <hi>ſubſtance;</hi> for by <hi>virtue,</hi> and <hi>Spiritual,</hi> cannot be underſtood any other change but that of <hi>virtue</hi> and <hi>quality,</hi> ſeeing this Author ſpeaks of this change, as being common to the Water of Baptiſm, to the Oyl of Unction, and to the Bread of the Euchariſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="century">
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:105312:11"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>That the Fathers of the</hi> THIRD CENTURY <hi>did not believe</hi> Tranſubſtantiation. <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">AGE </seg>iii.</label>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>TErtullian</hi> in his firſt Book againſt <hi>Marcion,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Tertullian.</note> ſhewing that Jeſus Chriſt is not contrary to the Creator, as this Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick affirm'd, ſaith in his 14th. Chap. <hi>Hitherto Jeſus Chriſt has not condemn'd the Water wherewith he cleanſeth his Children, nor the Oyl wherewith he anoints them, nor the Hony nor the Milk where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he makes them his Children, nor the Bread by which he repreſents his body.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By this paſſage, the <hi>Bread repreſents the Body of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> therefore the <hi>Bread</hi> remains in the Sacrament, and this <hi>Bread</hi> is not <hi>really</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, becauſe what doth <hi>repreſent,</hi> is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing than what is <hi>repreſented.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Two things have been ſaid on this place of <hi>Tertullian;</hi> firſt, that the <hi>Bread</hi> ſignifies the <hi>accidents of Bread;</hi> the ſecond that the Word <hi>repreſent,</hi> does ſignify in this place, <hi>to make preſent:</hi> As when in a Court of Juſtice a Priſoner is made appear as often as he is demanded.</p>
                  <p>Againſt the former, there's no reaſon to believe that <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſpeaking of <hi>Water,</hi> of <hi>Oyl,</hi> of <hi>Hony,</hi> and <hi>Milk,</hi> ſhould intend to ſpeak of their <hi>accidents,</hi> but of their very <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,</hi> and that ſpeaking of <hi>Bread,</hi> he ſhould ſpeak only of its <hi>accidents.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Againſt the ſecond it's moſt certain that in matter of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, the term to <hi>ſignify</hi> is taken literally, to <hi>ſignify.</hi> S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith, Ep. 5. <hi>the ſigns, when applyed to Holy things, are called Sacraments. Tertullian</hi> explains himſelf clearly Lib. 3. againſt <hi>Marcion,</hi> ſo that there's no cauſe of doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, when he ſaith, <hi>That Jeſus Chriſt has given to the Bread the priviledge of being the figure of his Body.</hi> The ſame <hi>Tertullian</hi> lib. 4. <hi>contra Marcion.</hi> cap. 40. doth prove that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> had a <hi>real Body,</hi> and not one in <hi>ſhew</hi> only, as <hi>Marcion</hi> dream'd, and he proves it by this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: That which hath a <hi>figure</hi> ought to be <hi>real</hi> and <hi>true;</hi>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:105312:12"/>now Jeſus Chriſt hath in the Euchariſt a <hi>figure of his Body,</hi> therefore the <hi>Body</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt is <hi>real</hi> and <hi>true,</hi> and not a <hi>Phantome.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Tertulliar.</note> ſaith <hi>Tertullian, having taken the Bread which he ariſtributed amongſt his Diſciples, he made it his Body, ſaying, This is the figure of my Body: now it had been no figure, if Jeſus Chriſt had not had a real and true Body; for an empty thing as a Phantaſm is, is not capable of having any figure.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>From hence 'tis concluded, that the <hi>Bread</hi> being the <hi>figure of the Body of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and that which is a <hi>figure,</hi> being diſtinguiſhed from the thing <hi>ſignified,</hi> the <hi>Bread</hi> of the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> is not <hi>properly</hi> and <hi>truly</hi> the <hi>Body</hi> of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and ſo the <hi>Bread</hi> is not deſtroy'd, but remains to be the <hi>figure</hi> of the <hi>Body</hi> of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If it be ſaid, the <hi>Bread</hi> is deſtroy'd, and that the <hi>acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents</hi> of <hi>Bread</hi> are the <hi>figure</hi> of the <hi>Body</hi> of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> this gives up the victory to <hi>Marcion,</hi> to prove, that Jeſus Chriſt had a <hi>true Body,</hi> and not one in <hi>ſhew only,</hi> becauſe Jeſus Chriſt hath in the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> the <hi>figure</hi> of <hi>Bread,</hi> which is <hi>Bread</hi> only in appearance. <hi>Marcion</hi> might have retorted the argument and ſaid, according to you, <hi>Tertullian,</hi> the Sacrament is the <hi>figure</hi> of the <hi>Body</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt; now as this <hi>figure</hi> is <hi>Bread</hi> in <hi>appearance,</hi> and is called <hi>Bread</hi> only becauſe of the outward <hi>accidents</hi> and <hi>qualities</hi> which it retains, ſo alſo the <hi>Body</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt was only a <hi>Body</hi> in <hi>appearance,</hi> and was called a <hi>Body</hi> becauſe it had the outward <hi>accidents and qualities.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Again, as <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaith, That Jeſus Chriſt diſtributed to his Diſciples the <hi>Bread</hi> which he had taken to make it the <hi>figure of his Body;</hi> it is moſt certain he took true <hi>Bread,</hi> and by conſequence, that he diſtributed <hi>true Bread.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſame <hi>Tertullian</hi> in his <hi>Treatiſe of the Soul,</hi> diſputing againſt the <hi>Academitians</hi> that queſtion'd the truth of the teſtimony of the <hi>Senſes,</hi> ſaith to them, that we muſt not at all doubt of the teſtimony of the Senſes, leſt occaſion might farther be taken to doubt the actions of the humanity of Jeſus Chriſt, that it might not be ſaid, That it was untrue that he ſaw <hi>Satan</hi> fall from Heaven; That it was not true, that he heard the Father's voice from heaven bearing witneſs to his Son;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:105312:12"/>That he was deceived when he touched <hi>Peter</hi>'s Wifes Mother; That he was deceived when he ſinelt the ſweet odour which he was pleas'd to accept for the preparation to his Death; or, That he taſted the Wine that he conſecrated in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of his Blood.</p>
                  <p>It is evident that to conſecrate <hi>Wine,</hi> in remembrance of <hi>Blood,</hi> cannot be underſtood of a <hi>ſubſtance</hi> which is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy'd all ſaving the <hi>accidents;</hi> This manner of expreſſion in the language of the Ancients ſignifying no more, but that a ſubſtance remains always in its firſt ſtate, only at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains to a higher degree, which is, to be the Sacrament of a Heavenly and ſupernatural thing. To conclude, if <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi> had believed that the Wine had been deſtroy'd, and that nothing but the appearance was left, againſt the teſtimony of all the Senſes, had it not been an unpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable fault in <hi>Tertullian,</hi> to prove that the Senſes could not be deceived by the Example of the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> where the Senſes are quite deceived?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Origen</hi> did not believe <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> when he ſaid in his Commentary on the 13th. Chap. of S. <hi>Matth.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Origen.</note> expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding theſe words of the <hi>Goſpel, what enters into the Mouth</hi> 
                     <q>
                        <hi>defiles not the Man</hi> &amp;c.
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Du Perron</hi> ſaith <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>n this paſſage, <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, ſtop your Hars.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>as there's nothing that's impure of it ſelf to him that's polluted and incredulous, but a thing is impure, by reaſon of his impurity and incredulity; ſo alſo, that which is ſanctifyed by the word of God and Prayer, doth not ſanctify by its proper nature, him that uſes it: If it were ſo, it would alſo ſanctify him that eats unworthily of the Lord, and none ſhould have been weak, nor ſick, nor ſhould have fallen aſleep, by reaſon of ſo eating —. If all that enters into the Mouth goes into the Belly, and there is caſt out into the draught, this food which is ſanctifyed by the word of God, and by Prayer, goes alſo into the Belly and is caſt out into the draught, according to its material ſubſtance; But according to the Prayer which has been thereunto added, it becomes profitable according to the meaſure of Faith, by cauſing the mind to become inlightned, having regard to what is profitable; And 'tis not the matter of Bread, but the words which have been pronounc'd upon it, that avails him which eateth in ſuch a manner as is not unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of the Lord, and this may be ſaid of the Body Typical, or Symbolical; Many things might be ſaid alſo of the Word made
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:105312:13"/>Fleſh, and true nouriſhment, the which whoſoever eats ſhall never dye, and which no wicked perſon can eat; for could it be that he which continues wicked ſhould eat of the Word incarnate, ſeeing he is the Word and Bread of Life,
<note place="margin">Origen.</note> it would not have been written, Whoſoever eateth this Bread ſhall live Eternally.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>When he ſaith of the <hi>Bread</hi> of the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> that it ſanctifieth not of it ſelf, it cannot he underſtood of the <hi>true Body</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, but of the Bread which remains. When he ſaith, This Bread ſanctified by the invocation of God, and by Prayer, remains in its material being, it means plainly, That it remains in its former ſubſtance. When he ſaith, That this Bread as to the matter of it goes down in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Belly, and is caſt into the draught as the other meats: This not being to be underſtood of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> without Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheming, is neceſſarily to be underſtood of the <hi>Bread.</hi> When he calls this <hi>Bread</hi> the <hi>Typical Body,</hi> it ſhews plainly, That this not being the <hi>true Body,</hi> it is not <hi>Tranſubſtantiated.</hi> When having ſpoken of the <hi>Typical Body,</hi> he after ſpeaks of the <hi>Word</hi> made <hi>Fleſh,</hi> which cannot but give life to thoſe which eat and receive him; he ſufficiently diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſheth the <hi>Bread</hi> of the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> from <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> the former of which may be mortal, but the latter can never be ſo to thoſe who receive and eat him.</p>
                  <p>This paſſage is ſo clear and evident, that <hi>Sixtus Senen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis</hi> in his Bibl. <hi>l.</hi> 6. annot. 66. found no better expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent than to ſay, That 'twas probable, This paſſage had been corrupted by the <hi>Hereticks. Gennebrard</hi> and <hi>Du Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi> ſuſpected <hi>Eraſmus</hi> to have ill tranſlated it: But the learned Monſieur <hi>Huet,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Origeniana l.</hi> 2. <hi>q.</hi> 14.</note> nominated to be Biſhop of <hi>Soiſſons,</hi> ſaith, It evidently appears by the Original <hi>Greek,</hi> that this paſſage is no way changed.</p>
                  <p>The ſame <hi>Origen</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">Pag. 411. Edit. Huet. G. L.</note> in <hi>Tom.</hi> 32. of his Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary on S. <hi>John,</hi> that the morſel of <hi>Bread</hi> Chriſt gave to <hi>Judas</hi> and thoſe he gave the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Take, Eat,</hi> were of the ſame ſort. Now if the morſel given to <hi>Judas</hi> was <hi>true Bread,</hi> as it is granted, and if the <hi>Bread</hi> given the other Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles was not true <hi>Bread,</hi> then the one and the other were not of the ſame kind.</p>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:105312:13"/>
                  <p>The ſame in the Seventh Homily on <hi>Leviticus,</hi> ſaith, That <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> before his Paſſion, drank Wine, but being ready to ſuffer, he reſuſed to drink it;
<note place="margin">Origen.</note> 
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi vero tempus advenit Crucis ſuae, accipiens, inquit, Calicem benedixit, &amp; dedit Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulis ſuis, dicens, Accipite &amp; Bibite ex hoc. Vos, inquit, bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite quia non acceſſuri eſtis ad altare, ipſe autem tanquam acceſſurus ad altare dicit, Amen, dico vobis quia non bibam de generatione vitis hujus, uſque quò bibam illud novum vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſcum in Regno Patris mei. Origen</hi> affirms, That our Saviour in celebrating the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> did not drink Wine, becauſe he was ready to approach the Altar (of his Paſſion) and that the Apoſtles did drink Wine, becauſe they were not yet ready to approach to the Altar of Martyrdom. And that in this ſenſe, the Figure of the Old Teſtament was accompliſhed, where 'twas forbidden to <hi>Aaron</hi> and his Prieſts to drink Wine when they were about to approach to the Altar. All this Diſcourſe is falſe, if Jeſus Chriſt ſpake not theſe words of <hi>true Wine, I will not drink,</hi> &amp;c. and if what the Apoſtles drank was not <hi>true Wine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Let us ſee now what St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">Cyprian.</note> 
                     <hi>The Sacrifice of the Lord recommends to us <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity: for when Jeſus Chriſt called his Body, the Bread which is made of ſeveral Grains, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of Chriſtian People; and when he called his Blood, the Wine, made of ſeveral Grains and Grapes, he repreſented one Flock united by the Band of Charity.</hi> Now theſe words, where Jeſus Chriſt called the <hi>Bread</hi> his <hi>Body,</hi> and the <hi>Wine</hi> his <hi>Blood,</hi> is as if he had ſaid of the <hi>Bread; This is my Body,</hi> and <hi>of</hi> the <hi>Wine, This is my Blood.</hi> And if hereunto we add the words of the Jeſuite <hi>Salmeron,</hi> who ſaid,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Tom.</hi> 9.1 <hi>Tract.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp; Tract.</hi> 16.</note> 
                     <hi>If Jeſus Chriſt had ſaid, This Bread is my Body, and this Wine is my Blood, it would have obliged us to have underſtood theſe words in a figurative ſenſe, becauſe the Bread cannot be a hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Body, nor the Wine Blood, but in a figurative Senſe. Bellarmine</hi> ſaith the ſame; <hi>If Jeſus Chriſt had ſaid,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>De Euch. l.</hi> 1 <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note> This Bread is my Body, this propoſition muſt be underſtood in a figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative Senſe; otherwiſe the Expreſſion would be abſurd and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible.</hi> Now as we ſee S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſaith, that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> ſaid of the <hi>Bread,</hi> That 'tis his <hi>Body,</hi> and of the <hi>Win,</hi> That 'twas his <hi>Blood,</hi> it muſt be concluded therefore that Jeſus Chriſt ſaid of the <hi>Breud</hi> and <hi>Wine,</hi> That they were his <hi>Body</hi>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:105312:14"/>and <hi>Blood,</hi> that is to ſay, That the <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> were his <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> in <hi>Figure,</hi> both the one and the other being <hi>repreſented</hi> and <hi>ſignified</hi> by the <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine.</hi> And therefore in his Epiſtle to <hi>Cecilius,</hi> where at large he proves the <hi>Wine</hi> muſt be mingled with <hi>Water,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>If there be no Wine in the Cup, the Blood of Jeſus Goriſt cannot be repreſented to us, becauſe 'tis the Wine that repreſents to us the Blood of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> And again, <hi>Vini ubique mentio eſt, &amp; ideo ponitur ut Domini Sanguis Vino intelligatur.</hi> He ſaith of the Water, that, <hi>Sola Chriſti ſanguinem non poteſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>primere.</hi> In <hi>aqua vidimus populum intelligi, in Vino oſtendi Sanguinem Chriſti.</hi> So that ſeeing St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſaith, That the <hi>Wine repreſenteth, expreſſeth, ſheweth,</hi> and makes us <hi>ſee</hi> the <hi>Blood</hi> of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> as the <hi>Water repreſenteth, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth,</hi> and <hi>ſhews</hi> us the <hi>Chriſtian People,</hi> it cannot be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin'd that St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> believed the <hi>Wine</hi> was deſtroy'd, but on the contrary, he believed that after Conſecration, the <hi>Wine remained,</hi> and that 'twas <hi>true Wine</hi> that he called his <hi>Blood,</hi> according to what he ſaith in the ſame Letter, <hi>Quia in parte invenimus Calicem mixtum fuiſſe quem Dominus obtulit, &amp; vinum fuiſſe quod Sanguinem ſuum dixit.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="century">
                  <head>
                     <hi>That the Fathers of the</hi> FOURTH CENTURY <hi>did not believe</hi> Tranſubſtantiation. <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">AGE </seg>iv.</label>
                     <note place="margin">Euſtathius.</note>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>E<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſtathius,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Nicaen. Syn.</hi> 2. <hi>Act.</hi> 6.</note> Patriarch of <hi>Antioch,</hi> upon theſe words of <hi>Solomon</hi> in the <hi>Proverbs, Eat my Bread, and drink the Wine which I have prepar'd;</hi> ſaith, <hi>That the wiſe Man by the</hi> Bread <hi>and</hi> Wine <hi>did foreſhew the Anti types of the Body of Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> Now that which is a <hi>Type,</hi> is an <hi>Image;</hi> what is an <hi>Image</hi> cannot be the <hi>thing</hi> but in <hi>Figure:</hi> ſo that the <hi>Bread</hi> is not deſtroy'd, becauſe it is the <hi>Type</hi> and the <hi>Image.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Euſebius</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Euſebius</hi> of <hi>Caeſarea,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lib.</hi> 8. <hi>de Dem. Evang.</hi>
                     </note> interpreting theſe words of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> Chap. 49. Verſ. 12. <hi>His Eyes ſhall be red with Wine, and his
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:105312:14"/>Teeth white with Milk,</hi> ſaith, <hi>That the firſt words ſignifie the Joy that the myſtical Wine doth cauſe in the Diſciples of Jeſus Chriſt when he ſaith to them, Take, Drink ye ALL of this,</hi> &amp;c.
<note place="margin">Euſrbius.</note> 
                     <hi>And theſe words, The Teeth white with Milk, do ſignifie the purity and cleanneſs of the Myſtical Food, which are the Symbols which Jeſus Chriſt left to his Diſciples, commanding them to celebrate the Image of his proper Body; not requiring any more bloody Sacrifices, and commanded to make uſe of Bread for the Symbol of his Body.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Seeing then that according to this ancient Doctor, the <hi>Wine</hi> is the <hi>Symbol</hi> of the <hi>Blood</hi> of Chriſt, and the <hi>Bread</hi> the <hi>Figure</hi> of his <hi>Body,</hi> and both the one and the other an <hi>Image</hi> of the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood,</hi> the <hi>Image</hi> is not that of which 'tis an <hi>Image;</hi> and by conſequence, in the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> beſides the <hi>Body</hi> of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> there is alſo <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine,</hi> which do <hi>repreſent</hi> and <hi>ſhew</hi> him; it being evident by the Text of this Author, that he underſtood the words of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> in this ſenſe, <hi>This is the Symbol of my Body.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cyril</hi> of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">Cyril us Hieroſol.</note> 
                     <hi>Quemadmodum Panis Fuchariſticus poſt Spiritûs Sancti invocationem, non amplius eſt Panis com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munis, ſed eſt Corpus Chriſti,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Catech. My<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>.</hi> 3.</note> ſic &amp; ſanctum hoc unguentum non amplius eſt unguentum illud.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Macharius,</hi> a noted Hermite in <hi>Egypt,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Macharius.</note> who wrote his Homilies about the year 368. ſaith in the 27th Homily, <hi>That before the birth of Jeſus Chriſt, the wiſe Men, Holy Men, Kings and Prophets, knew that Jeſus Chriſt was to come to be a redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, but they knew not that he was to ſuffer death, that he was to be Crucify'd, and that he ſhould ſhed his Blood on the Croſs, and that they had not attain'd ſo far as to know there ſhould be a Baptiſm of Fire and of the Holy Ghoſt, and that in the Church ſhould be offered Bread and Wine, Antitypes of the Body and Blood of Jeſus Chriſt, and that thoſe which eat of this viſible Bread, ſhould ſpiritually eat the Fleſh of the Lord.</hi> This Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſaying that the <hi>Antitype</hi> of the <hi>Fleſh</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> is <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine,</hi> doth ſuppoſe the <hi>Bread</hi> remains, as not being the <hi>Real Body</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, but a <hi>Type</hi> of it: now the <hi>Type</hi> is not the verity, <hi>ſed umbra veritatis,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> de ſide l. 3. c. 8. and by conſequence, there is in the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> ſomething elſe beſides the <hi>Body</hi> it ſelf of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:105312:15"/>Jeſus Chriſt. And when he ſaith, That thoſe which take the <hi>viſible Bread, do ſpiritually eat the Fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſh of Chriſt,</hi> he gives us ſufficiently to underſtand,
<note place="margin">Macharius.</note> that in this auguſt Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, there is beſides the <hi>Fleſh</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt a <hi>viſible Bread,</hi> and that the <hi>viſible Bread</hi> is eaten <hi>corporally,</hi> and the <hi>Fleſh</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt <hi>ſpiritually.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>S.
<note place="margin">S. <hi>Baſil</hi>
                     </note> Biſhop of <hi>Caeſaria,</hi> in his Epiſtle to <hi>Caeſarea,</hi> ſaith, <hi>That at</hi> Alexandria, <hi>and in</hi> Aegypt, <hi>each Lay-perſon for the
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ep.</hi> 289.</note> moſt part, kept the Euchariſt by them, and communicated them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves when they pleaſed; and if they receive from the Prieſt a morſel of the conſecrated Bread, they may receive the Holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament daily if they liſt, taking ſome of it to day, and the reſt to morrow. For,</hi> ſaith, he, <hi>the Prieſt in the Church gives a good Piece or morſel of the Euchariſt, and he that takes it, doth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate himſelf at his pleaſure. Now,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>as to the validity and virtue of the Sacrament, it is one and the ſame, whether one receives one morſel, or two, of the Prieſt.</hi> In what ſenſe can it be underſtood that one receives ſeveral parts of <hi>parcels</hi> in the <hi>Euchariſt?</hi> It cannot be meant of Jeſus Chriſt, whoſe <hi>Body</hi> cannot be divided into merſels; it muſt therefore be underſtood, that S. <hi>Baſil</hi> believed that the <hi>Bread</hi> remained in the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> as a <hi>Typical</hi> and <hi>Symbolical Body of</hi> Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ephrem Deacon</hi> of the Church of <hi>Edeſſa,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ephrem.</note> contemporary with S. <hi>Baſil,</hi> and whoſe Writings St. <hi>Jerom</hi> reports in his Catalogue, were read in the Church after the Holy Scriptures; he ſaith, in the Treatiſe he wrote, <hi>That Men ſhould not ſearch too curiouſly into the Nature of God; conſider diligently</hi> (ſaith this holy Deacon) <hi>how Jeſus Chriſt taking the Bread into his hands, bleſſed and broke it as a Figure of his immaculate Body; and taking the Cup, he bleſſed it as a Type of his bleſſed Blood, and gave it to his Diſciples.</hi> It is evident that <hi>Ephrem</hi> believed the <hi>Bread</hi> is the <hi>figure</hi> of the <hi>Body,</hi> and the <hi>Wine</hi> the <hi>Type</hi> of the <hi>Blood</hi> of <hi>Chriſt; figura autem non eſt veritas, ſed imitatie veritatis, ſaith S. Gaudentius</hi> upon <hi>Exodus,</hi> Tract. 2. the <hi>Body</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt is the <hi>verity,</hi> there muſt then be in the Sacrament, beſides the <hi>real Body,</hi> a <hi>material</hi> and <hi>Typi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Body,</hi> which may be the <hi>figure</hi> of the <hi>true Body</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:105312:15"/>
                  <p>S. <hi>Epiphanius</hi> having ſaid, That Jeſus Chriſt deſcended into the Waters to be Baptis'd, not to receive any virtue from the Waters, but to confer it upon them, he adds,
<note place="margin">Epiphanius. S. Ep. in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> fide Eccleſ. Deus ad aquas de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendit.</note> That 'tis in Jeſus Chriſt the Prophecy of <hi>Eſay</hi> is accompliſhed, who in the third Chap. ſpeaks of the vertue of <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Water,</hi> he gave ſtrength to the Waters, <hi>illuminans eas, &amp; roborans in Type earum quae in ipſo erant perficienda;</hi> and as for the Bread, <hi>Cibus quidem panis eſt, ſed virtus in eo eſt ad vivificationem.</hi> S. <hi>Epiphanius</hi> ſpeaks here of the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> as he doth of <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> he ſaith, That both one and the other receive their virtue from Jeſus Chriſt, who communicates to them ſpiritual ſtrength, ſufficient to ſanctify; now as the <hi>Water</hi> of Baptiſm is changed only by a change of virtue, and quality, it is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent S. <hi>Epiphanius</hi> did not mean that the <hi>Bread</hi> of the <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt</hi> ſhould be deſtroy'd, no more than the <hi>Water</hi> was in Baptiſm; elſe he would not have ſaid,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Incorporea re nihil augetur.</hi> Ariſt. de ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerat. &amp; cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptione. <hi>Ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum vel materiam par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim. Ibid. l.</hi> 2.</note> that the Conſecrated <hi>Bread</hi> was a food, for <hi>accidents</hi> cannot nouriſh, nothing can be fed by that which is not a <hi>Body;</hi> nouriſhment proceeds from a ſubſtance or matter, ſaith <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> and <hi>Boetius. in Praedic.</hi> ſaith, that 'tis impoſſible an accident ſhould paſs into the nature of a ſubſtance, <hi>ut accidens in ſubſtantia naturam tranſeat fieri nullo modo poteſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Gregory Nazianzen,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Greg. Naz.</note> ſpeaking of the miraculous recovery of his Siſter <hi>Gorgonia,</hi> ſpeaks in theſe terms,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Orat.</hi> 11.</note> 
                     <hi>pouring forth a Flood of tears after the example of her that waſhed Chriſt's feet with her tears, ſhe ſaid, ſhe would not depart thence till ſhe had recover'd her health, her tears were the perfume which ſhe ſpread over all his Body, ſhe mingled them with the Antitypes, or the Symbols of the Body and Blood of Jeſus Chriſt, as much at leaſt as ſhe could hold in her hands, and immediately, O the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle, ſhe found her ſelf healed.</hi> And in his ſeventeenth Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, this godly Prelate interceding to the Emperor's Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, that he would extend his favour, and no deliver up the City to be plundred, <hi>I ſet before your Eyes the Table where we joyntly receive the Sacrament, and the figure of my Salvation, which I conſecrate with the ſame Mouth wherewith I make my requeſt to you; this Sacrament, I ſay, which lifts us up to Heaven.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:105312:16"/>
                  <p>It appears by theſe words, that S. <hi>Gregory</hi> lookt upon the Conſecrated <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> as <hi>figures</hi> of the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt:
<note place="margin">Gregory Nazianz.</note> now if they are figures, then they are not that whereof they be figures, and by conſequence, there is in the Sacrament ſomething elſe beſides the <hi>very Body</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, to wit, the <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine,</hi> which are the <hi>Types</hi> and <hi>figures</hi> of it. For to ſay that S. <hi>Gregory</hi> means only that the <hi>accidents</hi> of <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> are the <hi>Types</hi> and <hi>figures,</hi> when he ſaith, his Siſter <hi>mingled her tears with the Antitypes of the Body and Blood of Jeſus Chriſt, as many as ſhe could keep in her hands, Si quid Antityporum pretioſt Corporis aut Sanguinis manus theſauriſaſſet,</hi> theſe words, <hi>as many as ſhe could gather in her hands,</hi> ſignify, as many portions and parts of the Euchariſt as ſhe could gather up, <hi>paululum Euchariſtiae,</hi> as <hi>Euſebius</hi> ſpeaks in the ſixth Book of his Hiſt. chap. 36. as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving gather'd together a little of the Sacrament, and having ſeparated it from a greater Maſs, or from a greater quantity of liquor. Now all antiquity agree, that the <hi>lines,</hi> the <hi>ſuperficies,</hi> the <hi>qualities,</hi> are inſeparable from their <hi>ſubject,</hi> ſo that this little parcel of <hi>Antitypes,</hi> this parcel of the <hi>figures,</hi> cannot be a part of <hi>accidents,</hi> and of <hi>appearances.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Gregory Nyſſen</hi> going to prove that the <hi>Water</hi> of Baptiſm,
<note place="margin">Greg. Nyſſ.</note> for being <hi>Water,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">In his Oration of the Baptiſ. of J.C.</note> ought not to be deſpiſed, but that after Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration it hath a marvellous Virtue, he proves it by the Example of the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> and <hi>extream <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction.</hi>
                     <q>
                        <hi>The Bread,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>before Conſecration is but common Bread, but after Conſecration it is called, and is the Body of Chriſt; ſo alſo the Myſtical Oyl, and Wine, before Benediction, are common things, and of no virtue, but after Benediction, both of them have a great virtue.</hi>
                     </q> Now theſe words ſhew, that the <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> remain after Conſecration; for it appears that St. <hi>Gregory</hi>'s Deſign is to prove, that common and ordinary things have a marvellous force after <hi>Conſecration,</hi> and if the <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy'd after <hi>Conſecration,</hi> what did operate would not be a vile and mean thing, becauſe it would be the <hi>very Body</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, and St. <hi>Gregory</hi> would not well have proved that vile things have any marvellous virtue in them after <hi>Conſecration;</hi> for inſtance, <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine,</hi> which not ſubſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting after Conſecration, could not have the virtue to ſanctify.</p>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:105312:16"/>
                  <p>S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> in his Epiſtle to <hi>Juſtus,</hi> explaining what <hi>Somer</hi> is, ſaith, it is a meaſure, and that this meaſure ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies the quantity of Wine which rejoyces the heart of Man;
<note place="margin">S. Ambroſe</note> and having explain'd the Wine, of the drinking Wiſdom,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>Ep.</hi> 1.</note> Sobriety, and Temperance, he ſaith, <hi>That it is to be underſtood more fully of the Blood of Jeſus Chriſt, which neither admits increaſe, nor decreaſe, as to grace; But of which if one receive more or leſs, the meaſure however of Redemption is equal to all. Plenius de ſanguine intelligitur cujus ad gratiam nihil minuitur, nihil adaugetur, &amp; ſi parum ſumas, &amp; ſi plurimum haurias, eadem perfecta eſt omnibus menſura Redemptionis.</hi> This manner of ſpeaking of taking more or leſs of the <hi>Blood</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, is not to be underſtood of the proper <hi>Body</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, which is indiviſible; there muſt be therefore in the Euchariſt, beſides the <hi>proper Blood</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, a <hi>Typical</hi> and <hi>Symbolical Blood,</hi> which is the <hi>Wine,</hi> which is ſo called, and of which we may ſay, we receive more or leſs.</p>
                  <p>The ſame Father ſaith elſewhere,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Id. Tom.</hi> 4. <hi>de fide l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 5.</note> 
                     <hi>That as often as we receive the Sacraments, which by the virtue of Holy Prayer are transfigur'd into the Fleſh and Blood of Jeſus Chriſt, we ſhew forth the Death of Chriſt.</hi> It is certain that by theſe words, S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> lookt upon the <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> as <hi>figures</hi> of the <hi>Fleſh</hi> and <hi>Blood;</hi> now the <hi>figure</hi> being a thing diſtinct from what it repreſents, as being two correlatives, the one of which is not the other, it muſt be concluded, that S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> believed that there is <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> in the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> which are the <hi>figures</hi> of the <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Heavenly Power.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſame Father ſpeaking of the bleſſing of <hi>Aſer,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Idem Tom.</hi> 1. of the bleſſing of the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchs. c.</hi> 9.</note> explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe Words, <hi>Aſhur his Bread is fat, he ſhall feed Princes; ſaith, Jeſus Chriſt who is Aſhur, that is rich, has nouriſh'd Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. When he multiply'd the five and ſeven Loaves, and gave them to his Apoſtles to diſtribute to the multitude, he every day gives us this Bread,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>when the Prieſt doth conſecrate: we may alſo by this Bread underſtand the Lord himſelf</hi> (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues S. <hi>Ambroſe) who has given us his Fleſh to eat.</hi> By theſe words it appears S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> diſtinguiſhes three ſorts of <hi>Bread</hi> which Jeſus Chriſt gave to theſe Princes; the firſt is that which he gave in multiplying the five and ſeven Loaves, <hi>John</hi> 6. and <hi>Matth.</hi> 15. the ſecond is the <hi>Bread</hi>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:105312:17"/>which the Prieſt conſecrates at <hi>Maſs;</hi> the third is that of which it is ſaid, <hi>I am the Bread of Life,</hi> which is Jeſus Chriſt himſelf.
<note place="margin">Ambroſe.</note> As then the ſecond is not the firſt, ſo neither is the ſecond the third: The <hi>Conſecrated Bread</hi> is another thing than <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>Bread of Life;</hi> and by conſequence, there is in the Sacrament a <hi>Bread</hi> diſtinct from <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>Heavenly Bread.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Gaudentius</hi> upon <hi>Exodus</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">Gaudentius.</note> 
                     <hi>With great reaſon we receive with the Bread the figure of the Body of Chriſt,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Gaud.</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Breſs.</hi> Tract. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</note> becauſe as the Bread is compos'd of many grains, which being ground into Flower is kneaded with Water, and baked by Fire, ſo alſo the Body of Chriſt is made and collected of the whole race of Mankind, and is perfected by the Fire of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> Now as this Author places the figure of the Body of Jeſus Chriſt in that the Bread is made up of ſundry grains, reduced into Meal, kneaded with Water, and baked with fire: it follows, that he believed the <hi>Bread</hi> remained in the <hi>Sacrament,</hi> and ſo much the rather becauſe this Biſhop ſaith elſewhere,
<note place="margin">Chryſoſtome.</note> 
                     <hi>figura noneſt veritas ſed imitatio veritatis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>S. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> expounding theſe words,
<note place="margin">S. <hi>Chryſ. Hom.</hi> 83. on S. Matth.</note>
                     <q>
                        <hi>I will no more drink of this fruit of the vine, until I drink it new in the Kingdom of my Father,</hi> ſaith, <hi>becauſe Jeſus Chriſt had ſpoke to his Diſciples of his Paſſion and of his Death, now he ſpeaks to them of his Reſurrection, making mention of his Kingdom, calling his reſurrection by this name; Now wherefore did Jeſus Chriſt drink after his Reſurrection, fearing leſt ignorant per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſhould think his Reſurrection was only imaginary, becauſe many took the act of drinking as a true ſign of the Reſurrection; Therefore the Apoſtles going to prove his Reſurrection, ſay, we that have eat and drank with him, Jeſus Chriſt. Therefore aſſuring them that they ſhould ſee him after his Reſurrection, and that he would ſtay with them, and that they might bear witneſs of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, might ſee and behold him, tells them, I will no more drink the Fruit of the Vine, until I drink it with you in a new manner, whereof you ſhall bear teſtimony, for you ſhall ſee me after my Reſurrection; But wherefore,</hi> continues S. Chryſoſtom, <hi>did he drink Wine after his Reſurrection and not Water? it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he would thereby deſtroy a pernitious Hereſy. For becauſe there would be Hereticks that would only make uſe of water in the Myſteries, he would repreſent the Myſteries; he gave Wine,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:105312:17"/>and when, after the Reſurrection, he eat his common Repaſt, he drank Wine, the Fruit of the Vine; now the Vine doth produce Wine and not Water.</hi>
                     </q> This Paſſage marketh in the firſt place, That Jeſus Chriſt drinking the <hi>Fruit of the Vine</hi> after his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, and not Water, he accompliſh'd what he ſaid in celebrating the Euchariſt, <hi>I will no more drink of this Fruit of the Vine, until I drink it now in my Fathers Kingdom.</hi> This ſhews that Jeſus Chriſt drank <hi>true Wine</hi> in the Inſtitution of the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> for what is to be done again, muſt needs be done before. Secondly, St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> doth not only ſay that Jeſus Chriſt drank <hi>Wine,</hi> but he ſaith further, That he diſtributed <hi>Wine</hi> amongſt his Diſciples, and <hi>the Fruit of the Vine,</hi> which doth not produce <hi>Water</hi> but <hi>Wine.</hi> So that theſe words of St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> import clearly, That the <hi>Wine</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains in the <hi>Euchariſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſame <hi>Father</hi> on theſe words of the Firſt to the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Idem in Hom.</hi> 24.</note> The Bread which we break is it not the Communion of the Body of Chriſt?</hi> (ſpeaks thus) <hi>What is the Bread? it is the Body of Jeſus Chriſt. What becomes of them which receive it? they become the Body of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Now this Propoſition, <hi>The Bread is the Body of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> cannot be in a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teral Senſe, for ſaith <hi>Vaſquez, The Bread without a Figure, cannot be called the Body of Jeſus Chriſt, nor the Body of Jeſus Chriſt be called Bread.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſame <hi>Father</hi> in his Commentary upon the Epiſtle to the <hi>Galatians,</hi> Chap. 5. explaining theſe words of the Apoſtle, <hi>The Fleſh luſteth againſt the Spirit, and the Spirit againſt the Fleſh;</hi> The <hi>Manicheans</hi> underſtood by the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> the <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the Body,</hi> and by the <hi>Spirit</hi> they underſtood the <hi>Soul;</hi> and they ſaid, That the Apoſtle cut Man into two, and intimated, that Man was compos'd of two contrary Subſtances, one bad, which was the Fleſh; and the other good, which was the Spirit, which proceeded from the good God, and the Body from the bad God.—S. <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtom</hi> anſwers, That the Apoſtle in this place doth not call the Fleſh the Body, <hi>Apoſtolum non hic carnem appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lare Corpus,</hi> as the <hi>Manicheans</hi> ſuppoſed, and ſaith, That the Apoſtle do's not always mean by the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> the <hi>nature of the Body, Naturam Corporis,</hi> but that very often by the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:105312:18"/>
                     <hi>Fleſh,</hi> he means ſomething elſe, as <hi>evil Deſires;</hi> and having proved this by ſundry paſſages of the Apoſtle, and other holy Writers, he proves it at laſt by the example of the <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>uchariſt,</hi> and of the Church, which, he ſaith, is called Body in the Holy Scriptures; he ſaith farther, That the Scripture is wont to call by the name of <hi>Fleſh,</hi> as well the <hi>Church,</hi> as the <hi>Myſteries,</hi> ſaving, It is his Body, <hi>Rurſum Carnis vocabulo Scriptura ſolet appellare tum Myſteria tum totam Eccleſiam, dicens eam Chriſti Corpus eſſe.</hi> It ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by theſe words of St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi>'s, That he did not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that the Conſecrated <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> were the ſame with the <hi>Body</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſeeing he proves by the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> that the <hi>Conſecrated Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> are called <hi>Fleſh;</hi> and that the Word <hi>Fleſh</hi> in this place, is taken for ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe beſides <hi>Body,</hi> and that he puts the Term <hi>Fleſh,</hi> given to the <hi>Conſecrated Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine,</hi> which are the <hi>Myſteries,</hi> in the rank of other Terms of Fleſh given to <hi>evil Deſires,</hi> and to the <hi>Church,</hi> which are <hi>myſtical</hi> and <hi>figurative</hi> Terms. So St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> believed the <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> remained, and are ſo called the <hi>Body</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt <hi>myſtically,</hi> as the <hi>Church is</hi> called the <hi>Body</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>The ſame St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> wrote a Letter to <hi>Caſarius,</hi> which indeed is not inſerted in his Works, but is found in Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuſcript in the Library at <hi>Florence,</hi> and it was alſo found in <hi>England</hi> in <hi>Archbiſhop Cranmer</hi>'s Library, it is men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd in the <hi>Bibliotheca Patrum,</hi> Printed at <hi>Collen,</hi> 1618. in this <hi>Bibliotheque,</hi> Tom. 4. there is found the Collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of an ancient nameleſs Author, who wrote againſt the <hi>Severian,</hi> and <hi>Acephalian</hi> Hereticks, wherein is recited a Paſſage taken out of this Letter. So alſo Monſieur <hi>de Marca</hi> Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Paris,</hi> acknowledges the truth of this Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in his <hi>Poſthume</hi> and <hi>French</hi> Treatiſe of the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> witneſs the Abbot <hi>Fagget</hi> in his Letter to Monſieur <hi>de Marca,</hi> Preſident of the Parliament at <hi>Pau,</hi> who ſaith alſo this Letter was found by Monſieur <hi>Bigot</hi> in a Library at <hi>Florence.</hi> St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> in this Letter writeth againſt <hi>Apol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linarius,</hi> and ſaith,
<q>
                        <hi>Jeſus Chriſt is both God and Man, God becauſe of his Impaſſibility, Man by his Paſſion, one Son,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:105312:18"/>one Lord, both Natures united making but one, the ſame Power, the ſame Dominion; although they be two different Natures, each conſerves its own Nature, becauſe they are two, and yet without confuſion; for as the Bread before it is ſanctified, is called Bread, when by the interceſſion of the Prieſt, Divine Grace has ſanctified it, it loſes the name of Bread, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes worthy to be called the Body of Jeſus Chriſt, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Nature of Bread abides in it, ſo that they are not two Bodies, but one ſole Body of the Son; ſo the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Nature being united to the Humane Nature of Jeſus Chriſt, it did not make two Perſons, but one only Perſon and one Son.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> ſaith plainly, That the <hi>Nature</hi> of <hi>Bread</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bideth after <hi>Conſecration;</hi> and this Father's Argument would be of no validity, if this <hi>nature</hi> of the <hi>Bread</hi> was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but in ſhew, for <hi>Apollinarius</hi> might have made ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther oppoſite Argument, and ſay, That indeed it might be ſaid there were two <hi>Natures</hi> in Jeſus Chriſt, but that the Humane <hi>Nature</hi> was only in appearance, as the <hi>Bread</hi> in the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> is but in <hi>ſhew,</hi> and hath only outward and viſible qualities remaining in it, whereby it is term'd to be <hi>Bread.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Author of the imperfect Work upon St. <hi>Matthew</hi> written in the time of the Emperour <hi>Theodoſius,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">This Author goes under S. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi>'s Name.</note> did not believe <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> when he ſpake in theſe Terms in Homily Eleventh, <hi>If it be dangerous to employ the holy Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels about common uſes, wherein the</hi> true Body <hi>of Jeſus Chriſt is not contain'd, but</hi> the Myſteries <hi>of his</hi> Body; <hi>how much rather the Veſſels of our Bodies, which God has prepared to dwell in.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="century">
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:105312:19"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>That the Fathers of the</hi> FIFTH CENTURY <hi>did not believe</hi> Tranſubſtantiation. <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">AGE </seg>v.</label>
                  </head>
                  <p>S. <hi>Jerom</hi> in his Epiſtle to <hi>Euſtochium</hi> ſpeaking of Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins,
<note place="margin">S. <hi>Jerom.</hi>
                     </note> ſaith, That when they were reproved for Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſs, they excus'd themſelves by adding Sacriledge to Drunkenneſs, ſaying, <hi>God forbid that I ſhould abſtain from the Blood of the Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the Second Book againſt <hi>Jovinian</hi> it is ſaid,
<note place="margin">It appears by theſe words, that they im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon belief, that there was true Wine in the Euchariſt; becauſe they ſay, That ſhould they abſtain from Wine, they muſt abſtain alſo from the Blood of the Lord.</note> 
                     <hi>The Lord in the Type of his Blood, did not offer Water, but Wine.</hi> Theſe words are indeed <hi>Jovinian</hi>'s, but St. <hi>Jerom</hi> finds no fault with them. For he himſelf ſaith the ſame, upon the 31 Chapter of <hi>Jeremy,</hi> Verſ. 12. on theſe Words, <hi>They run after Gods Creatures, the Wheat, the Wine, and the Oyl, the Bread, and the Wine,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>whereof is made the Bread of the Lord, and wherein is accompliſhed the Type of his Blood.</hi> Now ſaith St. <hi>Ambroſe
<note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>De fide l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 5.</note>, The Type is not the Truth, but it is the ſhadow of the Truth.</hi> There muſt then be in the Euchariſt, <hi>Bread,</hi> and <hi>Wine,</hi> diſtinct from the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, to be the <hi>Types</hi> and <hi>Figures</hi> of it.</p>
                  <p>The ſame Father in his Letter to <hi>Hedibia, Let us hear, that the Bread which the Lord broke and gave his Diſciples was the Lord's own Body, ſaying, Take, Eat, This is my Body;</hi> and a little after he ſaith, <hi>If the Bread that came down from Heaven is the Body of the Lord, and the Wine which he diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted among his Diſciples his Blood,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>St. <hi>Jerom</hi> ſaith, That Jeſus Chriſt brake and diſtributed <hi>Bread</hi> to his Diſciples, that he gave them <hi>Bread,</hi> and that the <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> were his <hi>Fleſh</hi> and <hi>Blood.</hi> It cannot then be ſaid, That what Jeſus Chriſt gave in communicating his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples was not <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine;</hi> and when he ſaith, both the one and the other was his <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood,</hi> it cannot be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood but only <hi>figuratively;</hi> for we ſee above in St. <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian,</hi>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:105312:19"/>that the Jeſuites <hi>Salmeron</hi> and <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> do confeſs, That if Jeſus Chriſt ſaid of the Bread, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> it muſt be meant, <hi>This Bread is the Figure of my Body,</hi> the one not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing capable of being the other but <hi>figuratively:</hi> And the Reaſon is given by <hi>Vaſquez,</hi> when he ſaith, <hi>If the Pronoun, This, in the words of Conſecration be underſtood of the Bread, undoubtedly by virtue of it, there can be wrought no Tranſubſtantiation, becauſe of neceſſity the Bread muſt needs remain; Si Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>omen hoc in illis verbis demonſtraret panem, fatemur fore ut nulla converſio vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute illorum fieri poſſet, quia panis de quo enunciatur manere debeat.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſame S. <hi>Jerom</hi> in his Commentary upon the 26 Chapter of St. <hi>Matthew,</hi> ſaith, <hi>Jeſus Chriſt having eaten the Paſchal Lamb, took Bread which ſtrengthens the Heart of Man, and proceeded to the accompliſhment of the Sacrament of the true Paſſover, that as Melchiſedeck had offered Bread and Wine in Figure, he alſo him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf would repreſent the truth of his Body.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>According to this Father, the <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine,</hi> repreſent the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, and therefore are not <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly</hi> and <hi>truly</hi> the <hi>Fleſh</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, but are ſomething elſe beſides them, and by conſequence remain in the Sacrament. For to ſay, as the Author of the Second Book of the <hi>perpetuity of the Faith of the Euchariſt</hi> doth againſt Monſieur <hi>Claude,</hi> that St. <hi>Jerom</hi> means by <hi>repreſenting,</hi> to make a thing be <hi>preſent,</hi> we before refuted this Fancy, in <hi>Tertullian,</hi> who ſpeaks juſt as St. <hi>Jerom:</hi> And the terms ſufficiently declare, that St. <hi>Jerom</hi>'s meaning is, That Jeſus Chriſt made uſe of <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine,</hi> to <hi>ſignifie</hi> and <hi>ſhew forth</hi> his <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood,</hi> as <hi>Melchiſedeck</hi> had done, that is to ſay, as he had <hi>repreſented</hi> both the one and the other by the Oblation of <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> in his Sermon to the newly Baptized,
<note place="margin">St. <hi>Auſtin.</hi>
                     </note> which it's true is not found in his other Works, but was preſerv'd and is cited by "St. <hi>Fulgentius de Baptiſmo Aethiop.</hi> Cap. 7.
<q>
                        <hi>What you ſee,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>upon the Altar of God, you ſaw alſo the laſt Night, but you were not yet aware of how great a thing it is a Sacrament; That which you ſee is Bread, and a Cup of Wine, and it is alſo what your Eyes declare unto you; but what your Faith ſhould inſtruct you in, is, That the Bread is the Body of Jeſus Chriſt, and the Cup his Blood. If you tell me, Jeſus Chriſt is born, he was crucified, he was buried, he roſe again, and is aſcended into Heaven, whither he has carry'd his Body, and is
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:105312:20"/>at preſent on the right hand of God, from whence he ſhall come to judge the quick and the dead, how then can the Bread be his Body, and the Cup his Blood? theſe things, my Brethren, are called Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, becauſe one thing is ſeen in them, and another thing is under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by them? what is ſeen hath a Corporeal Subſtance; what is underſtood hath a Spiritual Fruit. If then you deſire to underſtand what the Body of Jeſus Chriſt is, hearken to the Apoſtle which ſaith, You are the Body of Chriſt and his Members: If then you are the Body of Jeſus Chriſt and his Members, it is the Myſtery of what you are, which is upon the Holy Table, it is the Myſtery of the Lord, which you receive; in ſaying</hi> Amen, <hi>you anſwer and ſubſcribe to what you are. All you that are united in Charity, you make but one Body of Jeſus Chriſt, of which you are the Members, which is what is ſignified by the Bread compos'd of ſeveral Grains, and by the Wine which is made of ſundry Grapes. For as Bread to be made a viſible Species of Bread, is made of ſundry Grains collected together in one, and the Wine,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">St. <hi>Auſtin.</hi>
                     </note> That the <hi>Bread</hi> is the <hi>Body</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which cannot be but <hi>improporly</hi> and <hi>figuratively,</hi> as hath been ſhewed above; for by Confeſſion of <hi>Roman Catholick</hi> Doctors, every Propoſition that ſaith of the <hi>Bread,</hi> That it is the <hi>Body,</hi> muſt needs be <hi>typical</hi> and <hi>figurative.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>He ſaith what is <hi>ſeen</hi> is <hi>Bread,</hi> as our Eyes declare to us; now what our Eyes report to us is true <hi>Bread,</hi> as when one ſays, What you ſee is <hi>true Gold,</hi> and <hi>Silver,</hi> or <hi>Marble,</hi> and 'tis what your <hi>Eyes teſtifie,</hi> that is to ſay, That one ſees <hi>true Gold,</hi> and <hi>true Marble,</hi> and that one makes uſe of their <hi>Eyes</hi> to confirm it.</p>
                  <p>In the ſame ſenſe he ſaith; That Jeſus Chriſt although in Heaven, yet the <hi>Bread</hi> is the <hi>Body,</hi> and the <hi>Wine</hi> the <hi>Blood,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are the <hi>Sacraments</hi> of it.</p>
                  <p>He ſaith, What one ſees hath a <hi>bodily ſpecies;</hi> now in this Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, by <hi>bodily ſpecies,</hi> he means the <hi>very Subſtance,</hi> and not the <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents.</hi> For he ſaith afterwards, ſpeaking of <hi>Bread</hi> in general, as <hi>Bread</hi> to be a viſible <hi>ſpecies of Bread,</hi> muſt be made of ſeveral Grains reduced into one lump; now by the <hi>ſpecies of Bread,</hi> it is plain, St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> there means <hi>true Bread,</hi> and a <hi>true Subſtance.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>He ſaith, What you <hi>ſee,</hi> is <hi>Bread,</hi> and a <hi>Cup;</hi> now by <hi>Cup,</hi> he doth not mean the <hi>appearance of a Cup,</hi> he means a <hi>true Cup.</hi> He ſaith this <hi>Bread</hi> is the <hi>Myſtery</hi> of the Lord. Which is nothing elſe, but that 'tis the <hi>Figure of the Lord,</hi> as when he ſaith, This
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:105312:20"/>
                     <hi>Bread</hi> is the <hi>Myſtery of Believers. Myſterium veſtrum in Menſa Domini accipitis.</hi> That is to ſay, That the <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> are the <hi>Figure</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, as they are the <hi>Myſtical Body</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt. To conclude, St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith, The Faith of the New-baptized was to be ſtrengthened; it was therefore here the proper place for him to have ſaid, That the <hi>Bread</hi> was no more <hi>Bread,</hi> that the <hi>Wine</hi> was no longer <hi>Wine,</hi> but that there remained only the <hi>Accidents</hi> of the one and the other.</p>
                  <p>The ſame Holy Father anſwering Biſhop <hi>Boniface,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ep.</hi> 23. <hi>ad Bonif.</hi>
                     </note> who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to know how it might be ſaid of an Infant newly Baptis'd, he hath <hi>Faith,</hi> he <hi>Believes,</hi> who is incapable of believing, and of whom no aſſurance can be given what he will be afterwards; he ſaith, "<hi>That as every Sunday, and Eaſter Day, is called Eaſter, and the Reſurrection, although the Lords Eaſter, and Reſurrection, are things hapened ſeveral Ages paſt; ſo it may be ſaid, An Infant hath Faith, becauſe he hath the Sacrament of Faith. For, ſaith he, if the Sacraments had not ſome reſemblance with the things whereof they are Sacraments, they would be no Sacraments; as therefore in ſome ſort the Sacrament of the Body of Jeſus Chriſt is the Body of Jeſus Chriſt, and the Sacrament of his Blood, is the Blood of Chriſt, ſo alſo the Sacrament of Faith, is Faith; now to believe, is nothing elſe but to have Faith.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>He ſaith, The <hi>Euchariſt</hi> is called <hi>Fleſh</hi> and <hi>Blood,</hi> becauſe it is both the one and the other in ſome ſort: now according to St. <hi>Gregory Nyſſen,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>De Opif. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 15. <hi>Quod non per omnia eſt id quod eſſe dici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, illud abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive appe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem illam habet.</hi>
                        </note> What is not truly that by the name by which it is called, is but figuratively or improperly that by the name whereof it is called.</hi> Now that the <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> which are the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, are his <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> in ſome ſort, <hi>ſecundum quendam modum,</hi> it follows, The <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> are not <hi>properly</hi> the <hi>Fleſh</hi> and <hi>Blood,</hi> and by conſequence, are not <hi>Tranſubſtantiated.</hi> Moreover St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> doth explain the <hi>Manner</hi> according to which the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> is the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of Chriſt, and he ſhews it, by reaſon that generally the <hi>ſigns</hi> are called by the name of the <hi>things</hi> they <hi>ſignifie,</hi> not that they <hi>are</hi> the <hi>things</hi> they <hi>ſignifie,</hi> but becauſe they are the <hi>ſigns,</hi> and that they have ſome <hi>reſemblance</hi> to them.</p>
                  <p>The ſame Father upon the third <hi>Pſalm,</hi> admires the Patience of Jeſus Chriſt that bore the Treachery of <hi>Judas</hi> to the end, although he was not ignorant of his Thoughts, and admitted him to the Banquet, at which, ſaith St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> Jeſus Chriſt
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:105312:21"/>recommended and gave to his Diſciples, the <hi>Figure</hi> or <hi>Type</hi> of his <hi>Fleſh</hi> and <hi>Blood, Cum adhibuit ad convivium, in quo Corporis &amp; Sanguinis ſui Figuram Diſcipulis commendavit &amp; tradidit.
<note place="margin">St. <hi>Auſtin.</hi>
                        </note> Now the Figure is not the Truth, but the Imitation of the Verity, ſaith</hi> Gaudentius <hi>in Exod. Tractatu</hi> 2. Moreover, St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> cannot find in the Scriptures, that Jeſus Chriſt in inſtituting the Sacrament, gave to his Diſciples the <hi>Figure</hi> of his <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood,</hi> but in theſe words, <hi>Take, Eat, This is my Body, This is my Blood,</hi> he muſt then underſtand theſe words of the Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, in a figurative ſenſe. And according to the ſame Doctor, a
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>De Princip. Dialect l.</hi> 5. <hi>Signum eſt quod ſeipſum ſenſibus, &amp; praeter ſe ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid animo oſtendit.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Sign is that which ſhews it ſelf to the Senſes, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that ſhews ſomething elſe to the Mind;</hi> It muſt then follow, That the Sign is a thing which remains, to ſhew it ſelf.</p>
                  <p>The ſame Father diſputing againſt <hi>Adimantus</hi> the <hi>Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chean,</hi> Chap. 12. and againſt the Adverſary of the Law and the Prophets, in the Second Book, Cap. 6. who ſaid, The <hi>Blood</hi> is the <hi>Soul,</hi> as is ſaid, <hi>Deuteronom.</hi> 12. and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, that Men killed the <hi>Soul</hi> when they ſhed <hi>Blood.</hi> S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi> replies, That this Precept in <hi>Deuteronomy,</hi> That <hi>Blood</hi> muſt not be eat, becauſe 'tis the <hi>Soul,</hi> is a Precept that muſt he underſtood as many other things contained in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, which are to be taken in <hi>Types,</hi> and <hi>Figures, Illud praeceptum poſitum eſſe dicimus ſicut alia multa &amp; pene omnia Scripturarum illarum Sacramenta ſignis &amp; figuris plena ſunt.</hi> And concludes towards the end of that Chapter, That the <hi>Blood</hi> is the <hi>Soul,</hi> as the <hi>Rock</hi> was <hi>Chriſt, Sanguis eſt Anima quomodo petra erat Chriſtus.</hi> And upon <hi>Leviticus, Queſt.</hi> 54. <hi>The thing which ſignifies, is wont to be called by the name of the thing ſignified, as 'tis written, the Rock was Chriſt: For 'tis not ſaid, The Rock ſignifi'd Chriſt, but as if it were that which indeed it was not in ſubſtance, but only in ſignification.</hi> And as in the beginning of the Chapter he ſaith, <hi>That it muſt be underſtood in the Sign, Jeſus Chriſt making no difficulty to ſay, This is my Body, when he gave the Sign of his Body. San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guis eſt Anima, praeceptum illud eſt in ſigno poſitum, non enim Dominus dubitavit dicere, Hoc eſt Corpus meum, cum daret ſignum Corporis ſui.</hi> Seeing then St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> doth ſay, That the <hi>Blood</hi> is the <hi>Soul,</hi> as the <hi>Rock</hi> was Chriſt; and as the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> is the <hi>Sign</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, he muſt of neceſſity have under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the Words of Inſtitution of the Sacrament, in a figura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:105312:21"/>ſenſe; and that ſo much the rather, becauſe this manner of ſpeech, <hi>Jeſus Chriſt made no difficulty,</hi> plainly ſhews, that Jeſus Chriſt did not ſpeak in a <hi>proper</hi> but in a <hi>figurative ſenſe,</hi> as <hi>Fulgentius</hi> ſaith, <hi>Although the Apoſtle ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ad Monym. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 10. <hi>cum Electionis Vas dicat quia Chriſtus caput eſt corporis Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae, ipſum tamen corpus Chriſti non du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitat Chriſtus veraciter ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellare. Ad Paulin. Ep</hi> 59.</note> That Jeſus Chriſt is the Head of the Body of the Church, nevertheleſs he makes no Scruple to call Jeſus Chriſt the Church, which is his Body.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This manner of ſpeech is never uſed in <hi>proper</hi> expreſſions: no Body will ſay, Jeſus Chriſt made <hi>no difficulty</hi> to give <hi>Gold,</hi> or <hi>Water,</hi> if it were <hi>true Gold</hi> or <hi>Water</hi> which he gave.</p>
                  <p>The ſame holy <hi>Doctor</hi> ſaith in ſeveral places after the Apoſtle, That the <hi>Bread</hi> in the Sacrament after Conſecration, is <hi>bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken,</hi> and <hi>diſtributed;</hi> and he doth very well recommend this breaking the Bread, as being a great myſtery. In his Epiſtle to <hi>Paulinus,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>In that Jeſus Chriſt was known by the two Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples in breaking the Bread, no body ought to queſtion but this breaking was the Sacrament whereby Jeſus Chriſt brings us all to the knowledge of his Perſon.</hi> A little before he ſaith; <hi>By the</hi> Prayers, <hi>we mean thoſe which are ſaid before one begins to bleſ; what is upon the Lords Table. The Prayers</hi> are ſaid when that which is on the Lords. Table is bleſsed, ſanctifyed, and diſtributed. In his Epiſtle to <hi>Caſulaus</hi> he ſaith of S. <hi>Paul,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ep.</hi> 86.</note> that in the night time he went <hi>to break Bread,</hi> as it is broken in the <hi>Sacrament</hi> of his <hi>Body.</hi> In his Commentary upon the firſt Ep. of S. <hi>John,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Tract.</hi> 2.</note> It was very reaſonable that Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt recommending his Fleſh, <hi>broke Bread,</hi> and it was very juſt that the Diſciples knew him in <hi>breaking of Bread.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the 140. Sermon <hi>de temp:</hi> and in the Hom. Of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of Evangeliſts, lib. 3. c. 25. and <hi>de diverſis,</hi> Serm. 87. he ſaith, <hi>Where would Jeſus Chriſt be known? In the breaking of Bread. We are then ſecure; we break Bread, and we know the Lord.</hi> If then after conſecration we <hi>break Bread</hi> to diſtribute, then of neceſſity the <hi>Bread</hi> muſt remain: for to ſay that 'tis the <hi>accidents</hi> which are <hi>broken,</hi> and <hi>diſtributed,</hi> S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> doth fay the contrary, when he affirms, that one <hi>breaks</hi> and <hi>diſtributes</hi> what is on the Table, being <hi>bleſſed</hi> and <hi>ſanctify'd.</hi> Now to <hi>bleſs</hi> and <hi>ſanctify,</hi> one ſhall never find to have ſignifi'd to <hi>deſtroy,</hi> and <hi>change the ſubſtance.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſame Doctor in ſeveral places does always call the Euchariſt, <hi>the Sacrament of Bread and Wine,</hi> he ſaith, S.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>De conſenſu Evangeliſt. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 25.</note> 
                     <hi>Paul</hi> doth teach the unity of the Church in the <hi>Sacrament of</hi> Bread, when he ſaith, <hi>We are all one Bread, and one Body.</hi> In the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:105312:22"/>queſtions upon the Evangeliſts, he ſaith, <hi>Jeſus Chriſt by the Sacrament of Wine, recommends his Blood.</hi> In his Books againſt, <hi>Fauſtus, we are very far from doing what the Heathens did for their Gods,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>q.</hi> 43.</note> Ceres <hi>and</hi> Bacchus, <hi>although we have a ceremony of celebrating the Sacrament of Bread and Wine.
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>l.</hi> 20. <hi>c.</hi> 13.</note> Now to what end were it to call the Euchariſt a Sacrament of Bread and Wine,</hi> if there did not remain <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> after <hi>Conſecration?</hi> for what means this manner of ſpeech, the <hi>Sacrament</hi> of <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine,</hi> but the <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> which is the <hi>Sacrament?</hi> As when the Apoſtle ſaith, Rom. 4. v. 11. <hi>the ſign of Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</hi> What elſe doth this import, but the <hi>Circumciſion</hi> which is the <hi>ſign?</hi> When <hi>Tertullian de Baptiſmo,</hi> calls Baptiſm <hi>Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum aquae noſtrae:</hi> What elſe can that mean, but our <hi>Water</hi> which is a <hi>Sacrament?</hi> When S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> upon S. <hi>John</hi> Tract. 11. ſaith, The <hi>figure</hi> of the <hi>Sea, figura Maris</hi> What more can this ſignify, but the <hi>Sea</hi> which is the <hi>figure?</hi> When it is frequently ſaid, the <hi>Sacrament of the Euchariſt,</hi> what elſe can that import, but the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> which is a <hi>Sacrament?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſame Father in his 52 Sermon,
<note place="margin">Penè quidem Sacramentum omnes corpus ejus dicunt.</note> 
                     <hi>de verbis Domini,</hi> ſaith, <hi>almoſt all do call the Sacrament the Body of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Now if the <hi>Bread</hi> were the <hi>real Body</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, wherefore ſhould S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve that all called it the <hi>Body</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt? For one cannot make ſuch a remark, but when one ſaith of a thing, that 'tis that which properly it is not. It would be ridiculous to ſay, almoſt all call <hi>Lewis</hi> 14. King; &amp; the reaſon is, becauſe 'tis not ſtrange that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſhould be called by their names: but on the contrary, it is very ſtrange, to call one by a name that doth not at all belong to him.</p>
                  <p>The ſame <hi>Father</hi> in his 26. Treatiſe upon S. <hi>John,</hi> going to ſhew upon theſe words of the Apoſtle, <hi>They did all eat the ſame Spiritual meat, and drink the ſame Spiritual drink: The</hi> rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and difference there is betwixt the Sacraments of the old and new Teſtament, ſaith, <hi>The Fathers did eat the ſame ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual food as we do, not the ſame corporal food as we do; becauſe they did eat Manna, and as for us, we eat ſomething elſe; They drank the ſame ſpiritual drink we do, the ſame as to the ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but different as to viſible and outward kind.</hi> And upon S. <hi>John,</hi> Treatiſe 45. <hi>If you conſider the viſible ſpecies, it was another drink, if you conſider what was ſignify'd by their drink, and ours, it was one and the ſame thing. Si ſpeciem viſibilem intendas aliud eſt, ſi intelligibilem ſignificationem, eundem potum ſpirituaiem biberunt.</hi>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:105312:22"/>And upon the 77. Pſalm, <hi>Their food was the very ſame with ours, the ſame as to what it ſignify'd, but different in kind. Idem in myſterio cibus illorum qui noſter; Sed ſignificatione idem, non ſpecie.</hi> This reaſoning does intimate, That the Fathers under the old Teſtament did, and we now do eat a corporal food, and that we drink a corporal liquor. Now by this corporal meat and drink, we muſt underſtand either the <hi>accidents</hi> of <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine,</hi> or the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, or the <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine it ſelf.</hi> It cannot be ſpoken of the firſt, becauſe the <hi>accidents</hi> of Bread and Wine are only <hi>qualities,</hi> or <hi>dimenſions;</hi> now <hi>qualities</hi> and <hi>dimenſions</hi> are not <hi>corporal.</hi> The <hi>quality</hi> is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing which is <hi>incorporeal,</hi> ſaith <hi>Nemeſius,</hi> of the Soul; as concerning <hi>dimenſions,</hi> S. <hi>Auſtin de geneſi ad literam,</hi> ſaith, <hi>We call that a Body which taketh up ſome ſpace by its length, by its breadth, and by its depth. Nemeſius</hi> gives the reaſon of it, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>nothing that is immaterial is a Body, for all Bodies are material.</hi> There being nothing material then in the Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt, as is ſuppos'd, there being nothing that takes up place, that is large or long, or deep; There is nothing corporeal in the Sacrament, and by conſequence, nothing that can be ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med corporal meat or drink. Moreover, when Jeſus Chriſt ſpeaks of corporal nouriſhment and drink in the Euchariſt, as the Fathers under the old Teſtament had done, he ſpeaks of bodily meat and drink, S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> did not underſtand the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral meat and drink ſpoke of by the Fathers of the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to be only the <hi>accidents</hi> of one and the other, ſo that S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſpeaking in the ſame terms of bodily meat and drink, in relation to that of the Antients, he did not mean meer acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents or qualities. The <hi>Body of Jeſus Chriſt</hi> nor his <hi>Blood,</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be this corporal nouriſhment which S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> compares to that of the Fathers under the Law: for by bodily meat and drink which he ſaith we receive in the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> he means a viſible ſubject, <hi>aliud illi, aliud nos, ſed ſpecie viſibili, ſiſpeciem viſibilem inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das, aliud eſt.</hi> It remains then that in S. <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s ſenſe, we un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand by the <hi>corporal nature</hi> of the Euchariſt the <hi>viſible Bread,</hi> the <hi>viſible Wine,</hi> and not their <hi>qualities</hi> and <hi>accidents.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſame Father in the third Book of the Trin. cap. 10. ſpeaking of things that are taken to ſignify, ſaith, <hi>a thing is taken to ſignify, either after ſuch a manner, as that the thing ſhould ſubſiſt and remain ſome time, as did the Brazen Serpent, lift up in
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:105312:23"/>the Wilderneſs, or as do the letters of the Alphabet, or in ſuch a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as the thing taken to ſignify is not to ſubſiſt any long time, but is to paſs away and be deſtroy'd when the thing 'tis to repreſent is paſſed away; as the Bread of the Sacrament, which being taken to ſignify paſſeth away and is conſumed in receiving the Sacrament.</hi> S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> there ſaith, That the Bread of the Sacrament which is taken to ſignify, paſſeth and is conſumed in receiving the Sacrament; Now if the Bread be deſtroyed and Tranſubſtantiated by theſe words, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> then it paſſeth not away, and is not conſumed in the act of receiving.</p>
                  <p>The ſame Doctor in the ſeventeenth <hi>Of the City of God</hi> ſaith, <hi>To eat Bread, is in the New Teſtament the ſacrifice of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians;</hi> and againſt the Enemy of the Law. l. 7. c. 20. <hi>Thoſe,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>which read know what Melchiſedeck offered where he bleſſed Abraham, and thoſe which are partakers, ſee that the like ſacrifice is now offer'd through all the World.</hi> How is it that the Sacrifice of Chriſtians, is to <hi>eat Bread,</hi> if the <hi>Bread</hi> do not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main? How is it that communicating, one is partaker of what <hi>Melchiſedeck</hi> offer'd, if in communicating, one do not receive neither <hi>Bread,</hi> nor <hi>Wine?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſame Father in the third Book againſt <hi>Parmenian,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> for forſaking the Church, tells them, S. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> and the other Biſhops, did not ſeparate themſelves becauſe they would not communicate with covetous perſons, and Uſurers; <hi>but that on the contrary, they did eat with them the Bread of the Lord, and drank his Cup.</hi> This paſſage ſheweth, that when S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaid to the new Baptiſed, as hath been ſhewn, that the <hi>Bread</hi> is the <hi>Body</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, it could not be underſtood but <hi>figuratively:</hi> for here the <hi>Bread</hi> is ſaid to be of the <hi>Lord;</hi> now ſaith S. <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> that which is another's is not that other himſelf, to whom it belongs. <hi>Id quod ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cujus eſt, non idipſum eſt cujus eſt.</hi> And S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> elſewhere diſtinguiſheth betwixt the <hi>Bread</hi> which belongs to the Lord, and the <hi>Bread</hi> which is the Lord.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>In Joan. Tract.</hi> 59.</note> Speaking of <hi>Judas</hi> and the other Apoſtles, he ſaith of the Apoſtles, they ate the <hi>Bread</hi> which was the Lord; and of <hi>Judas,</hi> He did eat the <hi>Bread of the Lord</hi> againſt the Lord; they ate life, he Death; for 'tis ſaid by S. <hi>Paul,</hi> That he which <hi>eateth unworthily, eateth his own judgment and condemnation.</hi> Seeing then that the Euchariſt is diſtinguiſh'd from the Lord, it neceſſarily follows, That <hi>Bread</hi> remains in the Sacrament after Conſecration.</p>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:105312:23"/>
                  <p>The ſame Father in his 33 Sermon of the Words of our Lord, ſaith,
<q>
                        <hi>The Lord gave to his Diſciples the Bleſſed Sacrament with his own hands, but we were not at the Banquet; nevertheleſs by faith we daily eat the ſame Supper; and do not think that it had been any great advantage to have been preſent at that Supper that he gave with his own hands to his Diſciples, without Faith; Faith afterwards was of greater advantage than treachery was then; St.</hi> Paul <hi>who believed, was not there preſent, and</hi> Judas <hi>who betray'd his Maſter, was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. How many be there now that come to the Communien, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they did not ſee that Table, and though they never ſaw with their Eyes, nor taſted with their Palate, the Bread which the Lord held in his hands, nevertheleſs, becauſe the ſame Supper is ſtill prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, do there eat and drink their own damnation?</hi>
                     </q> It plainly appears, That the <hi>Bread</hi> which St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith our Saviour had in his hands during the <hi>Sacrament,</hi> was <hi>true Bread,</hi> becauſe St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith, that thoſe who at preſent participate of the Sacrament, do not <hi>Taſt,</hi> nor <hi>Eat</hi> the <hi>Bread</hi> which our Saviour held in his hands, and which he diſtributed, and of which the Diſciples did formerly eat.</p>
                  <p>The ſame Father teaching that the Good might participate of the Divine Sacraments with the Wicked, ſaith,
<note place="margin">Lib. Con. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat. <hi>c.</hi> 6. de ipſo quippe Pane, de ipſa Dominica Manu, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </note> Judas <hi>and</hi> Peter <hi>had each of them a part of the ſame Bread, which they received at the ſame hand of the Lord; and nevertheleſs what ſociety or likeneſs was there betwixt</hi> Peter <hi>and</hi> Judas? <hi>In the</hi> 7th chap. <hi>the wicked and the good hear the ſame Word of God, do partake of the ſame Sacraments, and eat the ſame holy nouriſhment.</hi> Now what is this holy Food? What is this <hi>Bread,</hi> whereof one receives one Portion, and another, another Part? Are they <hi>Accidents?</hi> But <hi>Accidents</hi> are neither <hi>Bread</hi> nor <hi>Food.</hi> It is not the <hi>real Body</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, for it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be received by Parcels; it muſt then be <hi>true Bread</hi> which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains after Conſecration, and which is, as is ſaid before, <hi>Bleſſed, Sanctified,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ep.</hi> 59.</note> and <hi>Broke</hi> in Pieces on the Holy Table to be diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. <hi>Benedicitur, &amp; Sanctificatur, &amp; ad diſtribuendum comminuitur.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſame Doctor in <hi>Ep.</hi> 120,
<note place="margin">Et ipſi qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem adducti ſunt ad Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam Chriſti, &amp;c.</note> ſpeaking of the Rich in oppoſition to the Poor, of whom it is ſaid, That <hi>they ſhall eat and be ſatisfied. Theſe Rich Perſons,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Auſtin, have been brought to the Lords Table, and receive from his hand his Body and Blood, but they only adore, and are not ſatisfied.</hi> For juſt as St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> diſtinguiſheth betwixt drinking the Wine, <hi>Vinum bibere;</hi> and drinking <hi>of</hi> the Wine, <hi>de Vino bibere;</hi> that is to ſay, to taſt of a little Wine,
<note place="margin">De Noe &amp; Arca. <hi>c.</hi> 29.</note> 
                     <hi>de ejus portione libare;</hi> ſo alſo St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> his Diſciple, diſtinguiſheth
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:105312:24"/>betwixt receiving the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of the Lord, <hi>accipere Corpus &amp; Sanguinem Domini,</hi> and to receive <hi>of the Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of the Lord, <hi>Accipere de Corpore &amp; Sanguine Chriſti.</hi> St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> explains himſelf more fully, when he ſaith in his 86th <hi>Ep.</hi> That one re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives in the Euchariſt a Portion of the <hi>Body</hi> of the immaculate Lamb, <hi>De Agni immaculati Corpore partem ſumere:</hi> And in the 35th Sermon on the Words of our Lord, he ſaith, <hi>In receiving the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, we know what we ſhould think of, we receive a little, and we are fatned in the heart, modulum accipimus &amp; in corde ſaginamur.</hi> Now that cannot be underſtood of the <hi>proper Body</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, which cannot be received by Parcels; therefore it muſt be meant of <hi>Bread,</hi> which is the <hi>Figure</hi> of his <hi>Body,</hi> or the <hi>Sacrament</hi> of it. It is what St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> intends, when he ſaith, <hi>Nec quando manduca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> (when we eat Jeſus Chriſt) <hi>de illo partes facimus; equidem in Sacramento ſic fit.</hi> We do not make Morſels, but it is done in Sacrament, that is to ſay, That we break and divide the <hi>Sign</hi> and the <hi>Bread,</hi> which is the Sacrament.</p>
                  <p>The ſame Father ſaying that the <hi>Accidents</hi> cannot in any wiſe ſubſiſt without their <hi>Subject,</hi> ſaith in his 2d Book of Soliloquies, chap. 12. <hi>What can reconcile what you demand? or who can think it poſſible to be done, that that which is in a ſubject ſhould remain, the ſubject it ſelf ceaſing to be? For 'tis a thing monſtrous, and very far from the truth, that that which doth not ſubſiſt, if it be not in a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, can be, the ſubject it ſelf not remaining.</hi> Alſo in the 13th chap. 19th Book, and in the Book of the Immortality of the Soul, <hi>ch.</hi> 5. <hi>The ſubject being changed, of neceſſity all that was in the ſubject muſt be changed.</hi> In the 8th chap. <hi>What is not of it ſelf, if it be abando<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by that by which it is, muſt undoubtedly ceaſe to be.</hi> Alſo in the 10th <hi>chap.</hi> and in the Book of Categories, ſpeaking of <hi>Accidents, A colour cannot be without a ſubject.</hi> And in the Epiſtle to <hi>Darda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, Take away the bodies from the qualities of bodies, they will have no place to remain in, and by conſequence it is neceſſary that they cannot be.</hi> And againſt <hi>Julian,</hi> chap. 5. <hi>It's true,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Auſtin, that the things that are in a ſubject as the qualities are, cannot be without the ſubject wherein they are, as the colour or form,</hi> &amp;c. It's impoſſible, had St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> believed that the <hi>Bread</hi> did not remain in the <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt</hi> after Conſecration, that he ſhould have eſteemed that ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd and ridiculous which happened every day. It alſo ſeems that St <hi>Auſtin</hi> had been too wide, when he doubts in the 146th <hi>Ep.</hi> to <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentius;</hi> Whether Jeſus Chriſt has <hi>Blood,</hi> when he ſaith on the 98th
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:105312:24"/>Pſalm, <hi>You ſhall not eat this Body which you ſee, nor ſhall drink this Blood, which thoſe that ſhall crucify me ſhall ſhed, I have given you a Sacrament,</hi> &amp;c And in the 20th Book againſt <hi>Fauſtus, The Fleſh and Blood of this Sacrifice was promiſed by Sacrifices of reſemblance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the coming of Jeſus Chriſt; It was given by the verity in the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Jeſus Chriſt; after the Aſcenſion of Jeſus Chriſt, it is celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Sacrament of Commemoration.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To conclude, St <hi>Auſtin</hi> in his 33d Sermon on <hi>the Words of our Lord,</hi> having ſaid, as hath been ſeen before, That of things which are put to ſignify, there are ſome that are to remain, others to be deſtroy'd, when the Miniſtry of their ſignification is accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh'd; as the <hi>Bread</hi> of the Sacrament; he adds, <hi>But becauſe theſe things are obvious to men, as being practis'd by men, they may deſerve our veneration, as being Holy and Religious things; but they cannot cauſe any wonder in us, as if they were miraculous.</hi> Certainly if St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> had held <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> as it comprehends many things repugnant to Natural Reaſon, which are ſo many aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Miracles, St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> could not have ſaid, That the Sacraments, wherein he includes that of the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> have ſomething in them that deſerves our <hi>reſpect and veneration;</hi> but have nothing that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves our <hi>aſtoniſhment and admiration.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe are ſome of the Reaſons which made Monſieur <hi>De Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca,</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Paris,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>French.</hi> Poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hum. Treatiſe of the Euch.</note> Predeceſſor to him that with ſo much reputation now fills the chiefeſt See of <hi>France,</hi> ſay, That the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Doctors are to blame, when they pretend that St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded the Text of the Inſtitution of the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> as it is done in the Schools. And a little before; that in St. <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s Divinity, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> ſhould be expounded in this manner, <hi>This Bread is the ſign and Sacrament of my Body:</hi> For according to St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> ſaith Monſieur <hi>De Marca,</hi> The <hi>Bread,</hi> to ſpeak properly, is but the <hi>ſign</hi> and <hi>Sacrament</hi> of the <hi>Body,</hi> to which Jeſus Chriſt made no ſcruple to give the name of the thing ſignified. It is alſo the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Tertullian,</hi> when he ſaith, <hi>When Jeſus Chriſt ſaid, this is my Body, That is to ſay, this is the figure of my Body;</hi> and ſaith Monſieur <hi>De Marca,</hi> The reaſons that are given to the contrary, are not ſatisfactory.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Bullenger</hi> writing againſt <hi>Caſaubon,</hi> recites this paſſage of <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doret,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Theodoret.</note> who was a Prieſt at <hi>Antioch,</hi> in the year <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>As the King,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>and his Image are not two Kings; ſo alſo the perſonal Body of Jeſus Chriſt, which Body is in the Heavens, and the Bread which is
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:105312:25"/>his Antitype, and is diſtributed to Believers by the Prieſt, are not two Bodies.</hi> It appears by this compariſon, that <hi>Theodoret</hi> did believe the <hi>Bread</hi> of the Euchariſt is ſomething elſe beſides the <hi>Body</hi> of Chriſt; and by conſequence, he believed that there remained <hi>true Bread</hi> in the Sacrament, and not <hi>Bread</hi> in <hi>ſhew</hi> and <hi>appearance</hi> only.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Theodoret,</hi> who in the year 423 was <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Cyrus,</hi> doth ſo fully explain himſelf hereupon, that there is no doubt to be made of his Opinion,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dial.</hi> 1.</note> 
                     <hi>He was pleas'd,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that thoſe who participated of the Divine Myſteries, ſhould not have any regard to the nature of the things that are ſeen; but that they ſhould believe by the change of Names, the change that is made by Grace: For having called his</hi> Body, Wheat <hi>and</hi> Bread, <hi>and having called himſelf a</hi> Vine, <hi>he honours the</hi> viſible Symboles <hi>with the name of his</hi> Body <hi>and</hi> Blood, <hi>not in changing their</hi> Nature, <hi>but in adding</hi> Grace <hi>to their</hi> Nature. He could not more fully expreſs that he did not hold <hi>Tranſubſtantiation.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Arnobius <hi>ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Arnobius</hi> the younger, who wrote in the year 431. upon the 4th <hi>Pſalm</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">Accipimus frumentum, &amp;c. Quod nunc ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beat intra ſe Eccleſia vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amus, &amp;c.</note> ſpeaking of the Sacrament, <hi>We have received Wheat in the Body, Wine in the Blood, and Oil in the Chriſm.</hi> On the 22d <hi>Pſalm,</hi> and on the 51ſt, and 54th <hi>Pſalms;</hi> Let us ſee what the Church keepeth; She hath a Table, from which ſhe gives <hi>Bread</hi> to Believers; ſhe hath <hi>Oil,</hi> wherewith ſhe refreſheth the Head, <hi>in libertatem conſcientiae praeſumenti,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>On <hi>Pſalm</hi> 103. We receive <hi>Bread</hi> becauſe it ſtrengthens the Body;
<note place="margin">Accipimus pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem quod con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmat, &amp;c.</note> we receive <hi>Wine,</hi> becauſe it rejoyces the Heart; and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving received double comfort in the Heart, our Faces are made ſhine by the Oil of Chriſm.
<note place="margin">Exurgens a Mortuis, &amp;c.</note> To conclude, on <hi>Pſalm</hi> 104. he ſaith theſe words, ſpeaking of the Lord, <hi>That the Lord in the Euchariſt gives us the ſpecies of Bread and Wine, as he doth the ſpecies of Oil in Baptiſm;</hi> which cannot be underſtood of appearances and <hi>Accidents,</hi> as the terms of <hi>ſpecies of Oil</hi> cannot be taken for the <hi>Accidents</hi> and appearances of <hi>Oil.</hi> Moreover, he obſerves we receive in the Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine,</hi> as we receive <hi>Oil</hi> in the Holy <hi>Chriſm;</hi> Now in the <hi>Holy Chriſm,</hi> it is true <hi>Oil</hi> that we receive; <hi>Arnobius</hi> then could not reaſon ſo, if he believed <hi>Tranſubſtantiation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Author of the Books of the <hi>Promiſes and Predictions of God,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Proſper.</note> attributed to St. <hi>Proſper</hi> by <hi>Caſſiodorus,</hi> and which were written about the year 450, under the Empire of <hi>Valentinian</hi> the 3d, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates a Hiſtory of a young unchaſt Girl that was poſſeſſed with the Devil, who in Communicating, had received a little morſel of the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:105312:25"/>Lords Body, which the Prieſt had moiſtned; it was half an hour before ſhe could ſwallow it down, till ſuch time as the Prieſt tou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ched her throat with the Chalice; then ſhe cried out inſtantly that ſhe was healed. After which, Prayers being made for her, ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived a portion of the Sacrifice, and was reſtor'd to her former health. Theſe terms <hi>of ſome portion of the Sacrifice,</hi> and of a little <hi>part</hi> of the moiſtned <hi>Body</hi> of the Lord by the Prieſt, cannot be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of the <hi>true Body</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt; of neceſſity then the <hi>Bread</hi> by this Author muſt be called by the name of the <hi>Body</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt; and by conſequence he believed it remained in the Sacrament after Conſecration.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Heſychius,</hi> one of the Prieſts of the Church of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Heſychius.</note> in the year 480, ſaith in the ſecond Book on <hi>Leviticus, ch.</hi> 8. <hi>This My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery</hi> (ſpeaking of the <hi>Euchariſt) is at once Bread and Fleſh, Illud Myſterium ſimul panis &amp; caro.</hi> In this ſame place he ſaith, it was the cuſtom of the Church of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> in his time, to burn what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained after the Communion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Procopius</hi> of <hi>Gaza,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Procopius Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zaeus.</note> who in all likelihood wrote in the end of the fifth Century, expounding theſe words of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> where <hi>Jacob</hi> ſaith of <hi>Juda, His eyes be red with wine, and his teeth white with milk, &amp;c.</hi> applying them to our Bleſſed Saviour in the Myſtery of the Sacrament, ſaith, <hi>that 'tis a metaphor taken from thoſe that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving drank, are the merrier for it, &amp;c.</hi> and ſaith that the holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures would denote the gladneſs which the Lord left to his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples in giving them the <hi>Myſtical Wine</hi> by the words of Inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Take, drink ye all of this: Theſe words,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>do ſhew that Jeſus Chriſt doth with mercy look on all thoſe that believe in him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe 'tis the nature of wine to make every one merry.</hi> And upon theſe words, <hi>his teeth are white as milk; milk,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>doth denote to us the whiteneſs and purity of the myſtical nouriſhment; for Jeſus Chriſt gave to his Diſciples the Image of his true Body; not deſiring any of the bloody ſacrifices of the Law, he would by the white teeth, ſignifie to us the purity of the food wherewith we are nouriſhed; for according to holy</hi> David, <hi>Sacrifice and burnt-offerings thou wouldeſt not, but a Body haſt thou prepared me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>When <hi>Procopius</hi> ſpeaketh of the <hi>Myſtical Wine</hi> that rejoyced the Diſciples, it being the nature of <hi>Wine</hi> to <hi>make merry;</hi> this <hi>Myſtical Wine</hi> is not the <hi>Blood</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, for 'tis not the nature of <hi>Blood</hi> to rejoyce. It muſt therefore be meant, that <hi>Procopius</hi> ſaid, by the <hi>Wine</hi> which Jeſus Chriſt diſtributed to his Diſciples, was to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:105312:26"/>
                     <hi>true Wine;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Procopius.</note> and by the <hi>whiteneſs</hi> of the <hi>Myſtical food,</hi> he meant the whiteneſs of the <hi>Bread</hi> which is both food and Image, which cannot be underſtood of the <hi>true Body</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, is neither the <hi>Image</hi> of himſelf, nor <hi>bodily food;</hi> nor of the acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, which cannot nouriſh the Body, becauſe nouriſhment pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth from matter.</p>
                  <p>The ſame <hi>Procopius</hi> in his Commentary on <hi>Eſay,</hi> expounding theſe words of the Prophet, <hi>Chap.</hi> 3. <hi>The Lord of Hoſts will take away from Judah and Jeruſalem the ſtaff of Bread and Water;</hi> ſaith, that in the firſt place theſe words of the Prophet may be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of Jeſus Chriſt, and of his <hi>Fleſh</hi> and <hi>Blood.</hi> The <hi>Bread</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be underſtood of him of whom <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>He gave them bread from Heaven;</hi> and the waters, of thoſe of which Jeſus Chriſt ſaid to the <hi>Samaritan, Whoſoever drinketh of this water, it ſhall be a fountain flewing unto everlaſting Life.</hi> Then he adds, <hi>There is another bread which giveth life to the world, which was taken from the Jews; and another water, which is that of Baptiſm.</hi> Now by this <hi>other bread</hi> which was taken from the <hi>Jews,</hi> he means that of the <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt;</hi> and whereas he diſtinguiſhes it from the <hi>bread,</hi> which is the <hi>Lord,</hi> as he diſtinguiſheth the <hi>water</hi> of Baptiſm from that which was given to the <hi>Samaritan;</hi> it follows, that the <hi>Bread</hi> of the <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charist</hi> is ſomething that is diſtinguiſht from Jeſus Chriſt himſelf, the <hi>Bread</hi> of Heaven.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Gelaſius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">P. <hi>Gelaſius.</hi>
                     </note> in the year 492, wrote a Treatiſe of the <hi>two Natures</hi> againſt <hi>Neſtorius</hi> and <hi>Eutyches,</hi> and he excludes <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> when he ſaith, <hi>that the ſubſtance or nature of Bread and Wine doth ſtill remain.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This Work is aſſuredly of Pope <hi>Gelaſius,</hi> as is confeſſed by Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal <hi>Du Perron,</hi> becauſe firſt <hi>Fulgentius</hi> cites four paſſages of this Treatiſe as being writ by Pope <hi>Gelaſius.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Reſp.</hi> 1. <hi>ad</hi> 2 <hi>Interrog. Ferr.</hi>
                     </note> And Pope <hi>John</hi> the Second in <hi>Epiſt. ad Amaenum,</hi> alſo cites ſome paſſages of this Work, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing writ by <hi>Gelaſius;</hi> and though he doth not give him the Title of Pope, 'tis becauſe his name was well enough known at <hi>Rome</hi> when <hi>John</hi> the Second lived.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="century">
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:105312:26"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>That the Fathers of the</hi> SIXTH CENTURY <hi>did not believe</hi> Tranſubſtantiation. <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">AGE </seg>vi.</label>
                  </head>
                  <p>SAint <hi>Fulgentius</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">Fulgentius.</note> 
                     <hi>The Catholick church doth continually offer to God, the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>De fide ad Pet. Diac. c.</hi> 19.</note> a Sacrifice of Bread and VVine throughout all the VVorld. For in the fleſhly Sacrifices of the</hi> Old Teſtament, <hi>there is a type of the Fleſh of Jeſus Chriſt, which he was to offer without ſpot for our Sins; but in this Sacrifice, there is a Thankſgiving and Commemoration of the ſame Fleſh, which he offer'd for us. and of the Blood which he ſhed for us.</hi> He ſaith, That this Sacrifice conſiſts in offering <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>VVine;</hi> there muſt then be <hi>true Bread</hi> and <hi>VVine</hi> in this Sacrifice to be offer'd.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ephrem</hi> de <hi>Conte,</hi> of the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> made Biſhop of <hi>Antioch,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ephrem.</note> in the Year 526. wrote Books, which he intitled <hi>Sacred Laws,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Apud. Pho. Bibl. cod</hi> 229.</note> in the firſt of which diſputing againſt the <hi>Eutychians,</hi> he ſaith, When our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſaid, That Jeſus Chriſt is compos'd of two <hi>Natures,</hi> they meant two <hi>Subſtances,</hi> as by two <hi>Subſtances</hi> two <hi>Natures. No body of any ſenſe, but may ſay, that the Nature of that which is to be felt, and not felt in Jeſus Chriſt, is the ſame Nature. Thus it is, that the body of Jeſus Chriſt, which is received by believers, doth not quit its ſenſible Nature, and remains without being ſeparated from the intelligible Grace.</hi> The which he confirms by the Example of <hi>Water,</hi> which doth not loſe its Nature by <hi>Conſecration.</hi> This Argument is of the ſame kind of that we ſee of <hi>Theodoret,</hi> and of <hi>Gelaſius,</hi> whereby theſe three Authors prove, that in the <hi>Incarnation,</hi> the preſence of the <hi>VVord</hi> did not deſtroy the <hi>human Nature</hi> in Jeſus Chriſt, as the preſence of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> doth not deſtroy the <hi>Subſtance</hi> of <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> in the <hi>Euchariſt.</hi> We may ſay of this Triple and ſame Argument, <hi>Funiculus triplex difficile rumpitur.</hi> Monſ. de <hi>Marca,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſt. 4. v. 12.</note> ſaith in reference to this paſſage, and of thoſe we have inſtanced in of <hi>Theodoret,</hi> and St. <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> that theſe three Authors have owned a real change of the <hi>bread,</hi> which nevertheleſs leaves the <hi>Species</hi> in their <hi>natural Subſtance.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Facundus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Hermiana</hi> in <hi>Africa,</hi> in the year 552.
<note place="margin">Facundus.</note> whoſe Books,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lib.</hi> 9. <hi>De viris illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribus, c.</hi> 18.</note> which he wrote in Defence of the <hi>Three Chapters</hi> of the Council of <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> are juſtly praiſed by <hi>Victor</hi> of <hi>Tunes</hi> in his Chronology, and by St. <hi>Iſidore</hi> of <hi>Sevil,</hi> and which Father <hi>Sirmond</hi> the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:105312:27"/>Jeſuit got out of the <hi>Vatican</hi> Library; going about to excuſe <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore</hi> de <hi>Mopſueſt,</hi> who taught that Jeſus Chriſt had taken the Adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Children of God;
<note place="margin">Facundus.</note> from whence it might have been concluded,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lib.</hi> 9.</note> that he believed that Jeſus Chriſt is only an adoptive Son, ſaith, <hi>Baptiſm, which is the Sacrament of Adoption, may be called Adoption, as we call the Sacrament of his Body and Blood, which is in the conſecrated Bread and Wine, his Body and Blood; not that the Bread is properly his Body, and the Cup his Blood; but, becauſe they contain in them the Myſtery of his Body and Blood. Therefore, as the faithful Servants of Jeſus Chriſt, receiving the Sacrament of his Body and Blood, are very rightly ſaid to receive his Body and Blood; ſo alſo Jeſus Chriſt having received the Sacrament of the Adoption of Children, might very well be ſaid to have received the Adoption of Children.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Certainly, if the Sacrament of <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> is not <hi>properly</hi> the <hi>Body</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, as <hi>Facundus</hi> ſaith, but barely <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood,</hi> as <hi>Baptiſm</hi> is <hi>Adoption;</hi> the <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> are not <hi>Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiated</hi> into the Euchariſt, and are but ſimple ſigns, and ſomething that is diſtinguiſhed from the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Primaſius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Adrumetum</hi> in <hi>Africa,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Primaſius.</note> in his Commentary up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the 10th Chapter of the 1ſt to the <hi>Corinth.</hi> ſaith, <hi>As the Bread which we break, is the Participation of the body of Chriſt, ſo alſo the Bread of Idols, is the Participation of Devils.</hi> Now as the Participation of the Bread of Idols, is no <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> or real change into Devils; ſo alſo the Participation of the Bread of the Lord, is not a <hi>real</hi> and <hi>ſubſtantial change</hi> of <hi>Bread</hi> into the <hi>Body</hi> of the Lord.</p>
                  <p>The ſame <hi>Doctor,</hi> on the words of the 11th Chap. of the ſame Epiſtle, where 'tis ſaid, <hi>That the Lord took Bread the night in which he was betrayed,</hi> relates, <hi>That Jeſus Chriſt thereby gave to us the commemoration of his Body.</hi> And on the following words, <hi>The Lord,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>hath given us an Example, to the end that as often as we do this, we ſhould think in our minds, that Chriſt died for us. It is for this end, that 'tis ſaid to us,</hi> the Body of Chriſt, <hi>that ſo thinking of it, we ſhould not be ungrateful and unthankful for his Grace. As if any one at his Death, ſhould leave to his Friend a pledg of his Love, could he, when he ſaw it refrain from Tears, if he really loved his Friend?</hi> There muſt therefore needs be in the Sacrament <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> to be Pledges of Jeſus Chriſt, for he cannot be a pledg of himſelf.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="century">
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:105312:27"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>That the Fathers of the</hi> SEVENTH <hi>and</hi> EIGHTH CENTURY<hi>'s did not believe</hi> Tranſubſtantiation. <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">AGE </seg>vii.</label>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ISidore</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Sevil, Anno</hi> 600. ſaith,
<note place="margin">Iſidorus Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpalenſis.</note> That by the command of Jeſus Chriſt himſelf, we do call <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood,</hi> that which being the fruits of the Earth,
<note place="margin">Orig. l. 6. c. 19.</note> is ſanctified and made a Sacrament by the inviſible Operation of the Holy Ghoſt. In the 1ſt Book of Eccleſiaſtical Offices, he ſaith, '<hi>That the Bread is called the Body of Jeſus Chriſt, becauſe it ſtrengthens the Body, and that the Wine is called his Blood, becauſe it increaſeth Blood in the Body; and that the Bread and Wine are two viſible things, which being ſanctified by the Holy Ghoſt, do go on to be the Sacrament of the Divine body.</hi> Now a <hi>Sacrament</hi> ſignifies a <hi>holy Sign.</hi> It would therefore be a ſtrange kind of way of <hi>Iſidore,</hi> if he had believ'd the <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> were <hi>tranſubſtantiated,</hi> to ſay, the <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> are two things viſible, which being ſanctified by the Holy Ghoſt, do become the Sacraments of the Divine body. By this Language it might as well be ſaid, That the Fathers believed that the <hi>Water</hi> of Baptiſm was <hi>tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiated</hi> after their Conſecration.</p>
                  <p>The ſame Biſhop ſaith, <hi>Melchiſedeck,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">In Alleg. Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Teſt.</note> that offer'd of the Fruits of the Earth a Sacrifice to God, thereby repreſented the Prieſthood or Reign of Jeſus Chriſt, which is the true King of Peace, <hi>of whoſe Body and Blood, that is to ſay, the oblation of Bread and Wine, is offer'd throughout the World.</hi> And in the Treatiſe <hi>De Vocat. Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium,</hi> cap. 26. <hi>Theſe are not any longer Jewiſh Sacrifices, ſuch as were offer'd by</hi> Aaron <hi>the Prieſt, which are now offer'd by Believers, but they are ſuch Sacrifices as were preſented by</hi> Melchiſedeck <hi>King of</hi> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, <hi>that is to ſay, it is Bread and Wine, the true Sacrament of the Body and Blood of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> He ſaith, The <hi>Sacrament</hi> of the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt is <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine,</hi> That both the one and the other are ſuch Sacrifices as thoſe offer'd by <hi>Melchiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deck;</hi> there is therefore no queſtion, but St. <hi>Iſidore</hi> did not believe that the <hi>Bread</hi> was deſtroy'd in the Sacrament, becauſe he eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhes the Sacrament in the <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine,</hi> ſuch as <hi>Melchiſedeck</hi> had offer'd.</p>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:105312:28"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Beda,</hi> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">AGE </seg>viii.</label> an Engliſh, Prieſt ſaith, <hi>That Jeſus Chriſt having ended the Ceremony of the Ancient Paſſover, which was celebrated in commemora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Bondage in</hi> Egypt,
<note place="margin">Beda.</note> 
                     <hi>out of which the</hi> Jews <hi>had been deliver'd, proceeded to the new Paſſover, which the Church celebrates in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of His Redemption,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>In Lucae</hi> 22. <hi>&amp; in Marc.</hi> 14. <hi>&amp; in Hom quadrageſ. Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria</hi> 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. <hi>palma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</hi>
                        </note> the</hi> figure of <hi>his Body; to the end, that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of the Fleſh and Blood of the Lamb, ſubſtituting the Sacrament ſtead of the Fleſh and Blood of the Lamb, ſubſtituting the Sacrament of his Fleſh and Blood in the</hi> figure of <hi>Bread and Wine, he might ſhew that it was him to whom God had ſworn, and repented not, ſaying, Thou art a Prieſt for ever after the Order of Melchiſedeck.</hi> Now, continues <hi>Beda, Jeſus Chriſt broke the Bread which he diſtributed to his Diſciples, to ſhew, That the breaking of his Body did not come to paſs without his good will.</hi> It appears from theſe words, <hi>(ſubſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Sacrament of his Fleſh and Blood in the figure of Bread and Wine)</hi> that the <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> remain after Conſecration, to be the figure of the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of Chriſt.
<note place="margin">Rom. 4.11.</note> As when the Apoſtle ſaith, the ſign of Circumciſion, <hi>ſignum circumciſionis;</hi> That is to ſay, Circumciſion which is a ſign and a figure. So <hi>Beda</hi> maketh the Sacrament conſiſt in the <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine.</hi> Therefore in the Homily, <hi>De Sanctis in Epiphania,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>That Jeſus Chriſt the Heavenly Lamb, having been offer'd up, and transfer'd into the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of Bread and VVine, the Myſtery of his Paſſion, and thereby be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a Prieſt for ever after the Order of</hi> Melchiſedeck. And elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where he ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Hom. aeſt. &amp;c.</hi> 55 <hi>in Virg. St. Joan. Bapt.</hi>
                     </note> Melchiſedeck <hi>Prieſt of the moſt high God, did long before the time of the legal Prieſthood, offer up Bread and VVine.</hi> Therefore our Saviour is called Prieſt after the Order of <hi>Melchiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deck,</hi> becauſe <hi>he abrogated the Sacrifices of the Law, and inſtituted a Sacrifice of the ſame kind to be under the New Teſtament, the Myſtery of his Body and Blood.</hi> Certainly, As our Myſtery is no Myſtery till after Conſecration; and that 'tis of the ſame Nature as was that of <hi>Melchiſedeck,</hi> it muſt be concluded, that the <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>VVine</hi> do remain in the Sacrament of the Euchariſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sedulius,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Sedulius.</note> a <hi>Scotchman,</hi> Author of the Commentaries upon St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and who flouriſhed about the year 735, in his Commentary up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the firſt to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> Chap. 11. ſaith, <hi>Jeſus Chriſt in the Euchariſt, hath left us the remembrance of himſelf, as if one going a far journey ſhould leave with his friend the pledg of his love, to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber their ancient amity.</hi> There muſt then needs be ſomething that is not Jeſus Chriſt himſelf, for no one is a pledg of himſelf.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Damaſcen</hi> a Frier,
<note place="margin">Jo. Damaſcen.</note> who lived about the year 750, ſaith in his fourth Book of Orthodox Law, <hi>Chap.</hi> 14. <hi>The Shew-bread did typifie
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:105312:28"/>this Bread, and 'tis this pure and unbloody Sacrifice which our Saviour foretold by the Prophet, ſhould be offered to him from the riſing of the Sun to the ſetting of the ſame, to wit,
<note place="margin">Damaſcen.</note> the Body and Blood of Jeſus Chriſt, which paſſeth into the ſubſtance of our Body and Soul, without being conſumed, without being corrupted, without going into the draft, God forbid, but paſſing into our ſubſtance for our preſervation.</hi> Now every body agrees this cannot be ſaid of the proper Body of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt. It muſt then be concluded, <hi>Damaſcen</hi> ſuppoſed that the <hi>Bread remained.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the ſame place he adds, <hi>That as in Baptiſm, becauſe men are wont to waſh with water, and anoint them with oyl, God has added to the water and oyl, the Grace of his Hely Spirit, and has made it the waſhing of Regeneration; ſo alſo, they being accuſtom'd to eat bread, and to drink wine and water, he has joined them to his Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and has made them his Body and Blood.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the ſame place, <hi>The Prophet Eſay ſaw a light coal; now the Coal is not of meer wood, but it is joined to fire; ſo alſo the Bread of the Euchariſt is not common bread, but it is united to the Divinity, and the Body which is united to the Divinity, is not one and the ſame Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but the Nature of the Body is one, and that of the Divinity, which is united to it, is another.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the ſame place, <hi>How is it that the Bread is made the Body of Jeſus Chriſt, and the Wine and Water his Blood? he anſwers, The Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt comes and diſpoſes theſe things after ſuch a manner as ſurpaſſeth our thoughts and expreſſions.</hi> The <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> are taken, <hi>Panis &amp; Vinum aſſumuntur,</hi> in Greek <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, a word uſed by St. <hi>Athanaſius</hi> to expreſs the <hi>Hypoſtatical Union.</hi> Now theſe kinds of expreſſions of <hi>Damaſcen</hi> do imply, that the <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> do remain in the Sacrament.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> compoſed of 338 Biſhops,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Concil. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant.</hi> Act. 6.</note> held in the viiith <hi>Century,</hi> for regulating the buſineſs of <hi>Image-Worſhip,</hi> having condemn'd their uſe, they would by the way explain the Doctrine of the Church touching the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> and to draw a proof againſt thoſe very Images, they call it the true Image of Jeſus Chriſt; they ſay he gave it to his Diſciples to be a Type of the evident Commemoration of his Death; they ſay that Jeſus Chriſt choſe no other Species under Heaven, nor no other Type that ſhould expreſs his Incarnation. Behold then, ſay they, <hi>the Image of his quickned Body, which was made after a precious and honourable manner.</hi> They affirm, that as the Word did not take a Perſon,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:105312:29"/>that ſo the addition of a Perſon might not be made to the Divinity; ſo alſo he appointed, that an Image ſhould be offered, which is a choſen matter,
<note place="margin">Conc. Conſt.</note> to wit, the <hi>Subſtance</hi> of <hi>Bread,</hi> that has not the figure of Man, to avoid giving occaſion of Idolatry; As then, ſay they, the Body of Jeſus Chriſt which is according to Nature, is Holy, as having been Deified; ſo alſo 'tis apparent, that that body alſo that is by Inſtitution, is Holy, and it's Image is Holy, as having been Deified by Grace, by a kind of Sanctification. They maintain, that as the Human Nature was Deified by its Union with the Word, ſo alſo the <hi>Bread</hi> of the Sacrament, as the true Image of the Natural Fleſh of Jeſus Chriſt, is ſanctified by the coming of the Holy Ghoſt, and becomes the Body of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>becauſe the Prieſt transfers the Oblation from the ſtate of a common thing, to ſomething that is holy.</hi> To conclude, they clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſtinguiſh the natural Fleſh of Jeſus Chriſt, which is living and intelligent, from his Image, which is the Heavenly Bread, filled with the Holy Spirit. All theſe continued Expreſſions are ſo far from any Idea of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> that one muſt needs ſee, that the <hi>deſtruction of the Bread and Wine</hi> in the Sacrament, was not beleieved by the Fathers of the Council, nor by the Church in their time.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Alcuin</hi> ſpeaking of the Conſecrating of Bread and Wine to be the Body and Blood of Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Alcuinus.</note> ſaith, that the Sanctification of this Myſtery doth foreſhew to us the effect of our Salvation:
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ep.</hi> 69.</note> 
                     <hi>That by the Water is ſignified the Chriſtian People; by the grains of the Wheat ground into Meal to make Bread, is meant the Union of the Univerſal Church, which is made one Body by the fire of the Holy Ghoſt, which unites the Members to the Head; and that by the Wine is ſhewed the Blood of the Paſſion of the Lord.</hi> Doubtleſs <hi>Alcuin</hi> did not believe <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> ſeeing he places in the <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine,</hi> the ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification of the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt; and that he ſaith by the <hi>Wine</hi> is ſhewed the <hi>Blood</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt; for that which is a Figure, and that which is figured; that which ſheweth, and that which is ſhewed, are two different things, the one of which is not the other. Therefore the ſame <hi>Alcuin</hi> doth formally diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh the Euchariſt from the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, when he ſaith after St. <hi>Auſtin, Whoſoever abideth not in Jeſus Christ, and he in whom Chriſt abideth not,
<note place="margin">In Joan. <hi>c.</hi> 13. <hi>v.</hi> 15.</note> doubtleſs doth not ſpiritually eat his fleſh, altho he viſibly and carnally eats with his teeth the Sacrament of the Body and Blood of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:105312:29"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Charles the great,</hi> his Diſciple, writing to the ſame <hi>Alcuin,</hi> calls the Euchariſt, <hi>the Figure of the Body and Blood of the Lord.</hi> The Lord, ſaith he, being at Supper with his Diſciples, broke <hi>Bread,</hi> and gave likewiſe the <hi>Cup, in figure of his Body and Blood;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Carol. M. De Offic. Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuag. ad Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin.</note> and by this means offered us a very profitable Sacrament: Now what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he ſaid of the <hi>figure</hi> it contain'd, or that it contain'd not the truth, the figure was never the ſame as the thing is that's fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gured.</p>
                  <p>In the <hi>Ambroſian</hi> Office which was aboliſh'd in the year 796,
<note place="margin">Ambroſian Office.</note> there was this Clauſe, which is ſtill to be ſeen in the 4th Book of St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> his Sacraments, <hi>Nobis hanc oblationem adſcriptam ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabilem, acceptabilem, quod eſt figura Corporis &amp; Sanguinis Dom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ni noſtri Jeſu Chriſti.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Ancient <hi>Roman</hi> Order doth frequently call the <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>VVine,</hi> the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of the Lord;
<note place="margin">Ordo Romen.</note> but it ſufficiently ſhews by theſe manner of expreſſions, that it doth not mean that the <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>VVine</hi> are the ſame thing with the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt; for in the firſt place it ſaith, that the Sub-Deacons when they ſee the Chalice wherein is the <hi>Blood</hi> of the Lord cover'd with a Cloth, and when the Prieſt hath ſaid theſe words at the end of the Lords Prayer, <hi>libera nos a malo,</hi> they ſhould go from the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, and prepare Chalices and clean Cloths to receive the <hi>Body</hi> of the Lord, <hi>fearing leſt it ſhould fall to the ground, and crumble to duſt.</hi> Now who doth not ſee that this cannot be ſpoken but of the Bread, figuratively and improperly called the <hi>Body</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt? 2ly, It ſaith, That the Biſhop breaketh the Oblation on the right ſide, and that he leaveth the part which he brake, on the Altar: Now who can ſay that the Body of Jeſus Chriſt can be broke into parts? 3dly, The Fraction being made, the <hi>Deacon</hi> receives from the <hi>Sub-Deacon</hi> the Cup, and carries it to the Chair, that the Biſhop might communicate, who having communicated, puts part of the holy Oblation of which he bit a Morſel, into the <hi>Arch-Deacons</hi> hands. Can it be ſaid that one doth bite the <hi>true Bedy</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, and that one breaks off part of it? 4thly, It adds, <hi>he is to take great heed that no part of the Body and Blood of the Lord doth remain in the Chalice, or on the Plate.</hi> By theſe words, the <hi>Roman</hi> Order gives us to underſtand, that it ſpeaks of ſuch a <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> that a part of it may be ſeparated from the whole: Now this is what can only be ſaid of the <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine,</hi> improperly called the Body and Blood of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:105312:30"/>
                  <p>The now <hi>Roman</hi> Order at preſent uſed in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> doth alſo furniſh us with the like reflections. It expreſly marketh, That Jeſus Chriſt gave in the Oblation,
<note place="margin">Ordo Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus.</note> 
                     <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>VVine,</hi> to cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate the Myſteries of his <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood.</hi> Therein is deſired, That this Bleſſed Oblation may be accepted of God in ſuch a manner, as that it might be made <hi>to us</hi> the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt; after all which, is recited the Hiſtory of the Inſtitution, and the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramental words. The Euchariſt is called, <hi>the Sacred Bread of Eternal Life; ond the Cup, the Cup of everlastiug Salvation.</hi> To conclude, They pray God to behold thoſe Gifts, and that he will accept them as he did the offering of <hi>Abel,</hi> and the Sacrifice of <hi>Melchiſedeck,</hi> which it's very well known, was <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine.</hi> All which doth plainly ſhew, That the <hi>Roman</hi> Order at this time obſerved, cannot reaſonably be interpreted, but in ſuppoſing that the <hi>Bread and Wine remain in the Eucharist after Conſecration.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="century">
                  <head>
                     <hi>That the Fathers of the</hi> NINTH CENTURY <hi>did not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve</hi> Tranſubſtantiation.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THeodorus Studita,</hi> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">AGE </seg>ix.</label> as is related by <hi>Michael Studita</hi> in <hi>Baronius,</hi> in the year 816. N. 15. ſeeing himſelf reduced to the extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of being ſtarv'd, ſaid to his Diſciple, <hi>If men are ſo crvel as to make me perriſh with hunger,
<note place="margin">Thecdorus Studita.</note> the participation of the Body and Blood of the Lord, which is the ordinary food of my Body and Soul, ſhall be my only nouriſhment:</hi> Now the <hi>real Body</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt cannot be the nouriſhment of the <hi>Body;</hi> therefore of neceſſity this Author muſt be underſtood to ſpeak of <hi>Bread,</hi> which is his <hi>Body figura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively</hi> and <hi>improperly.</hi> It is what is alſo confirm'd by this <hi>Michael Studita,</hi> who ſaith in the ſame place, that <hi>Theodore</hi> had always about him, <hi>ſome parcels of the quickning Body of the Lord;</hi> which cannot be meant of the <hi>true Body</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, which is not now ſubject to be broken, nor divided.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ahyto</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Baſil,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ahyto.</note> ſent Ambaſſador by <hi>Charlemaine</hi> in the year 814, to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> to Treat a Peace with the Emperor of the Eaſt, as is declared by the Annals of <hi>France,</hi> by <hi>Eginhart</hi> Author of the Life of <hi>Charlemaine,</hi> the Annals of <hi>Fulda, Herman Contract,</hi> and others. This <hi>Ahyto</hi> died in the year 836, and left a Capitulary for inſtruction of the Prieſts of his Dioceſs, publiſht by
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:105312:30"/>
                     <hi>Dom Luke D'achery</hi> in the Sixth Tome of his <hi>Spicilegium,</hi> pag. 692. <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">AGE </seg>viii.</label> now amongſt many other Inſtructions he gives his Prieſts in his Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitularies, this is one:
<q>In the fifth place, the Prieſt ſhould know what the Sacrament of <hi>Baptiſm</hi> and <hi>Confirmation</hi> is,
<note place="margin">Ahyto.</note> and alſo what the Myſtery of the <hi>body</hi> and <hi>blood</hi> of our Lord doth mean. How a viſible creature is ſeen in the ſame Myſteries, and is nevertheleſs the inviſible. Salvation is communicated for the Souls eternal hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs,</q> which is contained in faith only. By <hi>viſible creature,</hi> he can only mean a creature, not in appearance, but effective, for otherwiſe, according to this Author, it muſt be ſaid that in <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm,</hi> and <hi>Confirmation,</hi> there ſhould be only an apparent crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and not the ſubſtance of <hi>water</hi> and <hi>chriſm.</hi> Beſides, <hi>Ahyto</hi> attributed the ſame effect to theſe three Sacraments, to wit, the communication of eternal and inviſible ſalvation to them that with <hi>faith</hi> do receive theſe holy Sacraments.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Theodulphus</hi> in the year 810. Biſhop of <hi>Orleans,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Theodulphus.</note> ſaith in his Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of the Order of Baptiſm,
<q>
                        <hi>There is one ſaving ſacrifice which</hi> Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedeck <hi>alſo offer'd under the Old Teſtament, in Type of the body and blood of our Saviour, the which the Mediator of God and Man accem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed under the New, before he was crucify'd, when taking the bread and wine he bleſſed and gave them to his Diſciples, commanding them to do thoſe things in remembrance of him. It is this Myſtery which the Church doth celebrate, having put an end to the ancient ſacrifices, offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bread, becauſe of the bread which came down from Heaven; and wine, becauſe of him which ſaid, I am the true Vine; to the end that by the viſible Oblation of Prieſts, and by the inviſible conſecration of the Holy Ghoſt, the bread and wine ſhould have the dignity of the body and blood of our Lord, with which blood there is mingled ſome water, either becauſe there came out of the ſide of our Saviour water with the blood; Or becauſe according to the Interpretation of our Anceſtors, as Jeſus Chriſt is ſignify'd by the wine, ſo alſo the people is ſignify'd by the water.</hi>
                     </q> Now this Biſhop, ſaying that Jeſus Chriſt gave <hi>bread</hi> to his Diſciples in commemoration that this Myſtery is an Oblation of <hi>viſible bread</hi> which is conſecrated by the Holy Spirit, and which receiveth the dignity of the <hi>body;</hi> that he indifferently calls the <hi>blood, wine,</hi> and the <hi>wine, blood;</hi> that with the blood, water is mingled, and that Jeſus Chriſt is <hi>ſignify'd</hi> by the <hi>wine;</hi> that 'tis ſaid the <hi>wine ſignifies</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, as the water doth the people; theſe words cannot ſuppoſe any <hi>Tranſubſtantiation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:105312:31"/>
                  <p>The Oppoſers of <hi>Paſchaſius Radbertus</hi> Frier of the Monaſtry of <hi>Corby,</hi> who wrote a Book of the <hi>body</hi> and <hi>blood</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, did not believe <hi>Tranſubſtantiation.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Oppoſers of <hi>Paſchaſius Radbertus.</hi>
                     </note> That the ſaid <hi>Paſchaſius</hi> had ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral adverſaries, appears by his own Writings, for towards the end of his Commentary upon St. <hi>Matthew,</hi> he ſaith himſelf, <hi>I have inlarged upon the Lords Supper a little more than the brevity of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary would permit, becauſe there be ſeveral others that are of a differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent judgment touching theſe holy Myſteries, and that ſeveral are blind, and do not perceive that this bread and cup is nothing elſe but what is ſeen with the eyes, and taſted with the palate.</hi> And in his Epiſtle to <hi>Frudegard,</hi> as well as in his Commentary on St. <hi>Matthew,</hi> ch. 12. it appears he had Oppoſers, becauſe in his Epiſt. to <hi>Frudegard,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>You adviſe with me touching a thing that many do make doubt of.</hi> And in his Commentary, <hi>I am told that many,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>do cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure me, as if I had attributed to the words of our Lord, either more, or ſomething quite contrary to what the genuine ſenſe permits.</hi> So that <hi>Paſchaſius</hi> had adverſaries, and they did not believe <hi>Tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> becauſe they held that in the Euchariſt, <hi>there was only the virtue of the fleſh, and not the very fleſh; the virtue of the blood, and not the very blood of Chriſt. That the Euchariſt was figure, and not verity; ſhadow of the body, and not the body it ſelf. They would,</hi> ſaith Paſchaſius, <hi>extenuate the word,</hi> body <hi>and perſwade, Quod non ſit ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra caro Chriſti, ſed quaedam virtus &amp; figura corporis Chriſti.</hi> Now <hi>Paſchaſius Rathbertus</hi> was the firſt Author that wrote fully and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly of the <hi>truth</hi> of the <hi>body</hi> and <hi>blood</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt in the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt, as <hi>Bellarmin</hi> ſaith, <hi>de Scriptoribus Eccleſiaſticis in Paſchaſio Ratherto.</hi> And Father <hi>Sirmond</hi> ſaith, he is the firſt that hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd the ſenſe of the Church touching this <hi>Myſtery;</hi> ſo that, ſaith he, he hath opened the way to others, <hi>In vitae Ratherti prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixa ejus operibus.</hi> Therefore it is nothing ſtrange that <hi>Paſchaſius</hi> had enemies, and that he was accuſed for departing from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Faith, and to have ſpread abroad Viſions of a young Man. For he ſaith to <hi>Frudegard, You have,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>at the end of this Work, the Authorities of Catholick Fathers ſuccinctly marked, by which you may perceive, that 'twas not through raſhneſs, that formerly when I was young, I believed theſe things, but by Divine authority.</hi> He alſo endeavours to clear himſelf from this charge in alledging paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages, as of Saint <hi>Austins,</hi> the which nevertheleſs are not to be found in him; as theſe words, <hi>Receive in the Bread what hung on the Croſs, receive in the Cup what iſſued out of the ſide of Jeſus Christ.</hi> Which is not to be found in <hi>St. Austin.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:105312:31"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Rabanus</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Mayance</hi> in the year 847, <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">AGE </seg>ix.</label> ſtiled by <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronius</hi> in the year 843, <hi>No.</hi> 31. the bright Star of <hi>Germany, Fulgens Germaniae Sidus;</hi> ſaith in his Inſtitution of Clerks, <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 31.
<note place="margin">Rabanus.</note> 
                     <hi>Our Saviour liked better that believers ſhould receive with their mouth the Sacraments of his Body and Blood, and that they ſhould be turned into their nouriſhment, to the end that by the viſible work the inviſible effect ſhould be ſhewn. For as the material food, doth materially nouriſh the Body, and ſupport it, ſo alſo the VVord of God doth nouriſh the Soul inwardly, and doth strengthen it.</hi> And in the ſame place, <hi>The Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is one thing, and the virtue of the Sacrament is another. The Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament is turned into the nouriſhment of the Body, but by the virtue of the Sacrament one acquires everlaſting life. As the Sacrament there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is turn'd into our ſelves, when we do cat and drink it, ſo alſo we are converted into the Body of Jeſus Christ, when we live with piety and obedience.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſame Doctor on St. <hi>Matthew,</hi> Chap. 26. ſaith with Venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Beda,</hi> that Jeſus Chriſt hath ſubſtituted inſtead of the fleſh and blood of the Paſcal Lamb, the <hi>Sacrament of his Body and Blood.</hi> That the Creator of the World, and the Redeemer of Mankind, <hi>making of the very fruits of the Earth, that is to ſay, of Bread and VVine, a fit Mystery, turn'd it into the Sacrament of his Body and Blood, that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leavensd Bread and VVine mixt with water, must be ſanctified to be the Sacrament of the Body and Blood of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Afterwards he gives the reaſon wherefore our Saviour choſe <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> to make them Sacraments of his <hi>Fleſh</hi> and <hi>Blood,</hi> and ſaith, that 'tis becauſe <hi>Melchiſedeck</hi> offer'd <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>VVine,</hi> and that Jeſus Chriſt being a Prieſt after the Order of <hi>Melchiſedeck,</hi> he was to imitate his Oblation. And ſhewing the reaſon why the Sacrament takes the name of the <hi>body</hi> and <hi>blood</hi> of the Lord, he ſaith with <hi>Iſidore</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Sevil, 'Tis becauſe bread ſtrengthens the body, it is conveniently called the body of Jeſus Chriſt: and becauſe wine augments blood in the fleſh and veins for this reaſon, it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd to the blood. Now both theſe things are viſible, nevertheleſs being ſanctify'd by the Holy Ghoſt, they paſs into the Sacrament of the Divine body.</hi> A Sacrament which in the 33 <hi>chap.</hi> he calls the <hi>Mystical body</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, in oppoſition to his <hi>Natural body,</hi> from which he diſtinguiſhes it, and draws a reſemblance from the Myſtical body, to the proper body of Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>The holy Veſſels,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>are ſet on the Altar,</hi> viz. <hi>the Cup and Patten, which in ſome ſort are the figure of the Grave of Jeſus Chriſt, for as at that time the Body of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:105312:32"/>Jeſus Chriſt was laid in the Sepulcher, having been embalm'd by god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly people; ſo alſo at preſent, the Myſtical Body of Jeſus Chriſt, as it were imbalm'd with holy Prayers,
<note place="margin">Rabanus.</note> is kept in the holy Veſſels to be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred to Believers by the hands of the Miniſters.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſame Doctor in his Penitential, or Letter to <hi>Herribald</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Auxerre,</hi> which <hi>Monſieur Baluze</hi> got Printed at the end of his <hi>Regino</hi> at <hi>Paris</hi> in 1671, ſaith, <hi>Chap.</hi> 33. <hi>As to what you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of me, whether the Sacrament after it is eat and conſum'd, and caſt into the draft after the manner of all other meats, does return to the former nature it had before 'twas conſecrated at the Altar; to ſuch a needleſs queſtion may be reply'd, The Lord himſelf ſaid in the Goſpel, that what enters into the body goes into the helly, and is caſt into the draft. As for the Sacrament of the Body and blood, it is made of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poreal and viſible things, but it produceth an inviſible ſanctification, as well to the body as to the ſoul. What reaſon is there, that that which is digeſted in the ſtomack, and is caſt out into the draft, ſhould return to its former ſtate, there being never any that affirmed that ſuch a thing was done? For of late ſome perſons not having a right judgment of the Sacrament of the Body and Blood of Chriſt, have ſaid, that the ſame Body, and the ſame Blood of the Lord which was born of the Virgin</hi> Mary, <hi>and in which the Lord ſuffered on the Croſs, and roſe again from the Dead, is the ſame which is taken at the Altar; againſt which Error we have as much as was neceſſary written to the Abbot</hi> Egilon, <hi>Explaining what ought truly to be believed of the Body of Chriſt in the Euchariſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Amalarius,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Amalarius.</note> eſteemed a very Learned man, in the Manuſcripts cited by <hi>Dom Luke D'achery</hi> a Learned <hi>Benedictin,</hi> in his Preface to the Seventh Tome of his <hi>Spicilegium,</hi> was ſent by the Emperor <hi>Charles le Debonnair</hi> to Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> to find out Antiphonaries, <hi>(Amalar. in Prolog. Antiphon.)</hi> and who by expreſs command of the ſame Emperor, was choſen in a Council held at <hi>Aix la Chappel, Anno</hi> 816, to make Rules for Prebends, as is teſtified by <hi>Ademar</hi> a Monk of <hi>Angouliſm,</hi> in his Chronicle on the year 816, ſaith in his Treatiſe of <hi>Church-Offices, Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 25. That the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is to us inſtead of Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>The Frieſt,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>bows and recommends to God the Father, that which was offered in the room of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> In the 26th chap. he ſaith, <hi>The Oblation and the Cup, do ſignifie the Body of the Lord, when Jeſus Chriſt ſaid, This is the Cup of my Blood, he ſanctified his Blood, which Blood was in the Body, as the Wine is in the Chalice.</hi> In the third Book, chap. 25. he calls
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:105312:32"/>the Euchariſt, <hi>the Sacrament of Bread and Wine:</hi> and ſaith, that <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt hath in this bread recommended his Body; and in the Cup, his Blood.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſame <hi>Amalarius</hi> having been conſulted by <hi>Rangart</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Noyon,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Amal. ad Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gart, Tom.</hi> 7. <hi>Spicilegii, pag.</hi> 166.</note> how he underſtood thoſe words of Inſtitution of the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt, <hi>This is the Cup in my Blood of the New and Eternal Teſtament,</hi> with this addition which is in the Cannon of the Maſs, <hi>the Myſtery of Faith;</hi> anſwers him by a Letter, wherein after having ſpoken of the <hi>Cup</hi> of the <hi>Paſſover,</hi> he proceeds to that of the Euchariſt; and having alledged what is mention'd by St. <hi>Luke,</hi> he adds,
<q>
                        <hi>The Cup is in type of my Body, wherein is the Blood that ſhall run out of my ſide, to accompliſh the ancient Law; and after it is ſhed, it ſhall be the New Teſtament.</hi>
                     </q> And a little lower he ſaith,
<q>
                        <hi>The Myſtery is Faith, as St.</hi> Auſtin <hi>ſaith in his Letter to the Biſhop</hi> Boniface, <hi>as the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the Body of Jeſus Chriſt is in ſome manner the Body of Jeſus Chriſt, and the Sacrament of his Blood, his Blood; ſo the Sacrament of Faith, is Faith. So alſo we may ſay, This is the Cup of my Blood of the New and Eternal Teſtament. As if he ſhould ſay, This is my Blood which is given for you.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſame Doctor, in a Letter which he wrote to one <hi>Gontard,</hi> whom he calls his Son, ſaith,
<q>
                        <hi>That it is our Saviours good pleaſure to ſhed his Blood by the Members and Veins, for our Eternal Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. That 'tis a body of Jeſus Chriſt that may be caſt out in ſpitting after having receiv'd it, and of which, a part may be flung out of the mouth.</hi> To all which he adds, <hi>having ſo received the body of the Lord with a good intention; I don't pretend to diſpute, whether he be inviſibly lifted up to Heaven, or whether he remains in our Body, till the day of our Death, or whether he evaporates into Air, or whether he iſſues out of the Body with the Blood, or whether he goes out at the pores; our Saviour ſaying, All that enters in at the Mouth, goes down into the Belly, and from thence into the draft,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now when this great Man ſaith, That the Sacrament is to us in the ſtead of Jeſus Chriſt; that what is offered in the Euchariſt is ſacrific'd inſtead of Jeſus Chriſt; that the <hi>Cup</hi> is in <hi>Type</hi> of the <hi>Body;</hi> that the <hi>Blood</hi> is in the <hi>Body,</hi> as the <hi>Wine</hi> is in the <hi>Cup;</hi> that Jeſus Chriſt repreſents his <hi>Body</hi> by the <hi>Bread,</hi> and his <hi>Blood</hi> in the <hi>Wine;</hi> that the Sacrament of the <hi>Body</hi> is in ſome ſort his <hi>Body,</hi> and that 'tis ſo that the <hi>Cup</hi> of the <hi>Blood</hi> is his <hi>Blood,</hi> that the <hi>Body</hi> is poured forth upon our Members for our Salvation; that there is a <hi>Body</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt that may be caſt out by ſpitting, and whereof
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:105312:33"/>ſome part may be flung out of the Mouth; That he will not diſpute, whether this <hi>Body</hi> evaporates in the Air, or whether it departs out of the <hi>body</hi> with the <hi>blood,</hi> or whether it goes out at the pores, or into the Draft; all this doth ſufficiently ſhew, That this Doctor diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the <hi>Bread and Wine,</hi> as a <hi>Typical body,</hi> from the <hi>real Body</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt; and that by conſequence, he believed the <hi>bread</hi> and <hi>wine</hi> remained after Conſecration, to be called the <hi>body and blood</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, but improperly.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Valafridus Strabo,
<note place="margin">Valafridus Strabo.</note> Abbas Augienſis,</hi> ſtiled a very Learned Man, by <hi>Herman Contracted,</hi> in the year 849.
<q>
                        <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>gave to his Diſciples the Sacrament of his Body and Blood in the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of bread and wine,
<note place="margin">Lib. de Reb. Eccleſ. c. 16. Bill. p. 7. to. 10.</note> teaching them to celebrate it in remembrance of his moſt holy Paſſion, becauſe there could nothing be found fitter than theſe things to ſignify the unity of the Head and Members; for as Bread is made of ſundry Grains, and brought into one body by means of Water; and as the Wine is ſqueez'd from ſeveral Grapes, ſo alſo the body of Jeſus Chriſt is made of the anion of a multitude of Saints.</hi> And a little after, he declares, That <hi>Jeſus Chriſt hath choſe for us a very fit Sacrifice, for the Myſtery of his body and blood, in that</hi> Melchiſedeck <hi>having offer'd bread and wine, he gave to his Children the ſame kinds of Sacraments.</hi>
                     </q> And afterwards, <hi>cap.</hi> 18. That for that great Number of Legal Ordinances, Jeſus Chriſt gave us the word of his Goſpel; ſo alſo inſtead of the great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of Sacrifices, Believers are to reſt ſatisfied, <hi>with the ſole Oblation of bread and wine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is evident <hi>Strabo</hi> makes the Holy Sacrament to conſiſt in the <hi>ſubſtance of bread and wine,</hi> which according to him, is differenced from the <hi>body,</hi> becauſe it is but the <hi>memorial</hi> of it; That 'tis the figure, that it conſiſts in being made of ſundry Grains, and the Wine of ſundry Grapes. That the Sacrifice of the <hi>New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> is of the ſame kind as that of <hi>Melchiſedeck,</hi> and that the Euchariſt is an Oblation of <hi>bread</hi> and <hi>wine.</hi> All theſe things inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate, that the <hi>bread</hi> and <hi>wine</hi> remain in the Euchariſt after Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Herribald</hi> was Biſhop of <hi>Auxerre,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Herribald.</note> in the time that <hi>Vallafridus Strabo</hi> wrote.
<note place="margin">Tom. 2. ch. 19.52, and 61.</note> Now he was of the ſame Opinion with <hi>Rabanus. Thomas Waldenſis</hi> aſſures us ſo. <hi>Herribald</hi> of <hi>Auxerre,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>and</hi> Rabanus <hi>of</hi> Mayence <hi>ſay, That the Sacrament of the Euchariſt goes into the Draft.</hi> The Anonimous Author, contemporary with <hi>Herribald,</hi> which was publiſhed by Father <hi>Cellot</hi> the Jeſuit, ſaith
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:105312:33"/>alſo the ſame. Nevertheleſs <hi>Lupus</hi> Abbot of <hi>Ferriers,</hi> Ep. 19. ſpeaking of him, calls him a <hi>moſt excellent Prelate, excellentiſſimum Praeſulem.</hi> In the 37th Ep. he ſtiles him a Man of a lofty and Divine underſtanding, <hi>Altiſſimi &amp; Divini ingenii.</hi> And <hi>Hinemarus</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Reims,</hi> calls him the Biſhop of Venerable Qualities.
<note place="margin">De Praed. ch. 6.</note> So that the very Chronicle of <hi>Auxerre</hi> intimates, that there was ingrav'd on his Monument this Inſcription, <hi>Here lies the body of St.</hi> Herribald. Therefore the Author of the 1ſt Treatiſe of the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuity of the Euchariſt,</hi> ſaith in page 843, That <hi>Herribald</hi> and <hi>Rha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banus,</hi> were Adverſaries to <hi>Paſcaſius:</hi> Tho in the 2d Treatiſe of the <hi>Perpetuity,</hi> in page 842. he ſaith, ſpeaking of the Miniſter <hi>Claude,</hi> who told him, that <hi>Amalarius</hi> and <hi>Herribald</hi> were in any wiſe Adverſaries to <hi>Paſchas?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It appears by the Letter <hi>Paſchaſius</hi> wrote to <hi>Frudegard,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Frndegardus.</note> that he was not of the ſame Judgment <hi>Paſchaſius</hi> was of, ſeeing he oppoſes to him St. <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s 23d Letter to <hi>Boniface, Sic VVidefort contra VVick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liff,</hi> ad art. 1.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Trithem.</hi> de Script. Eccleſ.</note> 
                     <hi>Ratramne,</hi> Prieſt and Frier of <hi>Corby,</hi> experienc'd in the Scriptures,
<note place="margin">Ratramnus.</note> equally eſteem'd for his Learning and Manners, whom
<note n="†" place="margin">De Praedeſt.</note> 
                     <hi>Hinemar,
<note n="‖" place="margin">Ep. 79.</note> Lupus</hi> Abbot of <hi>Ferriers,</hi> his Contemporaries;
<note n="⁂" place="margin">De Script. Eccleſ.</note> 
                     <hi>Sigebert</hi> who liv'd in the xi. Century, and Father
<note n="‡" place="margin">De Euchr. ch. 1.</note> 
                     <hi>Cellot</hi> the Jeſuits Anonimus, do all make mention of, under his true name of <hi>Ratramne;</hi> wrote a Book under the Reign of <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Bald,</hi> as is reported by the ſame <hi>Trythemius,</hi> which he intitul'd, <hi>Of the Body and Blood of the Lord:</hi> From a Monk of <hi>Corby,</hi> he was made Abbot of <hi>Ovais.</hi> The Preſident
<note n="⁂" place="margin">
                        <hi>Maug.</hi> diſſert. Hiſt. &amp; Chron. c. 17. tom. 2. pag. 133 &amp; 135.</note> 
                     <hi>Mauguin</hi> ſpeaking of him, ſaith, he was a Learned Doctor of the Church, eminent in Probity, and in Doctrine, an undaunted defender and protector of the Catholick Truth, againſt Innovators. He dedicated his Book to the Emperor <hi>Charles</hi> the Bald. Now this Author did not believe <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> becauſe he ſaith,
<q>
                        <hi>For as to the ſubſtance of thoſe Creatures, they are after Conſecration what they were before; they were before bread and wine, and it is plainly ſeen, that after Conſecration theſe created ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances do remain in the very ſame ſpecies.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>And a little after he ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ratramnus</hi> in the Apology of the Fathers, is ſtiled a learn'd <hi>Benedictin</hi> Defender of Grace, a Man of great Wiſdom and Reputation; and in the 1ſt treatiſe of the <hi>Perpetuity,</hi> p. 3. c. 5. he is ſtiled an obſcure kind of a perſon, that evaporated himſelf in obſcure Reaſonings, which he added to thoſe of the Church, and explained as he pleaſed himſelf, as ſome are pleaſed to ſay.</note>
                     <q>
                        <hi>This ſpiritual fleſh which ſpiritually feeds Believers, is made of grains of Wheat, by the hands of the Baker,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:105312:34"/>ſuch as it appears to our ſight; but it hath neither bones nor ſinews, nor no diſtinction of parts, nor is it enliven'd with a Soul, or reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſubſtance. To conclude, it is unable to move of it ſelf, and if it gives life, it is the effect of a ſpiritual virtue, of an inviſible, and a Divine Virtue and Efficacy.</hi> A little after he ſaith again, <hi>As the Water repreſents the People in the Sacrament, if it were true, that the Bread conſecrated by Miniſters was corporally changed into the Body of Jeſus Chriſt, it muſt alſo neceſſarily follow, that the water which is mingled with it were changed into the blood of the faithful people; for where there is but one ſanctification, there ought to be but one operation; and the Myſtery ſhould be equal where the Reaſon of the Myſtery is the ſame. It is evident there is no corporal change in the water, and by conſequence, there is no corporal change to be expected in the wine. All that is ſaid of the Body of the people repreſented by water, is underſtood ſpiritually; it is then a neceſſary conſequence, that what is ſaid of the blood of Jeſus Chriſt repreſented by the wine, muſt be underſtood ſpiritually. Again. The things which dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer amongſt themſelves, are not one and the ſame thing. The Body of Jeſus Chriſt which was dead and roſe again, and become immortal, doth dye no more, Death has no more deminion over it, it is Eternal, and can no more ſuffer; but that which is celebrated in the Church is temporal and not eternal, and it is corruptible and not incorruptible.</hi> And again; <hi>it muſt then be ſaid, that the body of Jeſus Chriſt, ſuch as it is made in the Church, was incorruptible and eternal. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs it cannot be denied that what is ſo cut into morſels to be eat, changed and corrupted, and that being eat with the teeth, it goes into the Body.</hi> Again, <hi>Now 'tis true that the figure and the reallity are things diſtinct, therefore the body and blood which are celebrated in the Church, are different from the fleſh and blood of the body of Jeſus Chriſt, which it is well known, is glorious ſince his Reſurrection, therefore the body that we celebrate is a pledg and figure.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe words of <hi>Ratramne</hi> or <hi>Bertram,</hi> are ſo clear, that it is won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd the Author of the <hi>Perpetuity</hi> ſhould ſay in the firſt Treatiſe, <hi>p.</hi> 3. that <hi>Bertram</hi> is an obſcure Author, and not evidently favourable to <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> but that <hi>Catholicks</hi> may explain him in a good ſenſe. I cannot tell what to call this Confidence.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>John Erigen,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Joan. Erigena.</note> a Scotch Man, whom the Emperor <hi>Charles</hi> the Bald commanded to write touching the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of the Lord, as he had done alſo to <hi>Ratramne,</hi> which appears by <hi>Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renger</hi>'s Letter to <hi>Richard,</hi> publiſh'd by <hi>Dom Luke D'Achery</hi> in the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:105312:34"/>2d Tome of his Spicileg, was of an opinion contrary to <hi>Paſchaſius,</hi> as is acknowledged by
<note n="*" place="margin">De Euchar.</note> 
                     <hi>Lanfrank;</hi> and <hi>Berenger</hi> in his Epiſte to the ſame <hi>Lanfrank;</hi> and <hi>Hincmar</hi> ſaith of <hi>John Erigen,</hi> that he taught,
<note n="‡" place="margin">
                        <hi>De praedeſt. chap.</hi> 31.</note> 
                     <hi>That the Sacrament of the Altar was not the real Body and Blood of Jeſus Chriſt, but only the Remembrance both of the one and the other:</hi> And <hi>Berenger</hi> writing to <hi>Lanfranc,</hi> ſaith to him, <hi>If you hold</hi> John <hi>for a Heretick, whoſe Judgment we have been inform'd of touching the Sacrament, you muſt alſo hold for Hereticks,</hi> Ambroſe, Chryſoſtom, Auſtin, <hi>not to mention many more.</hi> Nevertheleſs
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>De Geſt. Reg. Angl. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 5.</note> 
                     <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam</hi> of <hi>Malmsbury,
<note n="‖" place="margin">
                           <hi>Annal. per pred. ad</hi> 882.</note> Roger de Hoveden,</hi> and
<note n="‡" place="margin">
                        <hi>Ad An.</hi> 883.</note> 
                     <hi>Matthew</hi> of <hi>Westmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> ſpeak of <hi>John Scot,</hi> as of the greateſt Man of his time; and <hi>Molanus</hi> Profeſſor in Divinity at the Univerſity of <hi>Lovain,</hi> in his Appendix to the Martyrology of <hi>Uſſuart,</hi> at the Letter <hi>J</hi> has left theſe Words engraven, <hi>John Scot, Martyr, tranſlated Dionyſius</hi>'s <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Hierarchy, after which by Authority of the Popes, he was put in the number of the Martyrs of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> To conclude, the <hi>Roman</hi> Martyrology, which we have in our Library, Printed at <hi>Antwerp,</hi> Anno 1586; by order of <hi>Gregory</hi> the 13th, as is ſaid in the Title of the Book, <hi>Martyrologium Romanum Juſſu Gregorii</hi> 13, <hi>editum,</hi> at the 4 of the <hi>Ides</hi> of <hi>November,</hi> makes mention of <hi>John Scot:</hi> It's true, the Author of the 1ſt Diſſertation upon <hi>John Scot,</hi> which the Author of the <hi>Perpetuity</hi> choſe, having placed the ſaid Diſſertation at the end of his 2d Treatiſe, to which he often refers his Readers, has made in the ſame Diſſertation, a Chapter which bears the Title, that <hi>John Scot</hi> was not put into the Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue of Martyrs by the Sacred Authority of Popes, and that his Name is not to be found in any Edition of the <hi>Roman</hi> Martyrology. But it is alſo certain, that the ſame Author, who hath alſo pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh'd the belief of the <hi>Greek</hi> Church touching <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> has inſerted in the end of his Book, a Treatiſe Entituled, A Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation of the Anſwer of a Miniſter of <hi>Charenton,</hi> to the Diſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation which is in the end of Monſieur <hi>Arnauds</hi> Book, concerning the Employments, the Martyrdom, and the Writings of <hi>John Scot,</hi> or <hi>Erigen;</hi> and the laſt Chapter of this Refutation hath this Title, <hi>A ſincere Declaration of the Author touching ſome things he had ſaid in his Diſſertation, the which he ſince confeſſes were not true.</hi> And in <hi>Numb.</hi> 6. of this Chapter, the Author ſaith in theſe Terms, in <hi>Art.</hi> 7. <hi>p.</hi> 25, (he ſpeaks of the 7th <hi>Art.</hi> of the firſt Diſſertation upon <hi>John Scot,</hi> which is at the end of Mr. <hi>Arnauds Perpetuity;</hi>) it is ſaid that 'tis falſe that there was a Martyrology Printed at <hi>Antwerp</hi>
                     <pb n="58" facs="tcp:105312:35"/>by Command of <hi>Gregory</hi> the 13th in the Year 1586. 2dly, That there is not to be found in any <hi>Roman</hi> Martyrology, Printed at <hi>Antwerp</hi> or any where elſe, the Commemoration of <hi>John Scot</hi> on the 4th of the Ides of <hi>November.</hi> It would be ſuperfluous here to relate the Reaſons that they have had, ſo poſitively to deny theſe matters of Fact. It is ſufficient to obſerve, Firſt, That there is a <hi>Roman Martyrology</hi> ſet forth by Order of <hi>Gregory</hi> the 13th, and Printed by <hi>Platin</hi> at <hi>Antwerp</hi> in the Year 1586. 2dly, That there is ſeen in this <hi>Martyrology,</hi> the Commemoration of <hi>John Scot</hi> on the 4th of the <hi>Ides</hi> of <hi>November</hi> in theſe Words, <hi>Eodem Die Sancti Joannis Scoti qui Grafiis puerorum confoſſus, Martyrii Coronam adeptus eſt.</hi> This Author is of good reputation, and doubtleſs was not ignorant of what St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith in ſome of his Works, <hi>That to Lye in a matter of Religion, is meer Blaſphemy.</hi> Nevertheleſs we may obſerve, before proceeding any farther, that if <hi>Scot</hi> had ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced any new Doctrine, he would certainly have been reproved for it by the Church of <hi>Lyons,</hi> by <hi>Prudentius,</hi> by <hi>Florus,</hi> by the Councils of <hi>Valence</hi> and <hi>Langres,</hi> which condemn'd and cenſur'd his Opinions on the Doctrine of <hi>Predeſtination.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>St.
<note place="margin">Prudentius.</note> 
                     <hi>Prudentius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Troyes</hi> in <hi>Champaign,</hi> who aſſiſted at the Councils of <hi>Paris</hi> in the Year 846, of <hi>Tours</hi> in 849, at <hi>Soiſſons</hi> in the Year 853. to whom <hi>Leo</hi> the 4th wrote an honourable Letter, which is to be ſeen in the 6th Tome of the Councils, of the which the Biſhop of <hi>Toul</hi> in the <hi>French</hi> Martyrology on the 7th of <hi>April,</hi> having ſaid, that at <hi>Troys</hi> his Anniverſary is ſolemnized, as of a holy Biſhop and Confeſſor; he alſo makes a magnificent Elegy of him. This holy Biſhop, I ſay, was of the ſame Judgment with <hi>John Scot</hi> in the Subject of the Euchariſt,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Hincmar de Praedeſt. c.</hi> 31.</note> for <hi>Hincmar</hi> Arch Biſhop of <hi>Rhemes,</hi> numbers him with <hi>John Scot,</hi> againſt whom he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves nevertheleſs, that he wrote touching <hi>Predeſtination,</hi> and ſaith, that they both held, <hi>That the Sacraments of the Altar are not the true Body and Blood of our Lord, but only the commemoration of his Body and Blood.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chriſtianus Drutmar</hi> Prieſt and Frier of <hi>Corby,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Chriſtianus Drutmarus.</note> famous for his Learned Works, ſaith <hi>Sigebert</hi> of Illuſtrious Men, as alſo the <hi>Abbot Trythemius;</hi> wrote a Commentary upon St. <hi>Matthew,</hi> about the year 845. It is in the <hi>Bibliotheca Patrum,</hi> Tom. 16: pag. 301.
<q>
                        <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> ſaith <hi>Drutmar, took Bread, becauſe Bread ſtrengthens the heart of man, and doth better fortifie our Body than any other food. He therein eſtabliſhes the Sacrament of his Love; but this propriety
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:105312:35"/>ought much rather to be attributed to the ſpiritual bread which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly ſtrengthens all men, and all creatures, becauſe 'tis by him we live, move, and have our being.</hi> He bleſſed it: <hi>He</hi> bleſſed <hi>it firſt,
<note place="margin">Chriſtianus Druemanes.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe as in his Perſon he bleſſed all Mankind, then afterwards he ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that the bleſſing and power of the Divine and Immortal Nature was truly in that Nature which he had taken from the Virgin</hi> Mary. He broke it: <hi>He</hi> broke <hi>the Bread which was Himſelf, becauſe expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing himſelf willingly to death, he broke and ſhattered the habitation of his Soul, to the end that he might ſatisfie us, according to what himſelf ſaith,</hi> I have power to lay down my life, or to ſave it. <hi>And</hi> he gave it to his Diſciples, ſaying to them, Take and eat, this is my Body. <hi>He</hi> gave <hi>to his Diſciples the Sacrament of his Body for the remiſſion of ſins, and for the keeping of charity, to the end that not forgetting this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, they ſhould always perform this in figure, and that they ſhould not be unmindful of what he was about to do for them.</hi> This is my Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, <hi>that is to ſay,</hi> Sacramentally; <hi>and having taken the</hi> Cup, <hi>he</hi> bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>it, and</hi> gave <hi>it to his Diſciples. As amongſt all things which are neceſſary to preſerve life, Bread and Wine are thoſe that do moſt of all repair and ſtrengthen the weakneſs of nature: It is with great rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that our Saviour was pleas'd in theſe two things to eſtabliſh the Myſtery of his Sacrament; for Wine rejoyces the heart, and increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes blood, therefore it is very fit to</hi> repreſent <hi>the Blood of Jeſus Chriſt, becauſe whatſoever comes from him, rejoyces with true joy, and encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth whatſoever there is of good in us. To conclude, as a perſon that is going a long journey, leaves to thoſe whom he loves, ſome particularpledg of his kindneſs, on condition that they ſhould look daily upon it, to the end that they may retain him always in remembrance; ſo in like manner, God by</hi> ſpiritually changing <hi>the Bread into his Body, and the Wine into his Blood, has commanded us to celebrate this Myſtery, that theſe two things ſhould make us never forget what he hath done for us with his Body and Blood, and keep us from being unthankful and ungrateful for his ſo tender love. Now becauſe water is wont to be mingled with the Sacrament of his Blood, this water repreſents the people for whom Jeſus Chriſt was pleas'd to ſuffer, and the Water is not without the Wine, nor the Wine without the Water, becauſe as he died for us, ſo alſo we ſhould be ready to die for Him, and for our Brethren, that is to ſay, for the Church, therefore there came out of his ſide Water and Blood.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>This paſſage is taken out of the Commentary, where the Author expounds theſe words of the Inſtitution, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> by theſe
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:105312:36"/>other words, That is to ſay, in <hi>Sacrament,</hi> which are words quite contrary to thoſe of <hi>Paſchaſius;</hi> for <hi>Paſchaſius</hi> ſaid in his Letter to <hi>Frudegard,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Chriſtianus Drutmanes.</note> fearing it ſhould be thought that Jeſus ſpake in Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, he ſaid demonſtratively, This is my Body. <hi>Ne putares quia in Sacramento loquebatur (Dominus) &amp;c. demonſtrative dixit, hoc eſt Corpus meum.</hi> So <hi>Drutman</hi> makes a difference 'twixt the <hi>Body</hi> and the <hi>Sacrament</hi> which he eſtabliſhes in the <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine,</hi> which he bleſſed, brake, and gave to his Diſciples; he aſcribes to the <hi>Wine,</hi> only the dignity of <hi>repreſenting the Blood</hi> of Chriſt; and that, to conclude, the <hi>Bread and Wine are pledges of his Love.</hi> Therefore the ſame Author, <hi>chap.</hi> 56. on theſe words, <hi>I will drink no more of this fruit of the Vine, until I drink it new with you in my Father's kingdom; from that very hour of Supper,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>he drank no wine, until he became immortal and incorruptible after his Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Deacon <hi>Florus</hi> wrote about the ſame time,
<note place="margin">Florus Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conus.</note> an expoſition of the <hi>Maſs,</hi> which is mention'd in the <hi>Bibliotheca Patrum,</hi> Tom. 6. pag. 170. he there ſaith, <hi>This Body and this Blood is not gather'd in Ears of Corn, or in cluſters of Grapes; nature doth not give it us, but it is conſecration that makes it myſtical to us: Jeſus Chriſt is eaten when the Creatures of Bread and Wine do paſs to the Sacrament of the Body and Blood, by the ineffable Sanctification of the Holy Ghoſt. He is eaten by parcels in the Sacrament, and remains whole and intire in Heaven, and whole and intire in our Hearts. Again, All that is done in this oblation of the Body and Blood of our Saviour, is a Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, we there ſee one thing, and we underſtand another; what we ſee, hath a corporal ſubſtance; what we underſtand, hath a ſpiritual fruit.</hi> He ſaith, <hi>Jeſus Chriſt ſaith to them, take, eat ye all of this; and ſpeaking of the Cup, The Wine,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>was the Myſtery of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, and he proves it by theſe words, I will drink no more of the fruit of the Vine.</hi> To conclude, Explaining theſe laſt words of the Canon, <hi>By which, O Lord, thou daily makeſt theſe good things for us,</hi> which contain a kind of Thankſgiving, which in the <hi>Latin</hi> Liturgy does follow the Conſecration; he ſufficiently intimates to us, that he did not believe the <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> were changed into the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, ſeeing he ſpeaks of them, as things God had created from the beginning of the world, which he creates every year by propagation and reparation, which he ſanctifies, which he fills with Grace and Heavenly Benediction, the which himſelf expounds to be <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:105312:36"/>
                  <p>See here Nine or Ten Authors, contemporaries with <hi>Paſchaſius,</hi> which are formally contrary to his Doctrine, beſides thoſe which <hi>Paſchaſius</hi> himſelf ſpeaks of in general, in his own Writings.</p>
                  <p>To conclude the Ninth Century, there might be added the manner that <hi>Charles</hi> the Bald, and the Count of <hi>Barcelona</hi> ſigned the Peace, which was done with the <hi>Blood</hi> of the Euchariſt, as is reported by Monſieur <hi>Baluze</hi> in his Notes on <hi>Agabard,</hi> out of <hi>Odo Aribert,</hi> in the year 844. It was in the ſame manner that <hi>Pope The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odore</hi> in the Seventh Century ſigned the condemnation of <hi>Pirrhus</hi> the <hi>Monotholite,</hi> as appears by <hi>Baronius</hi> on the year 648. §. 15.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="century">
                  <head>
                     <hi>That the Fathers of the</hi> TENTH CENTURY <hi>did not believe</hi> Tranſubſtantiation.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ALferick</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> about the year 940. <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">AGE </seg>x.</label> in one of his Sermons to be ſeen in the Fourth Book of <hi>Bedes</hi> Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Hiſtory, <hi>cap.</hi> 24.
<note place="margin">Alferic A. B. Cant.</note> which we have Copied in the Library of St. <hi>Victor,</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">The Expurgat. Index Orders theſe words to be blotted out.</note>
                     <q>
                        <hi>The Euchariſt is not the Body of Jeſus Chriſt cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porally, but ſpiritually; not the Body in which he ſuffered, but the Body of which he ſpake, when conſecrating the Bread and Wine he ſaid, This is my Body, this is my Blood; he adds, the Bread is his Body, juſt as the Manna; and the Wine his Blood, as the water in the Deſart was.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>There is another Sermon cited by ſome under the name of <hi>Wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> others ſay 'tis of <hi>Alfric,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Wolphinus.</note> wherein the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor uſes near the ſame Language. <hi>This Sacrifice,</hi> ſaith he,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Apud <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um de Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianae Eccleſi Succeſſ. &amp; Stat. c.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 54.</note> 
                     <hi>is not the Body of Jeſus Chriſt wherein he ſuffered for us, nor his Blood which he ſhed, but it is ſpiritually made his Body and blood, as the Manna that fell from Heaven, and the Water that ſprang out of the Rock.</hi> Beſides theſe two teſtimonies, which ſhew what was believed of the Sacrament in <hi>England,</hi> there is a Sermon ſeen, which was read every year to the People at <hi>Eaſter,</hi> to keep in their minds the Idea of the Ancient Faith; It is almoſt wholly taken out of <hi>Ratramne; There is great difference,</hi> ſaith this <hi>Homilly, betwixt the Body wherein Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt ſuffered, and the Body which is conſecrated for the Euchariſt; for the Body wherein Jeſus Chriſt ſuffered, was born of the Virgin</hi> Mary, <hi>and was provided with Blood, Bones, Nerves, and Skin, with bodily members, and a reaſonable Soul; but his Spiritual Body, which we call
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:105312:37"/>Euchariſt, is compos'd of ſeveral grains of Wheat, without Blood, without Bones, Nerves, and without a Soul. The Body of Chriſt which ſuffer'd death,
<note place="margin">Saxon Homily.</note> and roſe again, ſhall never dye more, it is eternal and immortal; but the Euchariſt is temporal and not eternal, it is corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and divided into ſundry parcels, ground by the Teeth, and goes along with the other excrements. This Sacrament is a pledge and figure; the Body of Jeſus Chriſt is the Truth it ſelf, we have this pledge Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally until we attain to the Truth, and then the pledg ſhall be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill'd.</hi> And a little lower, <hi>If we conſider the Euchariſt after a corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral manner, we ſee 'tis a changeable and corruptible Creature; but if we conſider the ſpiritual virtue that is in it, we eaſily ſee that life abides in it, and that it gives immortality to thoſe that receive it with Faith. There is great difference betwixt the inviſible virtue of this Holy Sacrament, and the viſible form of its proper Nature. By Nature it is corruptible Bread, and corruptible Wine, but by the virtue of the Word of God, it is truly his Body and Blood, yet not corporally but ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually.</hi> A little below, he explains this change, in ſaying, <hi>Jeſus Chriſt by an inviſible virtue did change the Bread and Wine into his Body and Blood; but 'twas after the ſame manner as he heretofore changed Manna, and the Water that came out of the Rock, into the ſame Body and Blood.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fulcuin</hi> Abbot of the Monaſtry of <hi>Lobes,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Fulcuinus.</note> in the Country of <hi>Liege,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Tom.</hi> 6. <hi>Spicil. de geſtis Abb. Lob. p.</hi> 573.</note> who departed this Life in the year 990. ſpeaking of the <hi>Euchariſtical</hi> Table, ſaith, <hi>That 'tis the Table on which is conſumed the ſacred Body of our Lord,</hi> which not being to be ſaid of the <hi>proper Body,</hi> cannot be underſtood but of the <hi>Bread</hi> which is called <hi>Body,</hi> an expreſſion which in all likelihood this <hi>Abbot</hi> had learn'd of St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> who ſaith, <hi>The Bread made for that uſe, is conſumed in recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Sacrament. That which is ſet on the Table is conſum'd, the holy celebration being ended.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Herriger,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Herriger.</note> Succeſſor to <hi>Fulcuin,</hi> and whom he that continued the Hiſtory of the <hi>Abbots of Lobes,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Idem tom.</hi> 6. <hi>p.</hi> 591.</note> mentions as a man whoſe vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and knowledg was known even to ſtrangers, <hi>he collected,</hi> ſaith this Author, <hi>ſeveral paſſages of Catholick Fathers againſt</hi> Paſchaſius Ratbertus, <hi>touching the Body and Blood of our Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Ancient Cuſtoms of the Monaſtry of <hi>Cluny,</hi> Reprinted by the care of <hi>Dom Luke D'Achery,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Monaſtry. of Cluny.</note> l. 2. ch. 30. ſay, <hi>The outſide of the Challice is carefully rub'd,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Tom.</hi> 4. <hi>in Spec. p.</hi> 146.</note> leſt there ſhould the leaſt drop of the Wine and Water remain; and being conſecrated, it ſhould fall to the ground, and periſh;</hi> by which it appears they believed the <hi>wine</hi> and
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:105312:37"/>
                     <hi>water</hi> ſtill remain'd after Conſcration, for the <hi>true Body</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt cannot periſh. Again, <hi>The Prieſt divides the Host, and puts part of it into the Blood; of one moiety he communicates himſelf,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Cuſtoms of the Monaſtry of</hi> Cluny.</note> and with the other, he communicates the Deacon.</hi> It cannot be ſo ſpoke of the <hi>Body</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt; then after the Prieſt has <hi>broke the Hest,</hi> he puts part of it into the <hi>Cup,</hi> after the uſual manner, two parts on the Patten, and covers both the one and the other with a clean Cloath; but firſt of all, he very carefully rubs the Challice, and ſhakes it with the ſame hand with which he touched it, fearing, leſt that breaking the Bread, there ſhould reſt ſome part of the <hi>Body</hi> of our Lord (which cannot be ſaid of the <hi>true Body</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt;) and elſewhere is preſcrib'd what ſhould be done, <hi>If there chance to remain ever ſo little of the Body of our Saviour,</hi> which is expounded to be a very little Crum, as 'twere indiviſible, and like an Atome. To conclude, treating of the Communion of ſick Folks,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Ch.</hi> 28. <hi>p.</hi> 217.</note> it is obſerv'd that the Body of our Lord is brought from the Church, that it is broke, and that the Prieſt holds on the Challice the part that he is to bring. It muſt needs be, that by the ſenſe of theſe cuſtoms, there muſt be <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> in the Sacrament, that it may be <hi>broken,</hi> and <hi>improperly</hi> called <hi>Body.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ratherius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Verona</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">Ratherius.</note> As to the Corporal ſubſtance which the Communicant doth receive, ſeeing that 'tis I that do now ask the Queſtion, I muſt alſo anſwer my ſelf,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>De Contemp. Canon. port. Spirileg. Tom.</hi> 2.</note> and I thereto yield; for ſeeing that to him that receives worthily, it is the <hi>true Body,</hi> altho one ſees that the <hi>Bread</hi> is the ſame it was before; and <hi>true Blood,</hi> altho the <hi>Wine</hi> is ſeen to be the ſame it was: I confeſs I cannot ſay nor think, what it is to him that doth receive unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily, that is to ſay, that doth not abide in God. Now the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municant, can he receive a corporal Subſtance? Can one ſay, that one ſees that the <hi>Bread</hi> is what 'twas before, if the Communicant receives no Subſtance? It is known on the contrary, that what is ſeen, is not <hi>Bread</hi> nor <hi>Wine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Moreover, <hi>Ratherius</hi> condemning Drunkenneſs, and Exceſs in ſome of his Prieſts, ſaith, that ſome of them ſpew'd before the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar of our Lord upon the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of the Lamb; this can be underſtood only of the Sacrament, which borrows the Name of the thing ſignifi'd, the abuſe whereof reflects on him that inſtituted it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="century">
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:105312:38"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>That the Authors of the</hi> ELEVENTH CENTURY <hi>did not believe</hi> Tranſubſtantiation. <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">AGE </seg>xi.</label>
                  </head>
                  <p>THE Author of the Life of St.
<note place="margin">The Author of the Life of St. <hi>Genulphius.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Genulphius,</hi> who in all probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity lived in the beginning of the <hi>Eleventh Century,</hi> and was publiſhed by <hi>John a Boſco</hi> a <hi>Celeſtin</hi> Frier, relates of this Saint, That from the very Day of his Ordination, he ſpent the reſt of his Life without taſting any Wine, except it was that he receiv'd in the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebration of the holy Sacrament. One would not ſpeak in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Ch.</hi> 6.</note> and believe that there was not <hi>Wine</hi> remaining in the Cup af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Conſecration.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Leutherick</hi> Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Sens,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Leuthericus.</note> who died in the year of our Lord 1032. did not believe <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> becauſe we read of him in the Life of Pope <hi>John</hi> the XVII. or according to others the <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth,</hi> that in this Popes Life, Leutherick <hi>Arch-Biſhop of</hi> Sens, <hi>laid the Foundation and Elements of the Hereſy of</hi> Berenger. Whence it is, that <hi>Helgald</hi> wrote in the Life of King <hi>Robert,</hi> that his Doctrine grew and increaſed in the World;
<note place="margin">In Epiſtola Roberti Regis.</note> 
                     <hi>Creſcebat,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>in Saeculo,</hi> notwithſtanding the threatnings which this Prince made to depoſe him from his Dignity, if he continued to teach it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fulbert,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Fulbertus.</note> Anno Dom. 1007. Biſhop of <hi>Chartres,</hi> and ordain'd by <hi>Leutherick,</hi> did not believe <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> when he ſaid in his 1ſt Epiſtle to <hi>Adeodatus,</hi> That Jeſus Chriſt intending to take up his Body to Heaven,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Bib. pat. tom.</hi> 3.</note> 
                     <hi>left us the Sacrament for to be a pledg of his Body and Blood. That under the viſible form of the Creature, there is a ſecret Virtue that Operates in the holy Solemnities.</hi> That the Divine Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty is diffus'd and ſpread abroad <hi>in that, which before was but a common thing, but being ſanctifi'd by the heavenly Word, it inwardly becomes the Body of Jeſus Christ.</hi> That this is effected by the Holy Spirit that joyns, unites and binds <hi>the Sacrament to the Body of Jeſus Christ,</hi> (compaginante Spiritu ſancto) <hi>that the terreſtrial mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſurpaſſing the Merits of its Nature and Kind, is changed into the ſubſtance of the Body of Jeſus Christ;</hi> that this change is not impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, <hi>no more than that is, which arrives to us by Baptiſm, being changed into the Body of the Church;</hi> not by any priviledg of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but by the purchaſe of Faith; <hi>Non Naturae privilegio, ſed fidei precio,</hi> being the ſame outwardly, and changed inwardly: Of
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:105312:38"/>Servants being become Children, being vile and abject, and all of a ſudden acquiring a new Dignity. <hi>What wonder is it, that he that produced theſe Natures cut of nothing, ſhould convert them into the dignity of a more excellent nature,
<note place="margin">Fulbertus.</note> and make them paſs into the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of his Body?</hi> Now the terms of <hi>pledges</hi> of the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of the Lord, do ſufficiently ſhew that he made a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the <hi>Sacrament</hi> and his <hi>Body;</hi> therefore we ſee before, that <hi>Ratramne</hi> drew the ſame conſequence in ſaying, that which is a Pledg and Image, is diſtinct from that whereof it is an Image and Pledg. Theſe terms of a <hi>ſecret virtue by which it operates,</hi> of the <hi>Sacred Majeſty which it ſpreads abroad,</hi> of the <hi>Holy Spirit that joins and unites,</hi> of the <hi>matter which is advanced to a greater dignity;</hi> and in that he confirms the change of the <hi>Bread,</hi> by that which hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens to Believers in <hi>Baptiſm;</hi> and by that which befel the <hi>Manna</hi> in the <hi>wilderneſs;</hi> as alſo what he farther ſays to <hi>Frudegard</hi> in his 2d Epiſtle of the Communion, as of a thing whereof the Prieſt newly ordained, during 40 days, received a little Portion, <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vam particulam,</hi> which might be taken by morſels, or by bits, <hi>minutatim ſumere,</hi> in that he calls the ſanctified <hi>Bread, Euchariſt,</hi> and that he ſaith, <hi>That the ſanctified Bread is called the true Body of Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> in that he ſaith elſewhere with St. <hi>Auſtin, That he that abides not in Jeſus Chriſt, and in whom Jeſus Chriſt abideth not, doth not eat his Fleſh, nor drink his Blood, though he eats and drinks to his condemnation, the Sacrament of ſo great a thing.</hi> All this ſheweth, that <hi>Berenger</hi> had all reaſon to alledg in his defence the Authority of <hi>Fulbert,</hi> as appears by <hi>Berenger</hi>'s Letter to <hi>Richard,</hi> which Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is printed by <hi>Dom Luke D'Achery</hi> in the 2d Tome of his <hi>Spirileg.</hi> If things be ſo, ſaith <hi>Berenger</hi> to <hi>Richard,</hi> how is it that this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Euchariſt, contain'd in the Writings of Biſhop <hi>Fulbert</hi> of glorious Memory, ſhould come to my knowledg, which ſome indeed imagine to be of this Biſhop, but was indeed taught by St. <hi>Auſtin?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Bernon</hi> Abbot of <hi>Auge,</hi> who about the Year 1030,
<note place="margin">Bernon.</note> wrote a Treatiſe of things concerning the <hi>Maſs,</hi> ſaith in the 1ſt Chapter,
<note place="margin">Bible of the Fath. <hi>Tom.</hi> 10.</note> That Pope <hi>Sergius</hi> commanded to ſing the <hi>Agnus Dei</hi> at the Break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the <hi>Body</hi> of the Lord; now this being not to be underſtood of the proper <hi>Body</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, it muſt be underſtood of the <hi>Sacrament,</hi> which is the figure of his <hi>Body:</hi> They do not ſpeak ſo now, they ſay the <hi>Sign</hi> is <hi>broken,</hi> but they do not ſay the <hi>Body</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt is <hi>broken:</hi> And in the 5th Chap. he ſaith, <hi>That we are
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:105312:39"/>refreſhed with the Wine which is in the Cup, in Type of the Blood of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Bruno</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Angers,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Bruno.</note> was of <hi>Berengers</hi> opinion, as appears by the 3d Tome of the <hi>Bibliotheca Patrum,</hi> p. 319, in a Letter the Biſhop of <hi>Liege</hi> writ to K. <hi>Henry</hi> againſt <hi>Bruno</hi> and <hi>Berenger,</hi> his Arch-Deacon. <hi>Sigebert</hi> in his Chronicle of <hi>Miraeus</hi> his Edition at <hi>Antwerp,</hi> 1608, ſaith, <hi>That many did diſpute for and againſt</hi> Berenger, <hi>by word of mouth, and by Writing.</hi> The Manuſcript of this Chronicle, which is ſeen in Monſieur <hi>d Thous</hi>'s Library ſaith the ſame: As alſo <hi>Conrart de Brunwill, apud Suriun vita Wolphelmi ad ap. Mathew of Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter</hi> on the year 1080, ſaith, That <hi>Berenger</hi> had almoſt corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all <hi>France, Italy,</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> with his Doctrine. <hi>Matthew Paris,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">In Willel. 2. In Willel. <hi>l.</hi> 6.3.</note> and <hi>William of Malmsbury</hi> do affirm, That all <hi>France</hi> was full of his Doctrine. <hi>Thomas Waldenſis</hi> relates the Acts of the Council held under <hi>Gregory</hi> the 7th, wherein there was a more mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate Confeſſion of Faith touching the Sacrament prepared, than that under <hi>Alexander</hi> the 2d, predeceſſor to <hi>Gregory; Berenger</hi> was forced to ſign it,
<note place="margin">Tom 2. Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileg. <hi>p.</hi> 508.</note> after which <hi>Greg.</hi> 7th. gave him Letters of Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation, which <hi>Dom Luke D'Achery,</hi> has cauſed to be printed in one of the Tomes of his Collection. Nevertheleſs it appears by the Acts, and by <hi>Hugh de Flavigny,</hi> in the Chronicle of <hi>Verdun</hi> in the 1ſt Tome of Father <hi>L'Abbes</hi> Bibliotheque, in <hi>an.</hi> 1078, that there were ſeveral in that Aſſembly that maintained <hi>Berengers</hi> Doctrine againſt <hi>Paſchaſius,</hi> that this Arch Deacons Adverſaries knew not how to anſwer his Reaſons, as the Chronicle of Mount <hi>Caſſin</hi> teſtifies, <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 33. And <hi>Sigonius de Regno Itali.</hi> relates <hi>lib.</hi> 9. on the year 1059. That they were forc'd to ſend to the Monaſtry of Mount <hi>Caſſin,</hi> for a learned Frier called <hi>Albert,</hi> whom Pope <hi>Stephen,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">P. <hi>Gregory</hi> 7.</note> ſaith <hi>Sigonius,</hi> made Cardinal Deacon, who being come, and not able to anſwer <hi>Berengers</hi> Arguments, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a weeks time to conſider of them; neither was Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the 7th himſelf well ſatisfied with what was urged againſt <hi>Berenger,</hi> ſeeing that Cardinal <hi>Bernon,</hi> in the life of <hi>Hildebrand,</hi> and the Abbot of <hi>Ursberg</hi> in the year 1080, do write, That <hi>Gregory</hi> the 7th, wavering in the Faith, caus'd a Faſt to be kept by his Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals, that it might be diſcover'd whether the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> or <hi>Berenger</hi> were in the beſt opinion touching the <hi>Body</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt in the Sacrament. One argument that <hi>Gregory</hi> the 7th, was not very contrary to <hi>Berenger,</hi> is, that the Abbot of <hi>Ursberg,</hi> and <hi>Aventin,</hi> that has it from <hi>Otto Fraxinenſis,</hi> relate on the year
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:105312:39"/>1080, that thirty Biſhops and Lords being aſſembled <hi>apud Brixiam Nomicam</hi> did depoſe <hi>Gregory</hi> the 7th, amongſt other things, for being a Diſciple of <hi>Berengers.</hi> Before I end my Diſcourſe of <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renger,</hi> it is neceſſary to obſerve,
<note place="margin">Bruno.</note> that the Confeſſion that was extorted from him, is not maintainable, ſeeing that, as is related by <hi>Lanfranc</hi> and <hi>Alger,</hi> it is therein ſaid,
<note place="margin">1. 1. <hi>c.</hi> 19.</note> that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt not only in Sacrament, but alſo in reality, is touched and broken by the Teeth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Theophylact</hi> Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Bulgary</hi> ſaid in his time, That God,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Theophylact. In Marcum. c.</hi> 14.</note> condeſcending to our infirmity, <hi>doth preſerve the Species of Bread and Wine, and changes them into the virtue of the Body and Blood of Chriſt.</hi> Alſo in his time the <hi>Greeks</hi> did not believe <hi>Tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In all probability <hi>Nicetas Pectoratus</hi> did not believe it,
<note place="margin">Nicetas Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoratus.</note> ſeeing Cardinal <hi>Humbert</hi> whom Pope <hi>Leo</hi> the 9th ſent to them, upbraids him, <hi>Perfidious Stercoraniſt,</hi> ſays he to him,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Humber. Tom.</hi> 4. <hi>Bibl. of the Patr.</hi> Edit. <hi>ult.</hi> 245.</note> 
                     <hi>you think that the Partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of the Body and Blood of our Lord breaks the Faſts of Lent, and other holy Faſts, believing that the Heavenly, as well as the terreſtrial Food, is caſt out into the Draft, by the ſordid and ſtinking way of the Belly.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Alger de Sacram.</hi> l. 2. <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>Tom.</hi> 6. of the Fathers, <hi>lib.</hi> and the Jeſuit <hi>Cellot,</hi> in <hi>Append. Miſcel. Opuſc.</hi> 7. <hi>p.</hi> 564. do frequently impute this Error to the <hi>Greeks.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Author of the Chronicle <hi>Malleacenſis,</hi> on the year 1083, obſerves in the Monaſtry <hi>(Cormoriacenſi),</hi> That there was a Friar called <hi>Literius,</hi> of ſuch great abſtinence, <hi>that for Ten years time, he drank neither Wine nor VVater, but what he received in the Sacrament;</hi> of neceſſity then, what one drinks in the Euchariſt, muſt be <hi>true Wine,</hi> and <hi>true Water.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="century">
                  <head>
                     <hi>That the Authors of the</hi> TWELFTH CENTURY <hi>did not believe</hi> Tranſubſtantiation.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>HOnorius</hi> Prieſt and Theologal of the Church of <hi>Rutan,</hi> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">AGE </seg>xii.</label> did not believe <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> ſeeing <hi>Thomas Waldenſis, Tom.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 90. ſaith,
<note place="margin">Honorius.</note> That this <hi>Theologal</hi> was of the Sect of the <hi>Bread-eaters</hi> of <hi>Rabanus, de Secta Panitarum Rabani;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>An.</hi> 1120. <hi>In Gemma A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 111:</note> and <hi>Honorius</hi> ſaith with <hi>Raban,</hi> that the Sacrament which is received with the Mouth, is
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:105312:40"/>converted into bodily food, but the virtue of the Sacrament is that whereby the inward Man is fed and ſatisfied. He ſaith alſo, That the Hoſt is broken,
<note place="margin">Honorius.</note> becauſe the Bread of Angels was broken for us upon the Croſs
<note n="‡" place="margin">Ib. c. 63.</note>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Ib. c. 64.</note> That the Biſhop bites one piece, that he divides it in parts, that it is not received whole, but broke in three parts,
<note n="‖" place="margin">Ibid c. 65.</note> that when 'tis put in the Wine, it is ſhewed that the Soul of our Lord return'd to his Body, and he calls that which is broke, the Body of the Lord; then he obſerves, that the Sub-Deacon receives from the Deacon the Body of our Saviour, and that he carries it to the Prieſts to divide it to the People; all this can only be underſtood of the <hi>Bread,</hi> which is improperly called the <hi>Body.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Rupert</hi> Abbot of <hi>Duits,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rupertus.</note> near <hi>Cologne,</hi> upon <hi>Exodus, l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 10. ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>A.</hi> 1111.</note> That the Holy Ghoſt doth not deſtroy the <hi>Subſtance</hi> of <hi>Bread,</hi> as he did not deſtroy the <hi>human Nature,</hi> when he joined it to the <hi>Word;</hi> and in his 6th Book on St. <hi>John,</hi> of the <hi>Paris</hi> Edition, in the year 1638, he ſaith, That as the Word was made Fleſh, not being changed into Fleſh, but in aſſuming Fleſh, ſo alſo the Word made Fleſh, is made <hi>viſible Bread,</hi> not being changed into <hi>Bread,</hi> but taking and transferring the <hi>Bread</hi> into the Unity of his Perſon.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>De Scriptor. Eccleſ. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 11. <hi>&amp;</hi> 15.</note> We will ſay no more of this Author, becauſe <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min</hi> and ſeveral others, do freely confeſs that <hi>Rupert</hi> did not believe <hi>Tranſubſtantiation;</hi> alſo <hi>Honorius</hi> of <hi>Autur</hi> gives him extraordinary Commendations,
<note place="margin">De Script. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ</note> ſaying, That <hi>Rupert</hi> illuminated with a Viſion of the Holy Ghoſt, explained almoſt all the Holy Scriptures in an admirable ſtile.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Zonaras</hi> in the <hi>Eaſt</hi> did not believe <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Zonaras.</note> ſeeing he ſaith of the Euchariſt,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Tom</hi> 6. <hi>Cyr. Alex in No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tic vuicani ad lib. adverſ. An. hrepom. Zonar. Ep.</hi> 2.</note> 
                     <hi>That it is a Shew-Bread which is ſubject to corruption, and which is eat and ground with the Teeth. Panis pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitionis corruptionieſt obnexius, ut pote caro exiſtens vere Chriſti, &amp; ſecatur dentibus noſtris, &amp; molitur.</hi> So that he was of the Opinion of <hi>Damaſcen</hi> and <hi>Rupert.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Abbot <hi>Francus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Francus.</note> in all likelihood, Abbot of <hi>Lobbes,</hi> did not approve the opinion of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> ſeeing the <hi>Centuriators</hi> of <hi>Magdebourgh</hi> obſerve, that he had no right judgment of the Lords Supper, aſſerting that the <hi>true Body</hi> of Chriſt was not in the Holy Sacrament.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Amalaricus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Chartres</hi> in the year 1207,
<note place="margin">Amalaricus.</note> a man of great Reputation for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Knowledg and Wiſdom, ſaith <hi>Gaugwin</hi> in his 6th Book of the Hiſtory of <hi>France,</hi> in the Reign of <hi>Philip</hi> the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt,</hi>
                     <pb n="69" facs="tcp:105312:40"/>amongſt other things, denied <hi>Tranſubſtantiation.
<note place="margin">In <hi>Catal.</hi> in <hi>Almar.</hi> contra Haereſ. verb. Euch. 4.</note> Bernard</hi> of <hi>Luxemburg, Prateolus,</hi> and <hi>Alphonſus alaſtro,</hi> report the ſame of <hi>Amaury,</hi> as alſo <hi>Genebrard</hi> in his Chronicle, lib. 4. <hi>Anno.</hi> 1215.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="century">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Opinions of Authors of the</hi> THIRTEENTH CENTURY, <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">AGE </seg>xiii.</label> 
                     <hi>and afterwards, touching</hi> Tranſubſtantion.</head>
                  <p>IT's true, Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the 3d. did condemn this <hi>Amaury</hi> at the Council of <hi>Lateran,</hi> after his death, in the year 1215. but 'tis not ſaid wherefore; and what was tranſacted in this Council, deſerves not to be much regarded, if it be conſider'd after what manner things were there tranſacted. The Pope, who then pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſided, was a man full of vain glory and ambition; <hi>Mathew Paris</hi> and <hi>Mathew of Weſtminſter</hi> intimate ſo much of him, and that the liberty of voting and ſpeaking was denied to the Prelates of the Aſſembly, for they were not ſeen to propoſe, nor deliberate, nor adviſe, nor prepare any of the Conſtitutions which were there in great numbers; but they were preſented to the Council ready drawn up, it not appearing that the advice of the Aſſembly was taken on each of them, as is uſually practis'd in all free and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Councils. <hi>Mathew Paris,</hi> on the year 1215. ſpeaks in theſe terms, Every one being Aſſembled in the place aboveſaid, and each having according to the cuſtom of General Councils, taken their place, the Pope having firſt made an Exhortatory Sermon, there was read in full Council Sixty Articles; which were liked by ſome, and diſliked by others.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Godfry,</hi> a Frier of St. <hi>Pantalion</hi> at <hi>Cologne,</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ad Ann.</hi> 1215.</note> there was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing worth the remembrance done at this Council, only that the Eaſtern Church ſubmitted to the Weſtern, which before was never known. <hi>Nauclerus,</hi> and <hi>Platina,</hi> in the Life of <hi>Innocent</hi> the 3d. affirm the ſame, for they mark, that ſeveral things were there propos'd, but that nothing was clearly determin'd. And Kings and Princes have no Reaſon to allow of this Council, becauſe in the 3d Chap. of the ſaid Council, power is given to the Pope to deprive Princes and Lords of their Lands, and to give them to others.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Guy le Gros</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Narbonne,</hi> in the year 1268. did not believe <hi>Tranſubſtantiation;</hi> for being at <hi>Rome,</hi> and diſcovering his
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:105312:41"/>mind to a certain Doctor, being return'd to <hi>Narbonne,</hi> Pope <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> the IV. wrote him a Letter, telling him that a certain Doctor inform'd him, that diſcourſing with him, he held that the Body of Chriſt was not eſſentially in the Sacrament, and no otherwiſe than as the thing ſignified is in the Sign; and that he ſaid alſo this Opinion was common at <hi>Paris.</hi> This appears by the Regiſter'd Manuſcript of the Letters of <hi>Clement</hi> the IV. And to ſhew that the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Narbonne</hi> ſaid this Doctrine was very frequent at <hi>Paris;</hi> we find that two years after, that is to ſay, in the year 1270. which was in the year St. <hi>Lewis</hi> died; <hi>Stephen</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Paris,</hi> by advice of ſome Doctors in Divinity, condemned thoſe which held, that God cannot make an Accident to be without a Subject, becauſe it is of its Eſſence to be actually in its Subject. 2ly, That the Accident without a Subject, is not evident, unleſs it be equivocal. 3ly, That to make the Accident ſubſiſt without its Subject, as we think it does in the Euchariſt, is a thing impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, and implies a Contradiction. 4ly, That God cannot make the Accident be without its Subject, neither that it ſhould have ſeveral Dimenſions. Which Maxims being inconſiſtent with <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation,</hi> doth plainly ſhew, that even at that time, Men were divided on the Subject of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation.</hi> One <hi>William,</hi> ſaith the Frier <hi>Walſingham,</hi> in the Life of <hi>Richard</hi> the 2d, King of <hi>England,</hi> on the year 1381. Preached at <hi>Leiceſter</hi> on <hi>Palm-Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, That the Sacrament of the Altar is real Bread after Conſecration;</hi> and that the Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln</hi> going to puniſh him for it, the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple appearing concern'd for him, made the Biſhop not dare do any thing againſt him, which doth plainly ſhew, that in that time the Doctrine of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> had not taken any deep root in the minds of the People.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reginald Peacock</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Chicheſter</hi> in <hi>England,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>In Richard.</hi> 2. <hi>Anno</hi> 1282.</note> in the year 1457, did not hold <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> ſeeing <hi>Baleus</hi> reports on the Credit of <hi>Thomas Gaſconius</hi> and <hi>Leland,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Tom.</hi> 2. <hi>Ch.</hi> 19.</note> that he had no ſound thoughts touching the Euchariſt, and that he aſſerted the Doctrine of <hi>Wickliff.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now the Doctrine of <hi>Wickliff,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Tho. Waldenſ. in Epiſt. ad Mart.</hi> 5.</note> as is related by this Frier <hi>Walſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Waldenſis,</hi> was, That after Conſecration by the Prieſt in the <hi>Maſs,</hi> there remains <hi>true Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine,</hi> ſuch as they were before; nevertheleſs, ſaith <hi>Walſingham,</hi> the Lords and Nobles of the Land favour'd <hi>Wickliff;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>In Rich.</hi> 2.</note> which ſhews plainly, that the belief of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> was not generally received.</p>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:105312:41"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Guy</hi> of <hi>Cluvigny,</hi> Doctor in Divinity, of the Order of <hi>Carmelites,</hi> and Reader of the Sacred <hi>Palace,</hi> did not hold <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> but held the Opinion of <hi>Rupert de Duits,</hi> to wit, the Impanation; and ſaid, That this Opinion was ſo agreeable to him, that if he were <hi>Pope,</hi> he would eſtabliſh it.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Tom.</hi> 2. <hi>Ch.</hi> 64.</note> 
                     <hi>Thomas Waldenſis</hi> reports the ſame thing, having receiv'd it from <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Paris.</hi> It's certain that <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Paris</hi> teacheth ſo in his Manuſcript Treatiſe in the Library of St. <hi>Victor,</hi> having for its Title, <hi>Determinatio fratris Joannis de Pariſiis Praedicatoris de modo exiſtendi Corpus Chriſti in Sacramento Altaris alio quam ſit ille quem tenet Eccleſia.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſame <hi>John de Paris</hi> wrote the Treatiſe above mention'd, about the year 1300. he was a <hi>Jacobin,</hi> and Doctor of the <hi>Sorbon;</hi> he held that the Euchariſt is the Body of Chriſt, as <hi>Rupert de Duits,</hi> and <hi>Guy</hi> of <hi>Cluvigny</hi> did, to wit, by Aſſumption, Jeſus Chriſt ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving taken the Bread into the Unity of his <hi>Suppoſitum,</hi> as he took the human Nature into the Unity of his Perſon. And towards the end of the Manuſcript it is ſaid, That the faculty thought fit, that the manner of explaining the Euchariſt, by <hi>Aſſumption</hi> of the <hi>Bread,</hi> or by <hi>Converſion,</hi> was a <hi>probable Opinion; but that neither the one nor the other was decided as a matter of Faith; and that whoever ſaid otherwiſe, did not ſay well,</hi> and run the riſque of Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. <hi>In praeſentia Collegii Magiſtrorum in Theologia dictum eſt;</hi> (ſays the end of the Manuſcript) <hi>utrumque modum ponendi Corpus Chriſti eſſe in Altari tenet pro Opinioni probabili, &amp; approbat utrumque per.—Et per dicta Sanctorum. Dicit tamen quod nullus eſt determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus per Eccleſiam, &amp; idcirco nullus cadit ſub fide, &amp; ſi aliter dixiſſet, minus bene dixiſſet, &amp; qui aliter dicunt minus bene dicunt, &amp; qui de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminate aſſereret alterum praeciſe cadere ſub fide incurreret ſententiam, Canonis vel Anathematis.</hi> Thomas Waldenſis <hi>attributes this Opinion to</hi> John de Paris.</p>
                  <p>There is commonly found in the Library of the <hi>Franciſcan</hi> Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, a Book called the <hi>Poor's Reckoning,</hi> writ by one, called <hi>De Goris,</hi> a Doctor of <hi>Tholouſe,</hi> and Native of <hi>Arragon;</hi> he Dedicated his Book to <hi>Alphonſus</hi> of <hi>Arragon</hi> Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Sarragoſſa.</hi> He charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <hi>John de Paris</hi> with the Opinion of the <hi>Impanation,</hi> and doth not condemn it. It is on the 4th Book of Sentences, <hi>Dist.</hi> 11. <hi>q.</hi> 3. The Continuator of <hi>VVilliam de Nangis,</hi> his Manuſcript Chronicle in the Library of St. <hi>German de Pres,</hi> that <hi>John de Paris</hi> is ſtiled, Doctor of great Knowledg and Learning.
<note n="*" place="margin">De Script. Eccleſiaſt.</note> 
                     <hi>Trythemius</hi> and <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuar.
<note n="‡" place="margin">Auctuan.</note> le Mire,</hi> give him alſo the ſame Epithets.</p>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:105312:42"/>
                  <p>I obſerve, That in this Manuſcript, <hi>John de Paris</hi> to confirm his Opinion, makes uſe of the Authority of the <hi>Maſter</hi> of the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, in 4th <hi>Sent. Dist.</hi> 21. (I take it to be <hi>Dist.</hi> 12.) as if the Maſter of the Sentences ſhould there ſay, That the <hi>Impanation</hi> is a <hi>probable Opinion.</hi> He alſo cites to the ſame purpoſe, <hi>Dominus Hoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enſem,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Super Corpus juris extra de ſumma Trinit. &amp; fide Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thol. C. firmiter Oredimus, &amp; de Celebratione Miſſarum, cap. cum. Marta.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Albertus Magnus</hi> expounds the Euchariſt by <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> but he ſaith, <hi>ſalvo Meliori judicio,</hi> which ſhews that he did not believe it as of Faith.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Durandus</hi> of St. <hi>Porcien</hi> taught, that the ſubſtance of <hi>Bread</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main'd, but that the form was chang'd.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Durand</hi> in the 4. Sent. diſt. 10. q. 13. ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>In</hi> 4. <hi>diſt.</hi> 11. <hi>Q.</hi> 3.</note> That in his time there were Catholick Doctors which taught, the <hi>Bread</hi> remain'd in the Euchariſt, and did prove it by the Confeſſion which <hi>Berenger</hi> was forc'd to make, affirming this opinion was not condemn'd.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cornelius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Bitonte,</hi> declared againſt <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> in the Council of <hi>Trent; Canus</hi> Locor. Theol. l. 12. c. 13.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Dominicus Bannes</hi> taught,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Diſp</hi> 49. <hi>Sect.</hi> 4. <hi>Diſp.</hi> 9. <hi>Sect.</hi> 8.</note> that the Exiſtence of <hi>Bread</hi> doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main, that ſo the <hi>Accidents of Bread and Wine</hi> may remain by this Exiſtence. At leaſt <hi>Suarez</hi> and <hi>Mairat</hi> attribute this oppinion to him.</p>
                  <p>To all which, if we add the Doctors that we have mention'd in our firſt Part, that could not ſpeak of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> but as of a New Doctrine, and which could not be proved by the Scriptures, without intimating that they were not at all ſatisfied with it; we ſhall ſee it plainly appears, that we cannot apply to the Doctrine of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> the Rule of <hi>Vincentius Lirrinenſis,</hi> which is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd to us by the Biſhops of <hi>France.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="conclusion">
                  <head>The CONCLUSION.</head>
                  <p>WHerefore the Biſhops are humbly deſired, That they would not continue to exerciſe ſo much rigor and ſeverity againſt the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> who having yielded farther than they well could with a ſafe Conſcience, to obey the Kings Orders, yet can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not in any wiſe reſolve to make any profeſſion of the Doctrine of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> it appearing that they oppoſe it only for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſake, and as being contrary to the very Rule offered to them by the Biſhops themſelves.</p>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:105312:42"/>
                  <p>If St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> could ſay,
<note place="margin">Epiſt. 162.</note> That thoſe ought not to be eſteemed <hi>Hereticks</hi> that with an honeſt mind maintained the Errors of their Anceſtors, and are ready to relinquiſh them when they are better inform'd of the Truth; how much greater Reaſon is there to bear with People who do ſhew by the very confeſſion of <hi>Romiſh</hi> Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Doctors, That the Doctrine of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> is a new in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention, and by conſequence, that it ought not to be impoſed as an <hi>Article</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> by the very Rule laid down by the Biſhops of <hi>France.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>No reaſonable perſon can find any queſtion in matter of Religion whereto this Rule of St. <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s can be more juſtly applied. For if it he not obſerv'd in this controverſy of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> there will never be any thing found that it may be uſed in.</p>
                  <p>If then ſuch Perſons are not <hi>Hereticks</hi> for ſeeking the Truth, and that they think 'tis their duty to ſeek it; that they are of the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Catholick Doctors, and that they obſerve the Rule pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by the Biſhops; it is no way ſafe to perſecute them to that degree of violence, to make them believe that which is contrary to the Rule which is laid down; and therefore, what is ſaid by St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi> on <hi>Pſalm</hi> 54. ſhould ſeriouſly be conſider'd, <hi>Plerumque cum tibi videris Odiſſe inimicum, fratrum odiſti, &amp; neſcis.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="addenda">
            <head>ADDENDA.</head>
            <p>THeſe words in their place, are alſo to be added.
<note place="margin">The Gloſs on the Canon <hi>hoc eſt,</hi> in the 2. diſt. of the Conſecrat.</note> 
               <hi>The heavenly Sacrament which truly repreſents the fleſh of Jeſus Chriſt, is called the Body of Chriſt, but improperly; and nevertheleſs it is ſo called after its manner, not according to the truth of the thing, but by a ſignificant Myſtery; ſo that the meaning is, 'tis called the Body of Jeſus Chriſt, that is to ſay, that the Body is thereby ſignified.</hi> And alſo the Text of the Canon taken out of St. <hi>Auſtin;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>De conſec.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 48.</note> Sicut Caeleſtis panis qui Chriſti caro eſt, ſuo modo vocatur Corpus Chriſti, cum re vera ſit Sacramentum Corporis Chriſti, illius videlicet quod viſibile, palpabile, mortale, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:105312:43"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Books lately Printed for</hi> Richard Chiſwell.</head>
            <p>A Diſſertation concerning the Government of the <hi>Ancient Church;</hi> more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly of the Encroachments of the <hi>Biſhops of Rome</hi> upon other <hi>Sees.</hi> By <hi>WILLIAM CAVE</hi> D. D. <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Serjeant's</hi> [Sure Footing in Chriſtianity] concerning the Rule of Faith: With ſome other Diſcourſes. By <hi>WILLIAM FALKNER,</hi> D. D. 4<hi rend="sup">to.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Vindication of the Ordinations of the <hi>Church of England;</hi> in Anſwer to a <hi>Paper</hi> written by one of the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> to prove the Nullity of our Orders. By <hi>GILBERT B<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RNET,</hi> D. D. <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Abridgment of the Hiſtory of the Reformation of the <hi>Church of England.</hi> By <hi>G. B<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RNET,</hi> D. D. <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The APOLOGY of the <hi>Church of England;</hi> and an Epiſtle to one Signior <hi>Scipio,</hi> a <hi>Venetian</hi> Gentleman, concerning the Council of <hi>Trent.</hi> Written <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in Latin, by the Right Reverend Father in God. <hi>JOHN JEWEL,</hi> Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Salisbury:</hi> Made Engliſh by a Perſon of Quality. To which is added, The Life of the ſaid Biſhop, Collected and written by the ſame Hand. <hi>Octa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Life of <hi>WILLIAM BEDEL,</hi> D. D. Biſhop of <hi>Kilmore</hi> in <hi>Ireland.</hi> To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with <hi>Certain letters</hi> which paſſed betwixt him and <hi>James. Waddeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> (a late Penſioner of the Holy Inquiſition of <hi>Sevil</hi>) in Matter of Religion, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the General Motives to the <hi>Roman Obedience. Octavo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Decree made at <hi>ROME</hi> the 2d of <hi>March,</hi> 1679. condemning ſome Opinions of the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> and other <hi>Caſuiſts. Quarto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Diſcourſe concerning the Neceſſity of Reformation, with reſpect to the Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors and Corruptions of the <hi>Church of Rome. Quarto.</hi> Firſt and Second Parts.</p>
            <p>A Diſcourſe concerning the Celebration of Divine Service in an Unknown Tongue. <hi>Quarto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Papiſt not Miſrepreſented by Proteſtants. Being a Reply to the Reflections upon the Anſwer to [A Papiſt Miſrepreſented and Repreſented]. <hi>Quarto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Expoſition of the Doctrine of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> in the ſeveral Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles propoſed by the late Biſhop of <hi>CONDOM,</hi> [in his Expoſition of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the <hi>Catholick Church]. Quarto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Defence of the Expoſition of the Doctrine of the <hi>Church of England;</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Exceptions of Monſieur de <hi>Meaux,</hi> late Biſhop of <hi>Condom,</hi> and his Vindicator. <hi>Quarto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A <hi>CATECHISM</hi> explaining the Doctrines and Practices of the <hi>Church of Rome.</hi> With an Anſwer thereunto. By a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> of the <hi>Church of England.</hi> 8vo.</p>
            <p>A Papiſt Repreſented and not Miſrepreſented, being an Anſwer to the Firſt, Second, Fifth and Sixth Sheets of the Second Part of the [Papiſt Miſrepreſented and Repreſented]; and for a further Vindication of the <hi>CATECHISM,</hi> truly repreſenting the Doctrines and Practices of the <hi>Church of Rome. Quarto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Lay-Chriſtian</hi>'s Obligation to read the Holy Scriptures. <hi>Quarto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Plain Man</hi>'s Reply to the <hi>Catholick Miſſionaries.</hi> 24<hi rend="sup">o.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Anſwer to <hi>THREE PAPERS</hi> lately printed, concerning the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the <hi>Catholick Church</hi> in Matters of Faith, and the Reformation of the <hi>Church of England. Quarto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Vindication of the Anſwer to THREE PAPERS concerning the Unity and Authority of the <hi>Catholick Church,</hi> and the Reformation of the <hi>Church of England. Quarto.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
